^ ***g16 pp. 10-11 How to Deal With Change***

HELP FOR THE FAMILY | YOUNG PEOPLE

How to Deal With Change

THE CHALLENGE

Your dad’s job requires that your family relocate.

Your best friend is moving far away.

Your older sibling is leaving home to get married.

How well would you adapt to such changes?

A tree that can bend with the wind is more likely to survive a storm. Like that tree, you can learn to “bend” with changes over which you have little or no control. Before discussing how you can do that, though, consider a few things you should know about change.

WHAT YOU SHOULD KNOW

Change is inevitable. The Bible states a fundamental truth about humans: “Unexpected events overtake them all.” (Ecclesiastes 9:11) Sooner or later, you will be confronted with the reality of those words. Of course, not all unexpected events are bad. And some changes that at first seem to be bad might turn out to be advantageous. Nevertheless, most people thrive on routine, while change—whether good or bad—rattles their comfort zone.

Change can be particularly stressful for adolescents. Why? “You’re already going through internal changes,” explains a young man named Alex.* “External changes just add to the stress.”

Here is another reason: When adults face a change, they can refer to their personal ‘book of experience’ to see how they dealt with similar situations in the past. But young people have less history on which to draw.

You can learn to adapt. Resilience is the ability to recover from misfortune or adjust to change. A resilient person can not only endure a new circumstance but also look at a seeming obstacle and see an opportunity in it. Resilient teens are less likely to turn to drugs or alcohol when they feel overwhelmed.

WHAT YOU CAN DO

Accept reality. No doubt you would like to have total control of your life, but that is simply not possible. Friends will move away or marry; siblings will grow up and leave home; circumstances may force your family to move, leaving behind friends and all that is familiar. It is better to accept reality than to let negative thoughts overwhelm you.—Bible principle: Ecclesiastes 7:10.

Look ahead. Focusing on the past is like driving on a highway with your eyes fixed on the rearview mirror. An occasional glance is beneficial, but you really need to concentrate on the road ahead. The same is true when you are confronted with change. Try to keep your eyes fixed on the future. (Proverbs 4:25) For example, what goal could you set for the next month, or six months?

Focus on the positive. “Resilience is about attitude,” says a young woman named Laura. “Find positive aspects of the circumstance you are in.” Can you list at least one advantage that your new circumstance offers?—Bible principle: Ecclesiastes 6:9.

A young woman named Victoria recalls that in her teen years, all her close friends moved away. “I felt so lonely, and I wished that everything could have stayed the way it was,” she says. “But looking back, that’s when I really started to grow. I came to realize that growth requires change. That’s also when I started seeing possibilities for new friendships that were all around me.”—Bible principle: Proverbs 27:10.

Focusing on the past is like driving on a highway with your eyes fixed on the rearview mirror

Do things for others. The Bible says: “Look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.” (Philippians 2:4) A good antidote to your own challenge is helping others with theirs. Anna, 17, says: “As I grew older, I came to realize that when I could help someone else who might be going through a similar situation—or a worse one—it was rewarding!”

^ par. 11 Some names in this article have been changed.

KEY SCRIPTURES

“Do not say, ‘Why were the former days better than these?’”—Ecclesiastes 7:10.

“Better to enjoy what the eyes see than to wander after one’s desires.”—Ecclesiastes 6:9.

“Better is a neighbor nearby than a brother far away.”—Proverbs 27:10.

JUAN

“Young people can develop resilience by analyzing the situation they are coping with and realizing that change is a part of life. The quicker a person accepts that reality, the easier it will be to move on with life. Things do get better.”

CARISSA

“Once a difficulty has passed, I try not to relive it over and over in my mind. I just move on to the next challenge in life. Part of being resilient, I believe, is looking ahead rather than looking behind.”

^ (Eccl. 9:11) I have seen something further under the sun, that the swift do not always win the race, nor do the mighty win the battle, nor do the wise always have the food, nor do the intelligent always have the riches, nor do those with knowledge always have success, because time and unexpected events* overtake them all.

Or “unforeseen occurrence.”

^ (Eccl. 7:10) Do not say, “Why were the former days better than these?” for it is not out of wisdom that you ask this.

^ (Prov. 4:25) Your eyes should look straight ahead, Yes, fix your gaze* straight ahead of you.

Or “beaming eyes.”

^ (Eccl. 6:9) Better to enjoy what the eyes see than to wander after one’s desires.* This too is futility, a chasing after the wind.

Or “than the walking about of the soul.”

^ (Prov. 27:10) Do not forsake your friend or your father’s friend, And do not enter your own brother’s house on the day of your disaster; Better is a neighbor nearby than a brother far away.

^ (Phil. 2:4) as you look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.

^ (Eccl. 7:10) Do not say, “Why were the former days better than these?” for it is not out of wisdom that you ask this.

^ (Eccl. 6:9) Better to enjoy what the eyes see than to wander after one’s desires.* This too is futility, a chasing after the wind.

Or “than the walking about of the soul.”

^ (Prov. 27:10) Do not forsake your friend or your father’s friend, And do not enter your own brother’s house on the day of your disaster; Better is a neighbor nearby than a brother far away.

^ ***ll pp. 6-7 Who Is the True God?***

Part 2

Who Is the True God?

There is only one true God, and his name is Jehovah. ([Psalm 83:18]) He is a Spirit; we cannot see him. He loves us and wants us to love him in return. He also wants us to love other people. (Matthew 22:35-40) He is the Supreme One, the Creator of all things.

The first of God’s creations was a mighty spirit person who later came to be known as Jesus Christ. Jehovah also created the angels.

Jehovah created everything in heaven . . . and on earth. Revelation 4:11

Jehovah God created the stars as well as the earth and all that is on it.—[Genesis 1:1].

He formed Adam, the first man, from the dust of the ground.—[Genesis 2:7].

Why should we honor Jehovah?—[Isaiah 42:5].

What are some of God’s qualities?—[Exodus 34:6].

^ (Ps. 83:18) May people know that you, whose name is Jehovah, You alone are the Most High over all the earth.

^ (Matt. 22:35-40) And one of them, versed in the Law, tested him by asking: 36 “Teacher, which is the greatest commandment in the Law?” 37 He said to him: “‘You must love Jehovah* your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul* and with your whole mind.’ 38 This is the greatest and first commandment. 39 The second, like it, is this: ‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’ 40 On these two commandments the whole Law hangs, and the Prophets.”

See App. A5.

See Glossary.

^ (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

^ (Gen. 1:1) In the beginning God created the heavens and the earth.

^ (Gen. 2:7) And Jehovah God went on to form the man out of dust from the ground and to blow into his nostrils the breath of life, and the man became a living person.*

Or “soul.” Hebrew, neʹphesh, which literally means “a breathing creature.” See Glossary.

^ (Isa. 42:5) This is what the true God, Jehovah, says, The Creator of the heavens and the Grand One who stretched them out, The One who spread out the earth and its produce, The One who gives breath to the people on it And spirit to those who walk on it:

^ (Ex. 34:6) Jehovah was passing before him and declaring: “Jehovah, Jehovah, a God merciful and compassionate,* slow to anger and abundant in loyal love* and truth,*

Or “gracious.”

Or “loving-kindness.”

Or “faithfulness.”

^ (Pss. 87:0-91:16) Of the sons of Korʹah. A melody. A song. 87 His city’s foundation is in the holy mountains.  2 Jehovah loves the gates of Zion More than all the tents of Jacob.  3 Glorious things are being said about you, O city of the true God. (Selah)  4 I will count Raʹhab and Babylon among those who know* me; Here are Phi·lisʹti·a and Tyre, together with Cush. It will be said: “This is one who was born there.”  5 And about Zion it will be said: “Each and every one was born in her.” And the Most High will firmly establish her.  6 Jehovah will declare, when recording the peoples: “This is one who was born there.” (Selah)  7 Singers and those performing circle dances will say: “All my springs are in you.”*

A song. A melody of the sons of Korʹah. To the director; in the style of Maʹha·lath,* to be sung alternately. Masʹkil* of Heʹman the Ezʹra·hite. 88 O Jehovah, the God of my salvation, By day I cry out, And by night I come before you.  2 Let my prayer come to you, Incline your ear* to my cry for help.  3 For my soul* has been filled with calamity, And my life is on the brink of the Grave.*  4 I am already counted among those going down to the pit;* I have become a helpless man,*  5 Left among the dead Like the slain lying in a grave, Whom you remember no longer And who have been separated from your care.*  6 You have put me in the lowest pit, In dark places, in a large abyss.  7 Your rage weighs heavily on me, And you overwhelm me with your crashing waves. (Selah)  8 You have driven my acquaintances far away from me; You have made me something detestable to them. I am trapped and cannot escape.  9 My eye is worn out because of my affliction. I call on you, O Jehovah, all day long; To you I spread out my hands. 10 Will you perform wonders for the dead? Can those powerless in death rise up to praise you? (Selah) 11 Will your loyal love be declared in the grave, Your faithfulness in the place of destruction?* 12 Will your wonders be known in the darkness Or your righteousness in the land of oblivion? 13 But I still cry to you for help, O Jehovah, Each morning my prayer comes before you. 14 Why, O Jehovah, do you reject me?* Why do you hide your face from me? 15 From my youth on, I have been afflicted and ready to perish; I am numb from the terrible things you allow me to suffer. 16 Your burning anger overwhelms me; Your terrors destroy me. 17 They surround me like waters all day long; They close in on me from all sides.* 18 You have driven my friends and companions far away from me; Darkness has become my companion.

Masʹkil.* Of Eʹthan the Ezʹra·hite. 89 I will sing about Jehovah’s expressions of loyal love forever. With my mouth I will make known your faithfulness to all generations.  2 For I have said: “Loyal love will be built up* forever, And you have firmly established your faithfulness in the heavens.”  3 “I have made a covenant with my chosen one; I have sworn to David my servant:  4 ‘I will firmly establish your offspring* forever, And I will build up your throne for all generations.’” (Selah)  5 The heavens praise your marvels, O Jehovah, Yes, your faithfulness in the congregation of the holy ones.  6 For who in the skies can compare to Jehovah? Who among the sons of God is like Jehovah?  7 God is held in awe in the council* of holy ones; He is grand and awe-inspiring to all who are around him.  8 O Jehovah God of armies, Who is mighty like you, O Jah? Your faithfulness surrounds you.  9 You rule over the raging of the sea; When its waves surge, you calm them. 10 You have crushed Raʹhab like one who is slain. With your strong arm you have scattered your enemies. 11 The heavens are yours, and the earth is yours; The productive land and what fills it—you have founded them. 12 The north and the south—you created them; Taʹbor and Herʹmon joyously praise your name. 13 Your arm is mighty; Your hand is strong; Your right hand is exalted. 14 Righteousness and justice are the foundation of your throne; Loyal love and faithfulness stand before you. 15 Happy are the people who know the joyful shouting. O Jehovah, they walk in the light of your face. 16 They rejoice in your name all day long, And in your righteousness they are exalted. 17 For you are the glory of their strength, And by your approval our strength* is exalted. 18 For our shield belongs to Jehovah, Our king belongs to the Holy One of Israel. 19 At that time you spoke in a vision to your loyal ones and said: “I have granted strength to a mighty one; I have exalted a chosen one from among the people. 20 I have found David my servant; With my holy oil I have anointed him. 21 My hand will support him, And my arm will strengthen him. 22 No enemy will exact tribute from him, And no unrighteous man will oppress him. 23 I will crush to pieces his adversaries from before him And strike down those who hate him. 24 My faithfulness and loyal love are with him, And in my name his strength* will be exalted. 25 I will put his hand* over the sea And his right hand over the rivers. 26 He will call out to me: ‘You are my Father, My God and the Rock of my salvation.’ 27 And I will place him as firstborn, The highest of the kings of the earth. 28 I will maintain my loyal love for him forever, And my covenant with him will never fail. 29 I will establish his offspring* forever And make his throne as enduring as the heavens. 30 If his sons leave my law And do not walk according to my decrees,* 31 If they violate my statutes And do not keep my commandments, 32 Then I will punish their disobedience* with a rod And their error with flogging. 33 But I will never abandon my loyal love for him Nor be untrue to my promise.* 34 I will not violate my covenant Or change what my lips have spoken. 35 I have sworn in my holiness, once and for all; I will not tell lies to David. 36 His offspring* will endure forever; His throne will endure like the sun before me. 37 Like the moon, it will be firmly established forever As a faithful witness in the skies.” (Selah) 38 But you yourself have cast off and rejected him; You have become furious with your anointed one. 39 You have spurned the covenant with your servant; You have profaned his crown* by throwing it to the ground. 40 You have broken down all his stone walls;* You have reduced his fortifications to ruins. 41 All who pass by have pillaged him; He is a reproach to his neighbors. 42 You have made his adversaries victorious;* You have caused all his enemies to rejoice. 43 You have also driven back his sword, And you have made him lose ground in the battle. 44 You have brought an end to his splendor And hurled his throne to the ground. 45 You have cut short the days of his youth; You have clothed him with shame. (Selah) 46 How long, O Jehovah, will you hide yourself? Will it be forever? Will your rage continue to burn like a fire? 47 Remember how short my life is! Was it to no purpose that you created all humans? 48 What man can live and never see death? Can he save himself* from the power of the Grave?* (Selah) 49 Where are your former acts of loyal love, O Jehovah, That you swore about to David in your faithfulness? 50 Remember, O Jehovah, the taunts hurled at your servants; How I have to bear* the taunts of all the peoples; 51 How your enemies have hurled insults, O Jehovah; How they have insulted every footstep of your anointed one. 52 May Jehovah be praised forever. Amen and Amen.

A prayer of Moses, the man of the true God. 90 O Jehovah, you have been our dwelling place* throughout all generations.  2 Before the mountains were born Or you brought forth* the earth and the productive land, From everlasting to everlasting,* you are God.  3 You make mortal man return to dust; You say: “Return, you sons of men.”  4 For a thousand years are in your eyes just as yesterday when it is past, Just as a watch during the night.  5 You sweep them away; they become like mere sleep; In the morning they are like grass that sprouts.  6 In the morning it blossoms and is renewed, But by evening it withers and dries up.  7 For we are consumed by your anger And terrified by your rage.  8 You place our errors in front of you;* Our secrets are exposed by the light of your face.  9 Our days ebb* away because of your fury; And our years come to an end like a whisper.* 10 The span of our life is 70 years, Or 80 if one is especially strong.* But they are filled with trouble and sorrow; They quickly pass by, and away we fly. 11 Who can fathom the power of your anger? Your fury is as great as the fear you deserve. 12 Teach us how to count our days So that we may acquire a heart of wisdom. 13 Return, O Jehovah! How long will this last? Have pity on your servants. 14 Satisfy us with your loyal love in the morning, So that we may shout joyfully and rejoice during all our days. 15 Make us rejoice in proportion to the days you have afflicted us, For as many years as we have experienced calamity. 16 May your servants see your activity, And may their sons see your splendor. 17 May the favor of Jehovah our God be upon us; May you prosper* the work of our hands. Yes, prosper* the work of our hands.

91 Anyone dwelling in the secret place of the Most High Will lodge under the shadow of the Almighty.  2 I will say to Jehovah: “You are my refuge and my stronghold, My God in whom I trust.”  3 For he will rescue you from the trap of the birdcatcher, From the destructive pestilence.  4 With his pinions he will cover* you, And under his wings you will take refuge. His faithfulness will be a large shield and a protective wall.*  5 You will not fear the terrors of the night, Nor the arrow that flies by day,  6 Nor the pestilence that stalks in the gloom, Nor the destruction that ravages at midday.  7 A thousand will fall at your side And ten thousand at your right hand, But to you it will not come near.  8 You will only see it with your eyes As you witness the punishment* of the wicked.  9 Because you said: “Jehovah is my refuge,” You have made the Most High your dwelling;* 10 No disaster will befall you, And no plague will come near your tent. 11 For he will give his angels a command concerning you, To guard you in all your ways. 12 They will carry you on their hands, So that you may not strike your foot against a stone. 13 On the young lion and the cobra you will tread; You will trample underfoot the maned lion and the big snake. 14 God said: “Because he has affection for me,* I will rescue him. I will protect him because he knows* my name. 15 He will call on me, and I will answer him. I will be with him in distress. I will rescue him and glorify him. 16 I will satisfy him with long life, And I will cause him to see my acts of salvation.”*

Or “acknowledge.”

Or “For me, you are the source of all things.”

See Glossary.

See Glossary.

Or “Bend down and listen.”

See Glossary.

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Or “grave.”

Or “like a man without strength.”

Lit., “hand.”

Or “in Abaddon.”

Or “my soul.”

Or possibly, “all at once.”

See Glossary.

Or “endure.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “assembly.”

Lit., “horn.”

Lit., “horn.”

Or “authority.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “judgments.”

Or “rebellion.”

Lit., “Nor be false with my faithfulness.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “diadem.”

Or “his shelters of stone.”

Lit., “lifted up the right hand of his adversaries.”

Or “his soul.”

Lit., “the hand of Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

Lit., “carry in my bosom.”

Or possibly, “our refuge.”

Or “brought forth as with labor pains.”

Or “From eternity to eternity.”

Or “You are aware of our errors.”

Or “Our life ebbs.”

Or “a sigh.”

Or “because of special mightiness.”

Or “firmly establish.”

Or “firmly establish.”

Or “block approach to.”

Or “a bulwark.”

Lit., “retribution.”

Or possibly, “fortress; refuge.”

Lit., “he has joined himself to me.”

Or “acknowledges.”

Or “see salvation from me.”

^ (Ps. 90:1-17) O Jehovah, you have been our dwelling place* throughout all generations.  2 Before the mountains were born Or you brought forth* the earth and the productive land, From everlasting to everlasting,* you are God.  3 You make mortal man return to dust; You say: “Return, you sons of men.”  4 For a thousand years are in your eyes just as yesterday when it is past, Just as a watch during the night.  5 You sweep them away; they become like mere sleep; In the morning they are like grass that sprouts.  6 In the morning it blossoms and is renewed, But by evening it withers and dries up.  7 For we are consumed by your anger And terrified by your rage.  8 You place our errors in front of you;* Our secrets are exposed by the light of your face.  9 Our days ebb* away because of your fury; And our years come to an end like a whisper.* 10 The span of our life is 70 years, Or 80 if one is especially strong.* But they are filled with trouble and sorrow; They quickly pass by, and away we fly. 11 Who can fathom the power of your anger? Your fury is as great as the fear you deserve. 12 Teach us how to count our days So that we may acquire a heart of wisdom. 13 Return, O Jehovah! How long will this last? Have pity on your servants. 14 Satisfy us with your loyal love in the morning, So that we may shout joyfully and rejoice during all our days. 15 Make us rejoice in proportion to the days you have afflicted us, For as many years as we have experienced calamity. 16 May your servants see your activity, And may their sons see your splendor. 17 May the favor of Jehovah our God be upon us; May you prosper* the work of our hands. Yes, prosper* the work of our hands.

Or possibly, “our refuge.”

Or “brought forth as with labor pains.”

Or “From eternity to eternity.”

Or “You are aware of our errors.”

Or “Our life ebbs.”

Or “a sigh.”

Or “because of special mightiness.”

Or “firmly establish.”

Or “firmly establish.”

^ ***sn song 49 Jehovah Is Our Refuge***

Song 49

Jehovah Is Our Refuge

([Psalm 91])

1. Jehovah is our refuge,

Our God in whom we trust.

His shadow is our shelter;

Abide in it we must.

For he himself will us defend,

Upon his might we can depend.

Jehovah is a stronghold,

Giving shelter to all the just.

2. Though thousands will be falling

Along your very side,

Among those who are loyal,

In safety you’ll reside.

You will not need to quake with fear,

As though great harm to you were near.

Your eyes will merely see it,

Underneath God’s wings you’ll abide.

3. Protection God will give you

From snares along your way,

And never will you falter

In fear or in dismay.

The maned young lion, you’ll not dread;

Upon the cobra you will tread.

Jehovah is our refuge,

Ever guarding us on our way.

(See also [Ps. 97:10;][121:3,][5;][Isa. 52:12].)

^ (Ps. 91:1-16) Anyone dwelling in the secret place of the Most High Will lodge under the shadow of the Almighty.  2 I will say to Jehovah: “You are my refuge and my stronghold, My God in whom I trust.”  3 For he will rescue you from the trap of the birdcatcher, From the destructive pestilence.  4 With his pinions he will cover* you, And under his wings you will take refuge. His faithfulness will be a large shield and a protective wall.*  5 You will not fear the terrors of the night, Nor the arrow that flies by day,  6 Nor the pestilence that stalks in the gloom, Nor the destruction that ravages at midday.  7 A thousand will fall at your side And ten thousand at your right hand, But to you it will not come near.  8 You will only see it with your eyes As you witness the punishment* of the wicked.  9 Because you said: “Jehovah is my refuge,” You have made the Most High your dwelling;* 10 No disaster will befall you, And no plague will come near your tent. 11 For he will give his angels a command concerning you, To guard you in all your ways. 12 They will carry you on their hands, So that you may not strike your foot against a stone. 13 On the young lion and the cobra you will tread; You will trample underfoot the maned lion and the big snake. 14 God said: “Because he has affection for me,* I will rescue him. I will protect him because he knows* my name. 15 He will call on me, and I will answer him. I will be with him in distress. I will rescue him and glorify him. 16 I will satisfy him with long life, And I will cause him to see my acts of salvation.”*

Or “block approach to.”

Or “a bulwark.”

Lit., “retribution.”

Or possibly, “fortress; refuge.”

Lit., “he has joined himself to me.”

Or “acknowledges.”

Or “see salvation from me.”

^ (Ps. 97:10) O you who love Jehovah, hate what is bad. He is guarding the lives* of his loyal ones; He rescues them from the hand* of the wicked.

Or “souls.”

Or “power.”

^ (Ps. 121:3) He will never allow your foot to slip.* The One guarding you will never be drowsy.

Or “totter.”

^ (Ps. 121:5) Jehovah is guarding you. Jehovah is the shade at your right hand.

^ (Isa. 52:12) For you will not depart in panic, Nor will you have to flee, For Jehovah will go ahead of you, And the God of Israel will be your rear guard.

^ ***w10 2/15 pp. 26-27 Welcome to the Best Way of Life!***

Safe in “the Secret Place”

10, 11. What is “the secret place of the Most High,” and how can we gain access to it?

10 Dedication and baptism result in another rich blessing—the privilege of dwelling in “the secret place of the Most High.” (Read Psalm 91:1.) This is a figurative place of safety and security—a condition, or state, of protection from spiritual harm. It is a “secret place” because it is unknown to people who lack spiritual vision and do not trust in God. By living in harmony with our dedication and by exercising complete confidence in Jehovah, in effect we are saying to him: “You are my refuge and my stronghold, my God, in whom I will trust.” ([Ps. 91:2]) Jehovah God becomes our secure dwelling place. ([Ps. 91:9]) Who could ask for more than that?

11 Gaining access to “the secret place” of Jehovah also implies that we have been blessed with the privilege of having developed a personal relationship with him. This begins with dedication and baptism. Thereafter, we build on our relationship with God by drawing close to him through Bible study, heartfelt prayer, and full obedience. ([Jas. 4:8]) No one has ever been closer to Jehovah than Jesus, whose confidence in the Creator has never wavered. ([John 8:29]) Therefore, let us never doubt Jehovah or his desire and ability to help us fulfill our dedication vow. ([Eccl. 5:4]) The spiritual provisions that God has made for his people are undeniable evidence that he truly loves us and wants us to succeed in serving him.

^ par. 10 (Ps. 91:1) Anyone dwelling in the secret place of the Most High Will lodge under the shadow of the Almighty.

^ par. 10 (Ps. 91:2) I will say to Jehovah: “You are my refuge and my stronghold, My God in whom I trust.”

^ par. 10 (Ps. 91:9) Because you said: “Jehovah is my refuge,” You have made the Most High your dwelling;*

Or possibly, “fortress; refuge.”

^ par. 11 (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

^ par. 11 (John 8:29) And the One who sent me is with me; he did not abandon me to myself, because I always do the things pleasing to him.”

^ par. 11 (Eccl. 5:4) Whenever you make a vow to God, do not delay to pay it, for he finds no pleasure in the stupid ones. What you vow, pay.

^ ***w07 10/1 pp. 26-30 Deliverance From the Traps of the Birdcatcher***

1. Who is “the birdcatcher,” and why is he dangerous?

ALL true Christians face a predator, one with superhuman intelligence and craftiness. He is referred to at [Psalm 91:3] as “the birdcatcher.” Who is this enemy? Since the issue of June 1, 1883, this magazine has identified him as none other than Satan the Devil. This formidable foe cunningly endeavors to mislead and trap Jehovah’s people as a birdcatcher tries to trap a bird.

2. Why is Satan likened to a birdcatcher?

2 In ancient times, birds were captured for their beautiful singing, for their colorful plumage, as well as for food and for sacrifice. However, birds are naturally cautious, skittish creatures, difficult to trap. Therefore, a birdcatcher in Bible times first carefully studied the peculiarities and habits of the type of birds he wished to ensnare. Then, he devised cunning methods to trap them. In likening Satan to a birdcatcher, the Bible helps us understand his methods. The Devil studies us as individuals. He notes our habits and characteristics and sets hidden traps in an attempt to catch us alive. (2 Timothy 2:26) Being caught by him would mean our spiritual ruin and could lead to our ultimate destruction. Hence, for our protection, we need to identify various schemes of “the birdcatcher.”

3, 4. When do Satan’s tactics resemble those of a lion? a cobra?

3 Using vivid imagery, the psalmist also likens Satan’s tactics to those of a young lion or those of a cobra. ([Psalm 91:13]) Like a lion, Satan at times makes open, frontal attacks by means of persecution or legislative action against Jehovah’s people. ([Psalm 94:20]) Such lionlike attacks may cause a few to stumble. More often than not, however, these overt attacks backfire and result in a unifying of God’s people. What, though, of Satan’s more subtle, cobralike attacks?

4 The Devil uses his superhuman intelligence to launch treacherous and deadly strikes like those of a poisonous snake from a hidden place. In this way, he has succeeded in poisoning the mind of some of God’s people, deceiving them into doing his will rather than Jehovah’s, with a tragic outcome. Happily, we are not ignorant of Satan’s designs. (2 Corinthians 2:11) Let us now consider four of the deadly traps that are used by “the birdcatcher.”

Fear of Man

5. Why is the snare of “trembling at men” so effective?

5 “The birdcatcher” understands the normal human desire for acceptance and the approval of others. Christians are not callously indifferent to the thoughts and feelings of those around them. Knowing this, the Devil would like to exploit their concern for what people think of them. For example, he throws some of God’s people off balance by using the snare of “trembling at men.” (Proverbs 29:25) If because of fear of man, servants of God join others in doing what Jehovah forbids or refrain from doing what God’s Word commands them to do, they have been ensnared by “the birdcatcher.”—Ezekiel 33:8;[James 4:17].

6. What example illustrates how a young person may be trapped by “the birdcatcher”?

6 For example, a young person may cave in to pressure from schoolmates and smoke a cigarette. Smoking a cigarette may have been the farthest thing from his mind when he left for school that day. Soon, though, he is doing something that is both harmful to his health and displeasing to God. (2 Corinthians 7:1) How was he enticed? Perhaps he got involved with the wrong sort of peers and was afraid to incur their disapproval. Young people, do not let “the birdcatcher” lure and trap you! To avoid being caught alive, guard against even small compromises. Heed the Bible’s warning to shun bad association.—1 Corinthians 15:33.

7. How might Satan cause some parents to lose their spiritual balance?

7 Conscientious Christian parents take seriously their Scriptural responsibility to provide materially for their families. (1 Timothy 5:8) However, Satan’s aim is to make Christians lose their balance in this regard. Perhaps they habitually miss meetings because they give in to pressure from their employers to do extra work. They may be afraid to ask for time off to attend all the sessions of a district convention to worship Jehovah with their brothers. The protection against this snare is to “trust in Jehovah.” (Proverbs 3:5, 6) Additionally, remembering that we are all members of Jehovah’s household and that he has obligated himself to watch over us will help us to maintain our balance. Parents, do you have faith that Jehovah will in one way or another care for you and your family when you do his will? Or will the Devil catch you alive and get you to do his will because of fear of man? We entreat you to consider these questions prayerfully.

The Snare of Materialism

8. In what way does Satan use the lure of materialism?

8 Satan also uses the lure of materialism to entrap us. The commercial system of this world often promotes get-rich-quick schemes that may even beguile some of God’s people. At times, individuals may be urged: “Work hard. When you reach a comfortable position, you can take it easy and enjoy life. You can even pioneer.” Such words may be the unbalanced reasoning of some who take financial advantage of their associates in the Christian congregation. Think carefully about that incentive. Does it not mirror the thinking of the “unreasonable” rich man of Jesus’ parable?—Luke 12:16-21.

9. Why might some Christians be ensnared by desiring things?

9 Satan operates his wicked system in such a way that it induces people to desire things. That desire can eventually make inroads into a Christian’s life, choking the word and making it “unfruitful.” ([Mark 4:19]) The Bible encourages us to be content with sustenance and covering. (1 Timothy 6:8) However, many get ensnared by “the birdcatcher” because they do not apply that counsel to themselves. Could it be that pride makes them feel that they must adhere to a certain lifestyle? What about us personally? Does our desire to possess things cause us to push the interests of true worship into second place? ([Haggai 1:2-8]) Sadly, during hard economic times, some have sacrificed their spirituality in order to maintain the standard of living to which they had grown accustomed. Such a materialistic attitude delights “the birdcatcher”!

The Trap of Unwholesome Entertainment

10. What self-examination should each Christian make?

10 Another tactic of “the birdcatcher” is to undermine people’s natural sense of what is good and what is bad. A mentality similar to that found in Sodom and Gomorrah has come to control much of the entertainment industry. Even news reports on television and in periodicals highlight violence and pander to a lurid interest in sex. Much of what appears as entertainment in the media blurs people’s ability “to distinguish both right and wrong.” ([Hebrews 5:14]) Recall, however, Jehovah’s words through the prophet Isaiah: “Woe to those who are saying that good is bad and bad is good!” ([Isaiah 5:20]) Has “the birdcatcher” insidiously affected your thinking with such unwholesome entertainment? Self-examination is essential.—2 Corinthians 13:5.

11. What warning about TV soap operas was given in this magazine?

11 Nearly a quarter of a century ago, The Watchtower lovingly warned the household of faith about TV serials.* This observation was made about the subtle impact of popular soap operas: “The search for love is used to justify any conduct. For instance, one unwed pregnant youth says to a friend: ‘But I love Victor. I don’t care. . . . To have his baby is worth everything to me!’ The soft background music makes it hard to consider her course to be so bad. You too like Victor. You feel sympathy for the girl. You ‘understand.’ ‘It is amazing how you can rationalize,’ stated one viewer who later came to her senses. ‘We know that immorality is bad. . . . But I realized that mentally I was taking part.’”

12. What facts indicate the current appropriateness of the warning about certain TV programming?

12 Since those articles were published, this type of heart-corrupting programming has become increasingly available. In many places, such programs are broadcast 24 hours a day. Men, women, and many teenagers frequently feed their minds and hearts on such entertainment. We, though, must not deceive ourselves with false reasoning. It would be wrong to reason that depraved entertainment is no worse than what is seen in the real world. Can a Christian really justify choosing to be entertained by the sort of people he would never dream of inviting into his home?

13, 14. How did some express how they benefited from warnings about TV?

13 Many benefited when they took to heart that warning provided by “the faithful and discreet slave.” (Matthew 24:45-47) After reading the straightforward, Bible-based counsel, some wrote to tell how the articles had personally affected them.* One confessed: “For 13 years I was a soap-opera addict. I thought that I was safe simply by attending Christian meetings and being semiregular in the field service. But I adopted the worldly soap-opera attitude that if your husband mistreats you or you feel unloved, adultery is justifiable—he brought it on himself. And so when I felt ‘justified’ I took this bad course and sinned against Jehovah and my mate.” This woman was disfellowshipped. Eventually, she came to her senses, repented, and was reinstated. The articles warning against TV soap operas gave her the strength to refuse to be entertained by what Jehovah hates.—Amos 5:14, 15.

14 Another reader whose life was affected said: “I cried when I read the articles, for I discovered that my heart was no longer complete toward Jehovah. I promised my God that I would no longer be a slave to these serials.” After expressing appreciation for the articles, one Christian woman admitted her addiction and wrote: “I wondered . . . if my relationship with Jehovah could be affected. How could I have ‘them’ as friends and also be a friend to Jehovah?” If such TV shows corrupted hearts 25 years ago, what impact do they have today? (2 Timothy 3:13) We must be aware of Satan’s trap of unwholesome entertainment in all its forms, whether TV soap operas, violent video games, or immoral music videos.

The Trap of Personal Differences

15. How are some caught alive by the Devil?

15 Satan uses personal differences as a trap to cause divisions among Jehovah’s people. We can be trapped this way regardless of our privileges of service. Some are caught alive by the Devil because they allow personal differences to disrupt the peace and unity and the beautiful spiritual prosperity that Jehovah has brought into existence.—Psalm 133:1-3.

16. How has Satan slyly been trying to disrupt our unity?

16 During World War I, Satan tried to destroy the earthly part of Jehovah’s organization by frontal attack, but he failed. (Revelation 11:7-13) Since then, he has slyly been working to disrupt our unity. When we allow personal differences to cause disunity, we have provided “the birdcatcher” a foothold. We could thus hinder the free flow of holy spirit in our personal lives as well as in the congregation. If that were to happen, Satan would be pleased because any disruption of the peace and unity of the congregation interferes with the preaching work.—Ephesians 4:27,[30-32].

17. What can help those who have personal differences to resolve them?

17 What can you do if you have personal differences with a fellow Christian? Granted, every situation is unique. However, while there may be many reasons why problems develop, there is no reason why personal differences should be left unresolved. (Matthew 5:23, 24;[18:15-17]) The advice in God’s Word is inspired, perfect. When applied, Bible principles never fail. They always work!

18. Why would imitating Jehovah help us resolve personal differences?

18 Jehovah is “ready to forgive,” and he grants “true forgiveness.” ([Psalm 86:5;][130:4]) We show that we are beloved children of Jehovah when we imitate him. (Ephesians 5:1) We are all sinners and desperately in need of Jehovah’s forgiveness. Thus, we must be careful if we feel inclined not to forgive someone. We could become like the slave in Jesus’ parable who refused to forgive his fellow slave a debt that was but a fraction of the debt that his master had already forgiven him. When the master was informed, he had the unforgiving slave thrown into prison. Jesus concluded the parable by saying: “In like manner my heavenly Father will also deal with you if you do not forgive each one his brother from your hearts.” (Matthew 18:21-35) Meditating on that illustration and reflecting on how many times Jehovah has freely forgiven us will surely help us when we are trying to settle personal differences with our brother!—[Psalm 19:14].

^ par. 1 (Ps. 91:3) For he will rescue you from the trap of the birdcatcher, From the destructive pestilence.

^ par. 2 (2 Tim. 2:26) and they may come to their senses and escape from the snare of the Devil, seeing that they have been caught alive by him to do his will.

^ par. 3 (Ps. 91:13) On the young lion and the cobra you will tread; You will trample underfoot the maned lion and the big snake.

^ par. 3 (Ps. 94:20) Can a throne* of corruption be allied with you While it is framing trouble in the name of the law?*

Or “rulers; judges.”

Or “by decree.”

^ par. 4 (2 Cor. 2:11) so that we may not be overreached* by Satan, for we are not ignorant of his designs.*

Or “outwitted.”

Or “intentions; schemes.”

^ par. 5 (Prov. 29:25) Trembling at* men is* a snare, But the one trusting in Jehovah will be protected.

Or “Fear of.”

Or “lays.”

^ par. 5 (Ezek. 33:8) When I say to someone wicked, ‘Wicked one, you will surely die!’ but you do not speak out to warn the wicked one to change his course, he will die as a wicked man because of his own error, but I will ask his blood back from you.

^ par. 5 (Jas. 4:17) Therefore, if someone knows how to do what is right and yet does not do it, it is a sin for him.

^ par. 6 (2 Cor. 7:1) Therefore, since we have these promises, beloved ones, let us cleanse ourselves of every defilement of flesh and spirit, perfecting holiness in the fear of God.

^ par. 6 (1 Cor. 15:33) Do not be misled. Bad associations spoil useful habits.*

Or “corrupt good morals.”

^ par. 7 (1 Tim. 5:8) Certainly if anyone does not provide for those who are his own, and especially for those who are members of his household, he has disowned the faith and is worse than a person without faith.

^ par. 7 (Prov. 3:5, 6) Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.

Lit., “lean.”

^ par. 8 (Luke 12:16-21) With that he told them an illustration, saying: “The land of a rich man produced well. 17 So he began reasoning within himself, ‘What should I do now that I have nowhere to gather my crops?’ 18 Then he said, ‘I will do this: I will tear down my storehouses and build bigger ones, and there I will gather all my grain and all my goods, 19 and I will say to myself:* “You* have many good things stored up for many years; take it easy, eat, drink, enjoy yourself.”’ 20 But God said to him, ‘Unreasonable one, this night they are demanding your life* from you. Who, then, is to have the things you stored up?’ 21 So it goes with the man who stores up treasure for himself but is not rich toward God.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “Soul, you.”

Or “soul.”

^ par. 9 (Mark 4:19) but the anxieties of this system of things* and the deceptive power of riches and the desires for everything else make inroads and choke the word, and it becomes unfruitful.

Or “this age.” See Glossary.

^ par. 9 (1 Tim. 6:8) So, having food* and clothing,* we will be content with these things.

Or “sustenance.”

Or “shelter.” Lit., “covering.”

^ par. 9 (Hag. 1:2-8) “This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘These people say, “The time has not yet come for the house* of Jehovah to be built.”’”* 3 And the word of Jehovah again came through Hagʹgai the prophet, saying: 4 “Is it the time for you to dwell in your paneled houses, while this house lies in ruins? 5 Now this is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘Set your heart on* your ways. 6 You have sown much seed, but you harvest little. You eat, but it is not to satisfaction. You drink, but you do not drink your fill. You put on clothing, but no one gets warm. The one who hires himself out puts his wages in a bag full of holes.’” 7 “This is what Jehovah of armies says, ‘Set your heart on* your ways.’ 8 “‘Go up to the mountain and bring in lumber. And build the house, so that I may take pleasure in it and I may be glorified,’ Jehovah says.”

Or “temple.”

Or “rebuilt.”

Or “Give careful thought to.”

Or “Give careful thought to.”

^ par. 10 (Heb. 5:14) But solid food belongs to mature people, to those who through use have their powers of discernment* trained to distinguish both right and wrong.

Or “their perceptive powers.”

^ par. 10 (Isa. 5:20) Woe to those who say that good is bad and bad is good, Those who substitute darkness for light and light for darkness, Those who put bitter for sweet and sweet for bitter!

^ par. 10 (2 Cor. 13:5) Keep testing whether you are in the faith; keep proving what you yourselves are. Or do you not recognize that Jesus Christ is in union with you? Unless you are disapproved.

^ par. 13 (Matt. 24:45-47) “Who really is the faithful and discreet* slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time? 46 Happy is that slave if his master on coming finds him doing so! 47 Truly I say to you, he will appoint him over all his belongings.

Or “wise.”

^ par. 13 (Amos 5:14, 15) Search for what is good, and not what is bad, So that you may keep living. Then Jehovah the God of armies may be with you, Just as you say he is. 15 Hate what is bad, and love what is good, Let justice prevail in the city gate. It may be that Jehovah the God of armies Will show favor to the remaining ones of Joseph.’

^ par. 14 (2 Tim. 3:13) But wicked men and impostors will advance from bad to worse, misleading and being misled.

^ par. 15 (Ps. 133:1-3) Look! How good and how pleasant it is For brothers to dwell together in unity!  2 It is like fine oil poured on the head That runs down the beard, Aaron’s beard, And runs down onto the collar of his garments.  3 It is like the dew of Herʹmon That descends on the mountains of Zion. That is where Jehovah decreed his blessing —Life everlasting.

^ par. 16 (Rev. 11:7-13) When they have finished their witnessing, the wild beast that ascends out of the abyss will wage war with them and conquer them and kill them. 8 And their corpses will be on the main street of the great city that is in a spiritual sense called Sodʹom and Egypt, where their Lord was also executed on the stake. 9 And those of the peoples and tribes and tongues* and nations will look at their corpses for three and a half days, and they do not allow their corpses to be laid in a tomb. 10 And those dwelling on the earth rejoice over them and celebrate, and they will send gifts to one another, because these two prophets tormented those dwelling on the earth. 11 After the three and a half days, spirit of life from God entered into them, and they stood on their feet, and great fear fell upon those who saw them. 12 And they heard a loud voice from heaven say to them: “Come up here.” And they went up into heaven in the cloud, and their enemies saw them.* 13 In that hour there was a great earthquake, and a tenth of the city fell; and 7,000 persons were killed by the earthquake, and the rest became frightened and gave glory to the God of heaven.

Or “languages.”

Or “were looking on.”

^ par. 16 (Eph. 4:27) do not give the Devil an opportunity.*

Or “neither allow place for the Devil.”

^ par. 16 (Eph. 4:30-32) Also, do not be grieving* God’s holy spirit, with which you have been sealed for a day of releasing by ransom. 31 Put away from yourselves every kind of malicious bitterness, anger, wrath, screaming, and abusive speech, as well as everything injurious. 32 But become kind to one another, tenderly compassionate, freely forgiving one another just as God also by Christ freely forgave you.

Or “cause sorrow to.”

^ par. 17 (Matt. 5:23, 24) “If, then, you are bringing your gift to the altar and there you remember that your brother has something against you, 24 leave your gift there in front of the altar, and go away. First make your peace with your brother, and then come back and offer your gift.

^ par. 17 (Matt. 18:15-17) “Moreover, if your brother commits a sin, go and reveal his fault* between you and him alone. If he listens to you, you have gained your brother. 16 But if he does not listen, take along with you one or two more, so that on the testimony* of two or three witnesses every matter may be established. 17 If he does not listen to them, speak to the congregation. If he does not listen even to the congregation, let him be to you just as a man of the nations and as a tax collector.

Lit., “and reprove him.”

Lit., “mouth.”

^ par. 18 (Ps. 86:5) For you, O Jehovah, are good and ready to forgive; You abound in loyal love for all those who call on you.

^ par. 18 (Ps. 130:4) For with you there is true forgiveness, So that you may be held in awe.*

Lit., “be feared.”

^ par. 18 (Eph. 5:1) Therefore, become imitators of God, as beloved children,

^ par. 18 (Matt. 18:21-35) Then Peter came and said to him: “Lord, how many times is my brother to sin against me and am I to forgive him? Up to seven times?” 22 Jesus said to him: “I say to you, not up to seven times, but up to 77 times. 23 “That is why the Kingdom of the heavens may be likened to a king who wanted to settle accounts with his slaves. 24 When he started to settle them, a man was brought in who owed him 10,000 talents.* 25 But because he did not have the means to pay it back, his master ordered him and his wife and his children and all the things he owned to be sold and payment to be made. 26 So the slave fell down and did obeisance* to him, saying, ‘Be patient with me, and I will pay back everything to you.’ 27 Moved with pity at this, the master of that slave let him off and canceled his debt. 28 But that slave went out and found one of his fellow slaves, who owed him 100 de·narʹi·i,* and grabbed him and began to choke him, saying, ‘Pay back whatever you owe.’ 29 So his fellow slave fell down and began to beg him, saying, ‘Be patient with me, and I will pay you back.’ 30 However, he was not willing, but he went and had him thrown into prison until he could pay back what he owed. 31 When his fellow slaves saw what had happened, they became greatly distressed, and they went and reported to their master all the things that had happened. 32 Then his master summoned him and said to him: ‘Wicked slave, I canceled all that debt for you when you pleaded with me. 33 Should you not also have shown mercy to your fellow slave as I showed mercy to you?’ 34 With that his master, provoked to wrath, handed him over to the jailers until he repaid all that he owed. 35 My heavenly Father will also deal with you in the same way if each of you does not forgive your brother from your heart.”

10,000 talents of silver equaled 60,000,000 denarii. See App. B14.

Or “bowed down.”

See App. B14.

^ par. 18 (Ps. 19:14) May the words of my mouth and the meditation of my heart Be pleasing to you, O Jehovah, my Rock and my Redeemer.

^ par. 11 The Watchtower, December 1, 1982, pages 3-7.

^ par. 13 The Watchtower, December 1, 1983, page 23.

^ ***w10 1/15 pp. 10-11 Belonging to Jehovah—An Undeserved Kindness***

13. How does Jehovah protect us from dangers that threaten our spiritual welfare?

13 How does Jehovah protect his people from these spiritual dangers? The psalm says: “He will give his own angels a command concerning you, to guard you in all your ways.” ([Ps. 91:11]) Heavenly angels guide and protect us so that we can preach the good news. ([Rev. 14:6]) In addition to the angels, Christian elders, by holding firmly to the Scriptures in their teaching, protect us from being deceived by false reasoning. They can provide individual help to any who are struggling to overcome worldly attitudes. ([Titus 1:9;][1 Pet. 5:2]) Also, “the faithful and discreet slave” provides spiritual food to protect us against the teaching of evolution, the enticement of immoral desires, the pursuit of riches and prominence, and numerous other harmful desires and influences. ([Matt. 24:45]) What has helped you to resist some of those dangers?

14. How can we take advantage of the protection God provides?

14 What must we do to remain in God’s “secret place” of protection? Just as we constantly have to protect ourselves from physical dangers, such as accidents, criminals, or infections, so we must act continuously to protect ourselves from spiritual dangers. Hence, we should regularly take advantage of the guidance that Jehovah provides for us in our publications and at congregation meetings and assemblies. We seek the advice of the elders. And do we not benefit from the variety of qualities displayed by our Christian brothers and sisters? Indeed, our association with the congregation helps us to become wise.—[Prov. 13:20]; read 1 Peter 4:10.

^ par. 13 (Ps. 91:11) For he will give his angels a command concerning you, To guard you in all your ways.

^ par. 13 (Rev. 14:6) And I saw another angel flying in midheaven,* and he had everlasting good news to declare to those who dwell on the earth, to every nation and tribe and tongue* and people.

Or “in midair; overhead.”

Or “language.”

^ par. 13 (Titus 1:9) holding firmly to the faithful word* as respects his art of teaching, so that he may be able both to encourage* by the teaching that is wholesome* and to reprove those who contradict.

Or “the trustworthy message.”

Or “exhort.”

Or “healthful; beneficial.”

^ par. 13 (1 Pet. 5:2) Shepherd the flock of God under your care, serving as overseers,* not under compulsion, but willingly before God; not for love of dishonest gain, but eagerly;

Or “carefully watching over it.”

^ par. 13 (Matt. 24:45) “Who really is the faithful and discreet* slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time?

Or “wise.”

^ par. 14 (Prov. 13:20) The one walking with the wise will become wise, But the one who has dealings with the stupid will fare badly.

^ par. 14 (1 Pet. 4:10) To the extent that each one has received a gift, use it in ministering to one another as fine stewards of God’s undeserved kindness that is expressed in various ways.

^ ***w01 11/15 pp. 19-20 Jehovah Is Our Refuge***

‘No Calamity Will Befall Us’

13. What calamities do not befall us, and why?

13 Although this world’s security is breaking down, we put God first and take courage from the psalmist’s words: “Because you said: ‘Jehovah is my refuge,’ you have made the Most High himself your dwelling; no calamity will befall you, and not even a plague will draw near to your tent.” (Psalm 91:9, 10) Yes, Jehovah is our refuge. However, we also make the Most High God ‘our dwelling,’ where we find safety. We laud Jehovah as the Universal Sovereign, ‘dwell’ in him as our Source of security, and declare the good news of his Kingdom. (Matthew 24:14) Therefore, ‘no calamity will befall us’—none of the calamities described earlier in this psalm. Even when we share with others in such calamities as earthquakes, hurricanes, floods, famines, and ravages of warfare, these do not destroy our faith or our spiritual security.

14. As Jehovah’s servants, why are we not infected by deadly plagues?

14 Anointed Christians are like alien residents living in tents apart from this system of things. ([1 Peter 2:11]) ‘Not even a plague draws near their tent.’ Whether our hope is heavenly or earthly, we are no part of the world, and we are not infected by such spiritually deadly plagues as its immorality, materialism, false religion, and worship of “the wild beast” and its “image,” the United Nations.—Revelation 9:20, 21;[13:1-18;][John 17:16].

15. In what respects do we enjoy angelic help?

15 Regarding the protection we enjoy, the psalmist adds: “He [Jehovah] will give his own angels a command concerning you, to guard you in all your ways. Upon their hands they will carry you, that you may not strike your foot against any stone.” (Psalm 91:11, 12) Angels have been given power to protect us. (2 Kings 6:17; Psalm 34:7-9;[104:4;] Matthew 26:53;[Luke 1:19]) They guard us ‘in all our ways.’ (Matthew 18:10) We enjoy angelic guidance and guardianship as Kingdom proclaimers and do not stumble spiritually. (Revelation 14:6, 7) Even ‘stones’ such as bans against our work have not caused us to stumble and fall out of divine favor.

16. How do attacks carried out by a “young lion” and a “cobra” differ, and how do we react to them?

16 The psalmist continues: “Upon the young lion and the cobra you will tread; you will trample down the maned young lion and the big snake.” ([Psalm 91:13]) Just as a young lion makes an open, frontal attack, some of our enemies show their opposition openly by passing laws designed to stop our preaching work. But unexpected attacks like those of a cobra striking from a place of concealment are also made upon us. Hiding behind the scenes, the clergy sometimes attack us through lawmakers, judges, and others. But with Jehovah’s support, we peacefully seek redress in the courts, thus ‘defending and legally establishing the good news.’—Philippians 1:7; Psalm 94:14,[20-22].

17. How do we trample down “the maned young lion”?

17 The psalmist speaks of trampling down “the maned young lion and the big snake.” A maned young lion can be quite fierce, and a big snake can be a reptile of great size. ([Isaiah 31:4]) Regardless of how fierce the maned young lion may be when making a frontal attack, though, we figuratively trample on it by obeying God rather than lionlike men or organizations. ([Acts 5:29]) So the menacing “lion” does not cause us spiritual injury.

18. “The big snake” may remind us of whom, and what do we need to do if we are under attack?

18 In the Greek Septuagint, “the big snake” is called “a dragon.” This may well remind us of “the great dragon . . . , the original serpent, the one called Devil and Satan.” (Revelation 12:7-9; Genesis 3:15) He is like a monstrous reptile capable of crushing and swallowing its prey. (Jeremiah 51:34) When Satan is trying to wrap his coils around us, crush us with this world’s pressures, and swallow us, let us shake ourselves loose and trample down this “big snake.” ([1 Peter 5:8]) The anointed remnant must do this if they are to share in the fulfillment of [Romans 16:20].

Jehovah—Our Source of Salvation

19. Why do we take refuge in Jehovah?

19 Concerning the true worshiper, the psalmist represents God as saying: “Because on me he has set his affection, I shall also provide him with escape. I shall protect him because he has come to know my name.” ([Psalm 91:14]) The phrase “I shall protect him” is literally, “I shall place him on high,” that is, out of reach. We take refuge in Jehovah as his worshipers especially because ‘we have set our affection on him.’ (Mark 12:29, 30;[1 John 4:19]) In turn, God ‘provides us with escape’ from our enemies. Never will we be wiped off the earth. Rather, we will be saved because we know the divine name and call upon it in faith. (Romans 10:11-13) And we are determined to ‘walk in Jehovah’s name forever.’—[Micah 4:5;] Isaiah 43:10-12.

^ par. 13 (Ps. 91:9, 10) Because you said: “Jehovah is my refuge,” You have made the Most High your dwelling;* 10 No disaster will befall you, And no plague will come near your tent.

Or possibly, “fortress; refuge.”

^ par. 13 (Matt. 24:14) And this good news of the Kingdom will be preached in all the inhabited earth for a witness to all the nations, and then the end will come.

^ par. 14 (1 Pet. 2:11) Beloved, I urge you as foreigners and temporary residents to keep abstaining from fleshly desires, which wage war against you.*

Or “the soul.”

^ par. 14 (Rev. 9:20, 21) But the rest of the people who were not killed by these plagues did not repent of the works of their hands; they did not stop worshipping the demons and the idols of gold and silver and copper and stone and wood, which can neither see nor hear nor walk. 21 And they did not repent of their murders nor of their spiritistic practices nor of their sexual immorality* nor of their thefts.

Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

^ par. 14 (Rev. 13:1-18) And it* stood still on the sand of the sea. And I saw a wild beast ascending out of the sea, with ten horns and seven heads, and on its horns ten diadems,* but on its heads blasphemous names. 2 Now the wild beast that I saw was like a leopard, but its feet were like those of a bear, and its mouth was like a lion’s mouth. And the dragon gave to the beast its power and its throne and great authority. 3 I saw that one of its heads seemed to have been fatally wounded, but its mortal wound had been healed, and all the earth followed the wild beast with admiration. 4 And they worshipped the dragon because it gave the authority to the wild beast, and they worshipped the wild beast with the words: “Who is like the wild beast, and who can do battle with it?” 5 It was given a mouth speaking great things and blasphemies, and it was given authority to act for 42 months. 6 And it opened its mouth in blasphemies against God to blaspheme his name and his dwelling place, even those residing in heaven. 7 It was permitted to wage war with the holy ones and conquer them, and it was given authority over every tribe and people and tongue* and nation. 8 And all those who dwell on the earth will worship it. From the founding of the world, not one of their names has been written in the scroll of life of the Lamb who was slaughtered. 9 If anyone has an ear, let him hear. 10 If anyone is meant for captivity, he will go into captivity. If anyone will kill with the sword,* he must be killed with the sword. This is where it calls for endurance and faith on the part of the holy ones. 11 Then I saw another wild beast ascending out of the earth, and it had two horns like a lamb, but it began speaking like a dragon. 12 It exercises all the authority of the first wild beast in its sight. And it makes the earth and its inhabitants worship the first wild beast, whose mortal wound was healed. 13 And it performs great signs, even making fire come down out of heaven to the earth in the sight of mankind. 14 It misleads those who dwell on the earth, because of the signs that it was permitted to perform in the sight of the wild beast, while it tells those who dwell on the earth to make an image to the wild beast that had the sword-stroke and yet revived. 15 And it was permitted to give breath* to the image of the wild beast, so that the image of the wild beast should both speak and cause to be killed all those who refuse to worship the image of the wild beast. 16 It puts under compulsion all people—the small and the great, the rich and the poor, the free and the slaves—that these should be marked on their right hand or on their forehead, 17 and that nobody can buy or sell except a person having the mark, the name of the wild beast or the number of its name. 18 This is where it calls for wisdom: Let the one who has insight calculate the number of the wild beast, for it is a man’s number,* and its number is 666.

That is, the dragon.

Or “royal headbands.”

Or “language.”

Or possibly, “If anyone is to be killed with the sword.”

Or “spirit.”

Or “a human number.”

^ par. 14 (John 17:16) They are no part of the world, just as I am no part of the world.

^ par. 15 (Ps. 91:11, 12) For he will give his angels a command concerning you, To guard you in all your ways. 12 They will carry you on their hands, So that you may not strike your foot against a stone.

^ par. 15 (2 Ki. 6:17) Then E·liʹsha began to pray and say: “O Jehovah, open his eyes, please, that he may see.” Immediately Jehovah opened the attendant’s eyes and he saw, and look! the mountainous region was full of horses and war chariots of fire all around E·liʹsha.

^ par. 15 (Ps. 34:7-9) The angel of Jehovah camps all around those fearing Him, And he rescues them.  8 Taste and see that Jehovah is good; Happy is the man who takes refuge in him.  9 Fear Jehovah, all you his holy ones, For those who fear him lack nothing.

^ par. 15 (Ps. 104:4) He makes his angels spirits, His ministers a consuming fire.

^ par. 15 (Matt. 26:53) Or do you think that I cannot appeal to my Father to supply me at this moment more than 12 legions of angels?

^ par. 15 (Luke 1:19) In reply the angel said to him: “I am Gaʹbri·el, who stands near before God, and I was sent to speak with you and to declare this good news to you.

^ par. 15 (Matt. 18:10) See that you do not despise one of these little ones, for I tell you that their angels in heaven always look upon the face of my Father who is in heaven.

^ par. 15 (Rev. 14:6, 7) And I saw another angel flying in midheaven,* and he had everlasting good news to declare to those who dwell on the earth, to every nation and tribe and tongue* and people. 7 He was saying in a loud voice: “Fear God and give him glory, because the hour of judgment by him has arrived, so worship the One who made the heaven and the earth and the sea and the springs* of water.”

Or “in midair; overhead.”

Or “language.”

Or “fountains.”

^ par. 16 (Ps. 91:13) On the young lion and the cobra you will tread; You will trample underfoot the maned lion and the big snake.

^ par. 16 (Phil. 1:7) It is only right for me to think this regarding all of you, since I have you in my heart, you who are sharers with me in the undeserved kindness both in my prison bonds and in the defending and legally establishing of the good news.

^ par. 16 (Ps. 94:14) For Jehovah will not forsake his people, Nor will he abandon his inheritance.

^ par. 16 (Ps. 94:20-22) Can a throne* of corruption be allied with you While it is framing trouble in the name of the law?* 21 They make vicious attacks on the righteous one* And condemn the innocent one to death.* 22 But Jehovah will become a secure refuge* for me, My God is my rock of refuge.

Or “rulers; judges.”

Or “by decree.”

Or “the soul of the righteous one.”

Lit., “And the blood of the innocent they declare guilty (wicked).”

Or “secure height.”

^ par. 17 (Isa. 31:4) For this is what Jehovah has said to me: “Just as the lion growls, a strong young lion,* over its prey, When a whole group of shepherds is called together against it, And it is not terrified by their voice Or daunted by their commotion, So will Jehovah of armies come down to wage war Over Mount Zion and over her hill.

Or “a maned young lion.”

^ par. 17 (Acts 5:29) In answer Peter and the other apostles said: “We must obey God as ruler rather than men.

^ par. 18 (Rev. 12:7-9) And war broke out in heaven: Miʹcha·el* and his angels battled with the dragon, and the dragon and its angels battled 8 but they did not prevail,* nor was a place found for them any longer in heaven. 9 So down the great dragon was hurled, the original serpent, the one called Devil and Satan, who is misleading the entire inhabited earth; he was hurled down to the earth, and his angels were hurled down with him.

Meaning “Who Is Like God?”

Or possibly, “but it [that is, the dragon] was defeated.”

^ par. 18 (Gen. 3:15) And I will put enmity* between you and the woman and between your offspring* and her offspring.* He will crush* your head, and you will strike* him in the heel.”

Or “hostility.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “bruise; strike.”

Or “bruise; crush.”

^ par. 18 (Jer. 51:34) “King Neb·u·chad·nezʹzar* of Babylon has devoured me; He has thrown me into confusion. He has set me down as an empty vessel. He has swallowed me down like a big snake; He has filled his stomach with my fine things. He has rinsed me away.

Lit., “Nebuchadrezzar,” a variant spelling.

^ par. 18 (1 Pet. 5:8) Keep your senses, be watchful! Your adversary, the Devil, walks about like a roaring lion, seeking to devour someone.*

Or “looking for someone to devour.”

^ par. 18 (Rom. 16:20) For his part, the God who gives peace will crush Satan under your feet shortly. May the undeserved kindness of our Lord Jesus be with you.

^ par. 19 (Ps. 91:14) God said: “Because he has affection for me,* I will rescue him. I will protect him because he knows* my name.

Lit., “he has joined himself to me.”

Or “acknowledges.”

^ par. 19 (Mark 12:29, 30) Jesus answered: “The first is, ‘Hear, O Israel, Jehovah* our God is one Jehovah,* 30 and you must love Jehovah* your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul* and with your whole mind and with your whole strength.’

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

See App. A5.

See Glossary.

^ par. 19 (1 John 4:19) We love, because he first loved us.

^ par. 19 (Rom. 10:11-13) For the scripture says: “No one who rests his faith on him will be disappointed.” 12 For there is no distinction between Jew and Greek. There is the same Lord over all, who is rich* toward all those calling on him. 13 For “everyone who calls on the name of Jehovah* will be saved.”

Or “generous.”

See App. A5.

^ par. 19 (Mic. 4:5) For all the peoples will walk, each in the name of its god, But we will walk in the name of Jehovah our God forever and ever.

^ par. 19 (Isa. 43:10-12) “You are my witnesses,” declares Jehovah, “Yes, my servant whom I have chosen, So that you may know and have faith in me* And understand that I am the same One. Before me no God was formed, And after me there has been none. 11 I—I am Jehovah, and besides me there is no savior.” 12 “I am the One who declared and saved and made known When there was no foreign god among you. So you are my witnesses,” declares Jehovah, “and I am God.

Or “and trust me.”

^ ***w14 10/15 pp. 10-11 Have Unshakable Faith in the Kingdom***

14 Consider what Jehovah promised King David of ancient Israel by means of the Davidic covenant. (Read 2 Samuel 7:12, 16.) Jehovah made this covenant with David during David’s reign in Jerusalem, promising him that the Messiah would be his descendant. ([Luke 1:30-33]) Thus, Jehovah further narrowed the line of descent of the offspring and established that an heir of David would have “the legal right” to the throne of the Messianic Kingdom. (Ezek. 21:25-27) Through Jesus, David’s kingship “will be firmly established forever.” Indeed, David’s offspring “will endure forever; his throne will endure like the sun.” ([Ps. 89:34-37]) Yes, the Messiah’s rule will never become corrupt, and its accomplishments will last forever!

^ par. 14 (2 Sam. 7:12) When your days come to an end and you are laid to rest with your forefathers, then I will raise up your offspring* after you, your own son,* and I will firmly establish his kingdom.

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “one who will come out of your inward parts.”

^ par. 14 (2 Sam. 7:16) Your house and your kingdom will be secure forever before you; your throne will be firmly established forever.”’”

^ par. 14 (Luke 1:30-33) So the angel said to her: “Do not be afraid, Mary, for you have found favor with God. 31 And look! you will become pregnant* and give birth to a son, and you are to name him Jesus. 32 This one will be great and will be called Son of the Most High, and Jehovah* God will give him the throne of David his father, 33 and he will rule as King over the house of Jacob forever, and there will be no end to his Kingdom.”

Or “conceive in your womb.”

See App. A5.

^ par. 14 (Ezek. 21:25-27) “But your day has come, O fatally wounded, wicked chieftain of Israel, the time of your final punishment. 26 This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah says: ‘Remove the turban, and take off the crown. This will not remain the same. Raise up the low one, and bring low the high one. 27 A ruin, a ruin, a ruin I will make it. And it will not belong to anyone until the one who has the legal right comes, and I will give it to him.’

^ par. 14 (Ps. 89:34-37) I will not violate my covenant Or change what my lips have spoken. 35 I have sworn in my holiness, once and for all; I will not tell lies to David. 36 His offspring* will endure forever; His throne will endure like the sun before me. 37 Like the moon, it will be firmly established forever As a faithful witness in the skies.” (Selah)

Lit., “seed.”

^ ***w07 7/15 p. 32 “A Faithful Witness in the Skies”***

Over 3,000 years ago, Jehovah God entered into the Kingdom covenant with King David of ancient Israel. (2 Samuel 7:12-16) The purpose of that covenant was to provide a legal basis for Jesus Christ, as David’s heir, to possess the throne forever. ([Isaiah 9:7;] Luke 1:32, 33) Referring to the throne of David’s “seed,” the psalmist sang: “As the moon it will be firmly established for time indefinite, and as a faithful witness in the skies.”—Psalm 89:36, 37.

The ‘luminary that dominates the night’—the moon—is a fitting reminder of the permanence of Christ’s rule. ([Genesis 1:16]) Concerning his Kingdom, [Daniel 7:14] states: “His rulership is an indefinitely lasting rulership that will not pass away, and his kingdom one that will not be brought to ruin.” The moon is a witness that reminds us of that Kingdom and the blessings it will bestow upon mankind.

^ (2 Sam. 7:12-16) When your days come to an end and you are laid to rest with your forefathers, then I will raise up your offspring* after you, your own son,* and I will firmly establish his kingdom. 13 He is the one who will build a house for my name, and I will firmly establish the throne of his kingdom forever. 14 I will become his father, and he will become my son. When he does wrong, I will reprove him with the rod of men and with the strokes of the sons of men.* 15 My loyal love will not be taken away from him the way I took it away from Saul, whom I removed from before you. 16 Your house and your kingdom will be secure forever before you; your throne will be firmly established forever.”’”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “one who will come out of your inward parts.”

Or possibly, “Adam.”

^ (Isa. 9:7) To the increase of his rulership* And to peace, there will be no end, On the throne of David and on his kingdom In order to establish it firmly and to sustain it Through justice and righteousness, From now on and forever. The zeal of Jehovah of armies will do this.

Or “government; princely rule.”

^ (Luke 1:32, 33) This one will be great and will be called Son of the Most High, and Jehovah* God will give him the throne of David his father, 33 and he will rule as King over the house of Jacob forever, and there will be no end to his Kingdom.”

See App. A5.

^ (Ps. 89:36, 37) His offspring* will endure forever; His throne will endure like the sun before me. 37 Like the moon, it will be firmly established forever As a faithful witness in the skies.” (Selah)

Lit., “seed.”

^ (Gen. 1:16) And God went on to make the two great luminaries, the greater luminary for dominating the day and the lesser luminary for dominating the night, and also the stars.

^ (Dan. 7:14) And to him there were given rulership, honor, and a kingdom, that the peoples, nations, and language groups should all serve him. His rulership is an everlasting rulership that will not pass away, and his kingdom will not be destroyed.

^ ***w06 7/15 p. 13 par. 4 Highlights From Books Three and Four of Psalms***

90:10, 12. Since life is short, we should “count our days.” How? By bringing “a heart of wisdom in,” or by exercising wisdom so that our remaining days are not wasted but are spent in a way that pleases Jehovah. This requires that we set spiritual priorities and use our time wisely.—Ephesians 5:15, 16; Philippians 1:10.

^ par. 4 (Ps. 90:10) The span of our life is 70 years, Or 80 if one is especially strong.* But they are filled with trouble and sorrow; They quickly pass by, and away we fly.

Or “because of special mightiness.”

^ par. 4 (Ps. 90:12) Teach us how to count our days So that we may acquire a heart of wisdom.

^ par. 4 (Eph. 5:15, 16) So keep strict watch that how you walk is not as unwise but as wise persons, 16 making the best use of your time,* because the days are wicked.

Lit., “buying out the appointed time.”

^ par. 4 (Phil. 1:10) that you may make sure of the more important things, so that you may be flawless and not stumbling others up to the day of Christ;

^ ***w01 11/15 p. 13 Jehovah Shows Us How to Count Our Days***

19 The psalmist’s words are a prayer that Jehovah teach his people how to exercise wisdom in valuing and using their remaining days in a God-approved way. A life expectancy of 70 years holds out hope of some 25,500 days. Regardless of our age, though, ‘we do not know what our life will be tomorrow, for we are a mist appearing for a little while and then disappearing.’ (James 4:13-15) Since ‘time and unforeseen occurrence befall us all,’ we cannot say how much longer we will live. Let us therefore pray for wisdom to deal with trials, to treat others properly, and to do our best in Jehovah’s service right now—today! (Ecclesiastes 9:11;[James 1:5-8]) Jehovah guides us by means of his Word, his spirit, and his organization. (Matthew 24:45-47; 1 Corinthians 2:10; 2 Timothy 3:16, 17) The exercise of wisdom moves us to ‘seek first God’s Kingdom’ and to use our days in a way that brings glory to Jehovah and makes his heart rejoice. (Matthew 6:25-33; Proverbs 27:11) Worshiping him wholeheartedly will not remove all our problems, of course, but it certainly results in great joy.

^ par. 19 (Jas. 4:13-15) Come, now, you who say: “Today or tomorrow we will travel to this city and will spend a year there, and we will do business and make some profit,” 14 whereas you do not know what your life will be like tomorrow. For you are a mist that appears for a little while and then disappears. 15 Instead, you should say: “If Jehovah* wills, we will live and do this or that.”

See App. A5.

^ par. 19 (Eccl. 9:11) I have seen something further under the sun, that the swift do not always win the race, nor do the mighty win the battle, nor do the wise always have the food, nor do the intelligent always have the riches, nor do those with knowledge always have success, because time and unexpected events* overtake them all.

Or “unforeseen occurrence.”

^ par. 19 (Jas. 1:5-8) So if any one of you is lacking in wisdom, let him keep asking God, for he gives generously to all and without reproaching,* and it will be given him. 6 But let him keep asking in faith, not doubting at all, for the one who doubts is like a wave of the sea driven by the wind and blown about. 7 In fact, that man should not expect to receive anything from Jehovah;* 8 he is an indecisive man, unsteady in all his ways.

Or “finding fault.”

See App. A5.

^ par. 19 (Matt. 24:45-47) “Who really is the faithful and discreet* slave whom his master appointed over his domestics, to give them their food at the proper time? 46 Happy is that slave if his master on coming finds him doing so! 47 Truly I say to you, he will appoint him over all his belongings.

Or “wise.”

^ par. 19 (1 Cor. 2:10) For it is to us God has revealed them through his spirit, for the spirit searches into all things, even the deep things of God.

^ par. 19 (2 Tim. 3:16, 17) All Scripture is inspired of God and beneficial for teaching, for reproving, for setting things straight,* for disciplining in righteousness, 17 so that the man of God may be fully competent, completely equipped for every good work.

Or “correcting.”

^ par. 19 (Matt. 6:25-33) “On this account I say to you: Stop being anxious about your lives* as to what you will eat or what you will drink, or about your bodies as to what you will wear. Does not life* mean more than food and the body than clothing? 26 Observe intently the birds of heaven; they do not sow seed or reap or gather into storehouses, yet your heavenly Father feeds them. Are you not worth more than they are? 27 Who of you by being anxious can add one cubit* to his life span? 28 Also, why are you anxious about clothing? Take a lesson from the lilies of the field, how they grow; they do not toil, nor do they spin; 29 but I tell you that not even Solʹo·mon in all his glory was arrayed as one of these. 30 Now if this is how God clothes the vegetation of the field that is here today and tomorrow is thrown into the oven, will he not much rather clothe you, you with little faith? 31 So never be anxious and say, ‘What are we to eat?’ or, ‘What are we to drink?’ or, ‘What are we to wear?’ 32 For all these are the things the nations are eagerly pursuing. Your heavenly Father knows that you need all these things. 33 “Keep on, then, seeking first the Kingdom and his righteousness, and all these other things will be added to you.

Or “souls.”

Or “the soul.”

See App. B14.

^ par. 19 (Prov. 27:11) Be wise, my son, and make my heart rejoice, So that I can make a reply to him who taunts me.

^ ***snnw song 141 Searching for Friends of Peace***

Song 141

Searching for Friends of Peace

Download:

Lyrics Only

Lead Sheet

([Luke 10:6])

Jesus commanded: ‘Let the truth be heard.’

In summer heat, on dusty roads,

He let all hear Jehovah’s word.

He loved God’s sheep and called to ev’ryone.

He searched the land

from the sunrise ‘til the day was done.

From door to door and in the street,

We share with ev’ryone we meet

The news that soon man’s troubles

all will be gone.

(CHORUS)

Searching the world

For friends of peace in ev’ry nation,

Searching to find

A heart inclined toward salvation,

Wanting to leave

No stone unturned.

Time waits for no one, so the search goes on.

A million hearts, a million lives,

We give our all to save just one.

Love is the force that makes us call again.

A wounded heart can be healed,

and broken lives can mend.

We search the towns and city squares,

And when we find someone who cares,

The joy we feel inspires us to go on.

(CHORUS)

Searching the world

For friends of peace in ev’ry nation,

Searching to find

A heart inclined toward salvation,

Wanting to leave

No stone unturned.

(See also [Isa. 52:7;] Matt. 28:19, 20;[Luke 8:1;][Rom. 10:10].)

^ (Luke 10:6) And if a friend of peace is there, your peace will rest upon him. But if there is not, it will return to you.

^ (Isa. 52:7) How beautiful on the mountains are the feet of the one bringing good news, The one proclaiming peace, The one bringing good news of something better, The one proclaiming salvation, The one saying to Zion: “Your God has become King!”

^ (Matt. 28:19, 20) Go, therefore, and make disciples of people of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the holy spirit, 20 teaching them to observe all the things I have commanded you. And look! I am with you all the days until the conclusion of the system of things.”*

Or “the age.” See Glossary.

^ (Luke 8:1) Shortly afterward he traveled from city to city and from village to village, preaching and declaring the good news of the Kingdom of God. And the Twelve were with him,

^ (Rom. 10:10) For with the heart one exercises faith for righteousness, but with the mouth one makes public declaration for salvation.

^ ***ia pp. 180-183 He Fought Against Fear and Doubt***

1-3. What had Peter witnessed during an eventful day, and what kind of night was he experiencing?

PETER strained against the oar and peered into the night. Was that a faint glow he saw on the eastern horizon, a sign of dawn at last? The muscles of his back and shoulders burned from long hours of rowing. The wind that whipped his hair about had churned the Sea of Galilee into a rage. Wave after wave crashed against the prow of the fishing boat, soaking him with cold spray. He rowed on.

2 Somewhere back there on shore, Peter and his companions had left Jesus by himself. That day, they had seen Jesus feed a hungry crowd of thousands with just a few loaves and fish. The people responded by seeking to make Jesus king, but he wanted no part of politics. He was also determined to keep his followers from cultivating such ambitions. Evading the crowds, he compelled his disciples to board the boat and head for the opposite shore while he went up into the mountain alone to pray.—[Mark 6:35-45]; read John 6:14-17.

3 The moon, nearly full, had been high overhead when the disciples set out; now it was sinking slowly toward the western horizon. Yet, they had managed to travel only a few miles. The exertion and the constant roar of the wind and the waves made conversation difficult. Likely, Peter was alone with his thoughts.

In two years, Peter had learned a great deal from Jesus, but he still had much to learn

4. What struggles make Peter’s example an outstanding one for us to imitate?

4 How much there was to think about! Peter had first met Jesus of Nazareth over two eventful years earlier. He had learned a great deal, but he still had much to learn. His willingness to do so—to struggle against such obstacles as doubt and fear—make him an outstanding example for us to imitate. Let us see why.

“We Have Found the Messiah”!

5, 6. What kind of life did Peter lead?

5 Peter would never forget the day he met Jesus. His brother, Andrew, had first brought him the astounding news: “We have found the Messiah.” With those words, Peter’s life began to change. It would never again be the same.—[John 1:41].

6 Peter lived in Capernaum, a city on the northern shore of a freshwater lake called the Sea of Galilee. He and Andrew were partners with James and John, the sons of Zebedee, in a fishing business. Living with Peter were not only his wife but also his mother-in-law and his brother, Andrew. To support such a household by fishing surely required hard work, energy, and resourcefulness. We can imagine the countless long nights of labor—the men letting out the dragnets between two boats and hauling aboard whatever catch the lake afforded. We can also picture toilsome daylight hours as the fish were sorted and sold, the nets mended and cleaned.

7. What did Peter come to hear about Jesus, and why was the news thrilling?

7 Andrew, the Bible tells us, was a disciple of John the Baptist. Peter surely listened to his brother’s reports about John’s message with intense interest. One day, Andrew saw John point out Jesus of Nazareth and say: “See, the Lamb of God!” Andrew immediately became a follower of Jesus and eagerly told Peter this thrilling news: The Messiah had arrived! ([John 1:35-40]) After the rebellion in Eden some 4,000 years earlier, Jehovah God had promised that a special individual would come to provide real hope for mankind. ([Gen. 3:15]) Andrew had met this very Rescuer, the Messiah himself! Peter hurried off to meet Jesus as well.

8. What was the meaning of the name Jesus bestowed on Peter, and why do some still question that choice of a name?

8 Until that day, Peter was known by the name Simon, or Simeon. But Jesus looked at him and said: “‘You are Simon the son of John; you will be called Cephas’ (which is translated Peter).” ([John 1:42]) “Cephas” is a common noun meaning “stone,” or “rock.” Evidently, Jesus’ words were prophetic. He foresaw that Peter would become like a rock—a stable, sturdy, and reliable influence among Christ’s followers. Did Peter see himself that way? It seems doubtful. Even some modern-day readers of the Gospel accounts see little that is rocklike in Peter. Some have suggested that his character as revealed in the Bible record seems to be unsteady, inconstant, vacillating.

9. What do Jehovah and his Son look for, and why, do you think, should we trust their point of view?

9 Peter did have his faults. Jesus was not blind to those. But Jesus, like his Father, Jehovah, was always looking for the good in people. Jesus saw much potential in Peter, and He sought to help him build on those good qualities. Jehovah and his Son look for the good in us today too. We may have a hard time believing that there is much good in us for them to find. However, we need to trust their viewpoint and prove ourselves willing to be trained and molded, as Peter was.—Read 1 John 3:19, 20.

“Stop Being Afraid”

10. What did Peter likely witness, yet to what did he return?

10 Peter likely accompanied Jesus on part of the preaching tour that ensued. He may thus have seen Jesus perform his first miracle, that of turning water into wine at the wedding feast in Cana. More important, he heard Jesus’ marvelous and hope-filled message about the Kingdom of God. Still, he tore himself away and returned to his fishing business. Some months later, though, Peter was again face-to-face with Jesus—and this time Jesus invited Peter to follow him full-time as a way of life.

11, 12. (a) What kind of night’s work had Peter endured? (b) Listening to Jesus likely brought what questions to Peter’s mind?

11 Peter had just endured a discouraging night’s work. Again and again, the fishermen had let down their nets, only to haul them in empty. Peter surely brought all his experience and ingenuity to bear on the problem, trying various spots in the lake to find where the fish were feeding. No doubt, there were times when he, like so many fishermen, wished he could peer right into the murky waters to find the schools of fish or somehow will them into his nets. Of course, such thoughts could only deepen his frustration. This was no pleasure sport for Peter; people depended on him to catch fish. Finally, he came ashore empty-handed. The nets had to be cleaned. He was thus busily engaged when Jesus approached.

Peter never tired of hearing Jesus develop the central theme of his preaching—the Kingdom of God

12 A crowd was pressing in on Jesus, eagerly taking in his every word. Hemmed in by them, Jesus got into Peter’s boat and asked him to pull away a bit from land. With his voice carrying clearly over the water, Jesus taught the crowd. Peter listened with rapt attention, as did those ashore. He never tired of hearing Jesus develop the central theme of his preaching—the Kingdom of God. What a privilege it would be to help the Christ spread this message of hope throughout the land! But would that be practical? How would Peter feed his family? Perhaps Peter thought again of the long and fruitless night behind him.—[Luke 5:1-3].

^ par. 2 (Mark 6:35-45) By now the hour had grown late, and his disciples came up to him and said: “This place is isolated, and the hour is already late. 36 Send them away, so that they may go off into the surrounding countryside and villages and buy themselves something to eat.” 37 He replied to them: “You give them something to eat.” At this they said to him: “Should we go off and buy 200 de·narʹi·i* worth of bread and give it to the people to eat?” 38 He said to them: “How many loaves do you have? Go see!” After finding out, they said: “Five, besides two fish.” 39 And he instructed all the people to recline in groups on the green grass. 40 So they reclined in groups of 100 and of 50. 41 Taking now the five loaves and the two fish, he looked up to heaven and said a blessing. Then he broke the loaves up and began giving them to the disciples to place them before the people, and he divided up the two fish for all. 42 So they all ate and were satisfied, 43 and they took up 12 baskets full of fragments, aside from the fish. 44 Those who ate the loaves were 5,000 men. 45 Then, without delay, he made his disciples board the boat and go on ahead to the opposite shore toward Beth·saʹi·da, while he himself sent the crowd away.

See App. B14.

^ par. 2 (John 6:14-17) When the people saw the sign he performed, they began to say: “This really is the Prophet who was to come into the world.” 15 Then Jesus, knowing that they were about to come and seize him to make him king, withdrew again to the mountain all alone. 16 When evening fell, his disciples went down to the sea, 17 and boarding a boat, they set out across the sea for Ca·perʹna·um. By now it had grown dark, and Jesus had not yet come to them.

^ par. 5 (John 1:41) He first found his own brother Simon and said to him: “We have found the Mes·siʹah” (which means, when translated, “Christ”),

^ par. 7 (John 1:35-40) Again the next day, John was standing with two of his disciples, 36 and as he looked at Jesus walking, he said: “See, the Lamb of God!” 37 When the two disciples heard him say this, they followed Jesus. 38 Then Jesus turned, and seeing them following, he said to them: “What are you looking for?” They said to him: “Rabbi (which means, when translated, “Teacher”), where are you staying?” 39 He said to them: “Come, and you will see.” So they went and saw where he was staying, and they stayed with him that day; it was about the tenth hour.* 40 Andrew, the brother of Simon Peter, was one of the two who heard what John said and followed Jesus.

That is, about 4:00 p.m.

^ par. 7 (Gen. 3:15) And I will put enmity* between you and the woman and between your offspring* and her offspring.* He will crush* your head, and you will strike* him in the heel.”

Or “hostility.”

Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “seed.”

Or “bruise; strike.”

Or “bruise; crush.”

^ par. 8 (John 1:42) and he led him to Jesus. When Jesus looked at him, he said: “You are Simon, the son of John; you will be called Ceʹphas” (which is translated “Peter”).

^ par. 9 (1 John 3:19, 20) By this we will know that we originate with the truth, and we will assure* our hearts before him 20 regarding whatever our hearts may condemn us in, because God is greater than our hearts and knows all things.

Or “persuade; convince.”

^ par. 12 (Luke 5:1-3) On one occasion when the crowd was pressing in on him and listening to the word of God, he was standing by the lake of Gen·nesʹa·ret.* 2 And he saw two boats docked at the lakeside, but the fishermen had got out of them and were washing off their nets. 3 Going aboard one of the boats, which was Simon’s, he asked him to pull away a bit from land. Then he sat down, and he began teaching the crowds from the boat.

That is, the Sea of Galilee.

^ ***snnw song 137 Grant Us Boldness***

Song 137

Grant Us Boldness

Download:

Lyrics Only

Lead Sheet

([Acts 4:29])

As we tell about the Kingdom,

As we witness for your name,

There are many who oppose us

And who try to bring us shame.

But instead of fearing men,

It’s really you we must obey.

So we beg you now for your spirit;

O Jehovah, hear what we pray.

(CHORUS)

Grant us boldness as we witness;

Help us overcome our fear.

Give us confidence and courage

So that all the world may hear.

Armageddon draws ever near,

But until that great day is here,

Grant us boldness as we witness.

This is our prayer.

Even though we may be fearful,

You remember we are dust.

Your assurance to support us

Is a promise we can trust.

Give attention to the threats

Of those who persecute and blame.

May you help us all to continue

As we boldly speak in your name.

(CHORUS)

Grant us boldness as we witness;

Help us overcome our fear.

Give us confidence and courage

So that all the world may hear.

Armageddon draws ever near,

But until that great day is here,

Grant us boldness as we witness.

This is our prayer.

(See also 1 Thess. 2:2;[Heb. 10:35].)

^ (Acts 4:29) And now, Jehovah,* give attention to their threats, and grant to your slaves to keep speaking your word with all boldness,

See App. A5.

^ (1 Thess. 2:2) For although we had first suffered and been insolently treated in Phi·lipʹpi, as you know, we mustered up boldness* by means of our God to tell you the good news of God in the face of much opposition.*

Or “courage.”

Or possibly, “amid much struggling.”

^ (Heb. 10:35) Therefore, do not throw away your boldness,* which will be richly rewarded.

Lit., “freeness of speech.”

^ (Pss. 102:0-105:45) A prayer of the oppressed one when he is in despair* and pours out his concern before Jehovah. 102 O Jehovah, hear my prayer; Let my cry for help reach you.  2 Do not hide your face from me in my time of distress. Incline your ear* to me; Do answer me quickly when I call.  3 For my days are vanishing like smoke, And my bones are charred like a fireplace.  4 My heart has been struck down like grass and has withered, For I forget to eat my food.  5 Because of my loud groaning, My bones cling to my flesh.  6 I resemble the pelican of the wilderness; I am like a little owl among the ruins.  7 I lie awake;* I am like a solitary bird on a roof.  8 All day long my enemies taunt me. Those who mock me* use my name as a curse.  9 For I eat ashes as my bread, And my drink is mingled with tears, 10 Because of your anger and your indignation, For you lifted me up only to cast me aside. 11 My days are like a fading shadow,* And I am withering like grass. 12 But you remain forever, O Jehovah, And your fame* will endure for all generations. 13 Surely you will rise up and show mercy on Zion, For it is time to show her your favor; The appointed time has come. 14 For your servants find pleasure in her stones And have affection even for her dust. 15 The nations will fear the name of Jehovah, And all the kings of the earth your glory. 16 For Jehovah will rebuild Zion; He will appear in his glory. 17 He will pay attention to the prayer of the destitute; He will not despise their prayer. 18 This is written for the future generation, So that a people yet to be brought forth* will praise Jah. 19 For he looks down from his holy height, From the heavens Jehovah views the earth, 20 To hear the sighing of the prisoner, To release those sentenced to death, 21 So that the name of Jehovah will be declared in Zion And his praise in Jerusalem, 22 When the peoples and kingdoms Gather together to serve Jehovah. 23 He prematurely robbed me of my strength; He cut short my days. 24 I said: “O my God, Do not do away with me in the middle of my life, You whose years span all generations. 25 Long ago you laid the foundations of the earth, And the heavens are the work of your hands. 26 They will perish, but you will remain; Just like a garment they will all wear out. Just like clothing you will replace them, and they will pass away. 27 But you are the same, and your years will never end. 28 The children of your servants will dwell securely, And their offspring will be firmly established before you.”

Of David. 103 Let me* praise Jehovah; Let everything within me praise his holy name.  2 Let me* praise Jehovah; May I never forget all that he has done.  3 He forgives all your errors And heals all your ailments;  4 He reclaims your life from the pit* And crowns you with his loyal love and mercy.  5 He satisfies you with good things all your life, So that your youth is renewed like that of an eagle.  6 Jehovah acts with righteousness and justice For all who are oppressed.  7 He made known his ways to Moses, His deeds to the sons of Israel.  8 Jehovah is merciful and compassionate,* Slow to anger and abundant in loyal love.*  9 He will not always find fault, Nor will he stay resentful forever. 10 He has not dealt with us according to our sins, Nor has he repaid us what our errors deserve. 11 For as the heavens are higher than the earth, So great is his loyal love toward those who fear him. 12 As far off as the sunrise is from the sunset, So far off from us he has put our transgressions. 13 As a father shows mercy to his sons, Jehovah has shown mercy to those who fear him. 14 For he well knows how we are formed, Remembering that we are dust. 15 As for mortal man, his days are like those of grass; He blooms like a blossom of the field. 16 But when a wind blows, it is no more, As though it was never there.* 17 But the loyal love of Jehovah is for all eternity* Toward those who fear him, And his righteousness toward their children’s children, 18 Toward those who keep his covenant And those who are careful to observe his orders. 19 Jehovah has firmly established his throne in the heavens; And his kingship rules over everything. 20 Praise Jehovah, all you his angels, mighty in power, Who carry out his word, obeying his voice.* 21 Praise Jehovah, all his armies, His ministers who do his will. 22 Praise Jehovah, all his works, In all the places where he rules.* Let my whole being* praise Jehovah.

104 Let me* praise Jehovah. O Jehovah my God, you are very great. With majesty* and splendor you are clothed.  2 You are wrapped in light as with a garment; You stretch out the heavens like a tent cloth.  3 He lays beams of his upper rooms in the waters above,* Making the clouds his chariot, Moving on the wings of the wind.  4 He makes his angels spirits, His ministers a consuming fire.  5 He has established the earth on its foundations; It will not be moved from its place* forever and ever.  6 You covered it with deep waters as with a garment. The waters stood above the mountains.  7 At your rebuke they fled; At the sound of your thunder they ran away in panic  8 —Mountains ascended and valleys descended— To the place you established for them.  9 You set a boundary that they should not pass, That they should never again cover the earth. 10 He sends springs into the valleys;* Between the mountains they flow. 11 They provide water for all the wild beasts of the field; The wild donkeys quench their thirst. 12 Above them roost the birds of the sky; They sing among the thick foliage. 13 He is watering the mountains from his upper rooms. With the fruitage of your works the earth is satisfied. 14 He is making grass grow for the cattle And vegetation for mankind’s use, To grow food from the land 15 And wine that makes man’s heart rejoice, Oil that makes the face shine, And bread that sustains the heart of mortal man. 16 The trees of Jehovah are satisfied, The cedars of Lebʹa·non that he planted, 17 Where the birds make nests. The home of the stork is in the juniper trees. 18 The high mountains are for the mountain goats; The crags are a refuge for the rock badgers. 19 He has made the moon to mark the appointed times; The sun well knows when to set. 20 You bring darkness, and night falls, When all the wild animals of the forest roam about. 21 The young lions* roar for their prey And seek their food from God. 22 When the sun rises, They withdraw and lie down in their dens. 23 Man goes to his work, And he labors until evening. 24 How many your works are, O Jehovah! You have made all of them in wisdom. The earth is full of what you have made. 25 There is the sea, so great and wide, Teeming with countless living things, both small and great. 26 There the ships travel, And Le·viʹa·than,* which you formed to play in it. 27 All of them wait for you To give them their food in its season. 28 What you give them, they gather. When you open your hand, they are satisfied with good things. 29 When you hide your face, they are disturbed. If you take away their spirit, they die and return to the dust. 30 If you send out your spirit, they are created, And you renew the surface of the ground. 31 The glory of Jehovah will last forever. Jehovah will rejoice in his works. 32 He looks at the earth, and it trembles; He touches the mountains, and they smoke. 33 I will sing to Jehovah throughout my life; I will sing praises* to my God as long as I live. 34 Let my thoughts be pleasing to him.* I will rejoice in Jehovah. 35 The sinners will vanish from the earth, And the wicked will no longer exist. Let me* praise Jehovah. Praise Jah!*

105 Give thanks to Jehovah, call on his name, Make his deeds known among the peoples!  2 Sing to him, sing praises* to him, Ponder over* all his wonderful works.  3 Boast about his holy name. Let the hearts of those seeking Jehovah rejoice.  4 Search for Jehovah and his strength. Seek his face* constantly.  5 Remember the wonderful works he has performed, His miracles and the judgments he has pronounced,  6 You offspring* of Abraham his servant, You sons of Jacob, his chosen ones.  7 He is Jehovah our God. His judgments are throughout the earth.  8 He remembers his covenant forever, The promise he made,* to a thousand generations,  9 The covenant he made with Abraham, And the oath he swore to Isaac, 10 Which he established as a decree to Jacob And as a lasting covenant to Israel, 11 Saying, “I will give you the land of Caʹnaan As your allotted inheritance.” 12 This was when they were few in number, Yes, very few, and they were foreigners in the land. 13 They walked about from nation to nation, From one kingdom to another people. 14 He did not allow any man to oppress them, But on their account he reproved kings, 15 Saying, “Do not touch my anointed ones, And to my prophets do nothing bad.” 16 He called down a famine on the land; He cut off their supply of bread.* 17 He sent ahead of them a man Who was sold to be a slave, Joseph. 18 With fetters they bound* his feet, His neck was put in irons;* 19 Until the time that his word proved true, The saying of Jehovah is what refined him. 20 The king sent to release him, The ruler of the peoples set him free. 21 He made him master of his household, Ruler over all his property, 22 To have authority over* his princes as he pleased* And to teach his elders wisdom. 23 Then Israel came into Egypt, And Jacob lived as a foreigner in the land of Ham. 24 God made his people very fruitful; He made them mightier than their adversaries, 25 Whose hearts he let change to hate his people, To plot against his servants. 26 He sent his servant Moses, And Aaron, whom he had chosen. 27 They performed his signs among them, His miracles in the land of Ham. 28 He sent darkness and the land became dark; They did not rebel against his words. 29 He changed their waters into blood And killed their fish. 30 Their land swarmed with frogs, Even in the royal chambers. 31 He ordered the gadflies to invade And gnats in all their territories. 32 He turned their rain to hail And sent lightning* on their land. 33 He struck their vines and their fig trees And shattered the trees of their territory. 34 He said that the locusts should invade, Young locusts without number. 35 They devoured all the vegetation in the land, And they devoured the produce of the ground. 36 Then he struck down every firstborn in their land, The beginning of their procreative power. 37 He brought his people out with silver and gold; And no one among his tribes stumbled. 38 Egypt rejoiced when they left, For the dread of Israel* had fallen on them. 39 He spread a cloud to screen them off And fire to give light by night. 40 They asked, and he brought quail; He kept satisfying them with bread from heaven. 41 He opened a rock, and waters flowed out; These flowed through the desert like a river. 42 For he remembered the holy promise he had made to Abraham his servant. 43 So he brought out his people with exultation, His chosen ones with a joyful cry. 44 He gave them the lands of nations; They inherited what other peoples had worked hard to produce, 45 So that they would keep his decrees And observe his laws. Praise Jah!*

Or “he grows weak.”

Or “Bend down and listen.”

Or possibly, “I am emaciated.”

Or “make a fool of me.”

Or “a lengthening shadow.”

Or “name.” Lit., “memorial.”

Lit., “be created.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “grave.”

Or “gracious.”

Or “loving-kindness.”

Lit., “And its place no longer knows it.”

Or “from eternity to eternity.”

Lit., “hearing the voice (sound) of his word.”

Or “the places of his sovereignty.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “dignity.”

Lit., “in the waters.”

Or “will not totter.”

Or “wadis.”

Or “maned young lions.”

See Glossary.

Or “make music.”

Or possibly, “Let my meditation about him be pleasurable.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “make music.”

Or possibly, “Speak about.”

Or “presence.”

Or “descendants.” Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “The word he commanded.”

Lit., “broke every bread rod.” Possibly referring to rods used for storing bread.

Lit., “afflicted.”

Or “His soul came into iron.”

Lit., “To bind.”

Or “agreeably to his soul.”

Or “flames of fire.”

Lit., “them.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

^ (Ps. 105:24-45) God made his people very fruitful; He made them mightier than their adversaries, 25 Whose hearts he let change to hate his people, To plot against his servants. 26 He sent his servant Moses, And Aaron, whom he had chosen. 27 They performed his signs among them, His miracles in the land of Ham. 28 He sent darkness and the land became dark; They did not rebel against his words. 29 He changed their waters into blood And killed their fish. 30 Their land swarmed with frogs, Even in the royal chambers. 31 He ordered the gadflies to invade And gnats in all their territories. 32 He turned their rain to hail And sent lightning* on their land. 33 He struck their vines and their fig trees And shattered the trees of their territory. 34 He said that the locusts should invade, Young locusts without number. 35 They devoured all the vegetation in the land, And they devoured the produce of the ground. 36 Then he struck down every firstborn in their land, The beginning of their procreative power. 37 He brought his people out with silver and gold; And no one among his tribes stumbled. 38 Egypt rejoiced when they left, For the dread of Israel* had fallen on them. 39 He spread a cloud to screen them off And fire to give light by night. 40 They asked, and he brought quail; He kept satisfying them with bread from heaven. 41 He opened a rock, and waters flowed out; These flowed through the desert like a river. 42 For he remembered the holy promise he had made to Abraham his servant. 43 So he brought out his people with exultation, His chosen ones with a joyful cry. 44 He gave them the lands of nations; They inherited what other peoples had worked hard to produce, 45 So that they would keep his decrees And observe his laws. Praise Jah!*

Or “flames of fire.”

Lit., “them.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

^ ***sn song 80 The Quality of Goodness***

Song 80

The Quality of Goodness

([Psalm 119:66])

1. Knowing goodness from Jehovah

Is a joy through all our days.

As our Father in the heavens,

He is good in all his ways.

Showing favor, granting mercy,

Far beyond what we deserve;

He is worthy of our worship

And the One we gladly serve.

2. In his likeness he has made us

So that we might cultivate

All the virtues he possesses

And his goodness imitate.

May we grow in godly goodness,

In his virtues may we share.

Let us pray for holy spirit,

That its fruitage we might bear.

3. Those to whom we are related

In the faith—our brotherhood—

We will show them special favor,

But to all may we do good.

As we share the Kingdom good news

And our hope with all we meet,

May we always be impartial;

May our goodness be complete.

(See also [Ps. 103:10;][Mark 10:18;][Gal. 5:22;][Eph. 5:9].)

^ (Ps. 119:66) Teach me good sense and knowledge, For I have put my trust in your commandments.

^ (Ps. 103:10) He has not dealt with us according to our sins, Nor has he repaid us what our errors deserve.

^ (Mark 10:18) Jesus said to him: “Why do you call me good? Nobody is good except one, God.

^ (Gal. 5:22) On the other hand, the fruitage of the spirit is love, joy, peace, patience,* kindness, goodness, faith,

Or “long-suffering.”

^ (Eph. 5:9) for the fruitage of the light consists of every sort of goodness and righteousness and truth.

^ ***w13 6/15 p. 20 Appreciate Jehovah’s Loyalty and Forgiveness***

14. How can we gain comfort from meditating on Jehovah’s forgiveness? Give an example.

14 We can gain comfort from meditating on Jehovah’s forgiveness. Consider an example. Many years ago, a sister whom we will call Elaine was disfellowshipped. Several years later, she was reinstated. “Although I told myself and others that I believed that I was forgiven by Jehovah,” admits Elaine, “I always felt that somehow he was at a distance or that others were closer to him and that he was more real to them.” However, Elaine drew comfort from reading and meditating on some of the word pictures that the Bible uses to describe Jehovah’s forgiveness. “I felt Jehovah’s love and tenderness toward me in a way that I had never realized before,” Elaine adds. She was especially moved by this thought: “When Jehovah forgives our sins, we need not feel that we bear the stain of such sins for the rest of our life.”* Elaine says: “I realized that I had not believed that Jehovah could fully forgive me, and I thought that I would carry this burden for the rest of my life. I know that it will take time, but I am starting to feel that I really can draw closer to Jehovah, and I feel that a weight has been lifted off me.” What a loving and forgiving God we serve!—[Ps. 103:9].

^ par. 14 (Ps. 103:9) He will not always find fault, Nor will he stay resentful forever.

^ par. 14 See paragraph 10 in chapter 26 of the book Draw Close to Jehovah.

^ ***w12 7/15 p. 16 Serve the God of Freedom***

17. Why should we not get downhearted about our imperfections, and what help does Jehovah provide?

17 At times, of course, we all make mistakes. ([Eccl. 7:20]) When that occurs, do not feel worthless or overly discouraged. If you stumble, so to speak, get up and move forward—even if that means asking the local elders for help. Their “prayer of faith,” wrote James, “will make the indisposed one well, and Jehovah will raise him up. Also, if he has committed sins, it will be forgiven him.” ([Jas. 5:15]) Yes, never forget that God is truly merciful and that he drew you into the congregation because he saw your potential. (Read Psalm 103:8, 9.) So as long as you maintain a complete heart toward Jehovah, he will never give up on you.—1 Chron. 28:9.

^ par. 17 (Eccl. 7:20) For there is no righteous man on earth who always does good and never sins.

^ par. 17 (Jas. 5:15) And the prayer of faith will make the sick one* well, and Jehovah* will raise him up. Also, if he has committed sins, he will be forgiven.

Or possibly, “tired one.”

See App. A5.

^ par. 17 (Ps. 103:8, 9) Jehovah is merciful and compassionate,* Slow to anger and abundant in loyal love.*  9 He will not always find fault, Nor will he stay resentful forever.

Or “gracious.”

Or “loving-kindness.”

^ par. 17 (1 Chron. 28:9) “And you, Solʹo·mon my son, know the God of your father and serve him with a complete* heart and with a delightful* soul,* for Jehovah searches through all hearts, and he discerns every inclination of the thoughts. If you search for him, he will let himself be found by you, but if you leave him, he will reject you forever.

Or “completely devoted.”

Or “willing.”

See Glossary.

^ ***w15 4/15 p. 26 Always Trust in Jehovah!***

8. What does Jehovah promise with regard to our personal limitations?

8 Another factor is that Jehovah is fully aware of our limitations. ([Ps. 103:14]) Therefore, he does not expect us to endure in our own strength but offers us his fatherly help. Of course, at times, we might feel that we cannot go on anymore. But Jehovah assures us that he will never allow his servants to suffer beyond their limit of endurance. Yes, he will “make the way out.” (Read 1 Corinthians 10:13.) Therefore, we have good reason to trust that Jehovah’s assessment of what we can bear is right.

^ par. 8 (Ps. 103:14) For he well knows how we are formed, Remembering that we are dust.

^ par. 8 (1 Cor. 10:13) No temptation has come upon you except what is common to men. But God is faithful, and he will not let you be tempted beyond what you can bear, but along with the temptation he will also make the way out so that you may be able to endure it.

^ ***w13 6/15 pp. 15-16 Appreciate Jehovah’s Generosity and Reasonableness***

16 Well, imagine that you are an Israelite and quite poor. As you arrive at the tabernacle with a little flour to offer as a sacrifice, you notice wealthier Israelites bringing livestock. You might feel embarrassed about your seemingly insignificant sacrifice of flour. Then you remember that in Jehovah’s eyes, your offering is significant. Why? For one thing, Jehovah required that the flour be of high quality. In effect, Jehovah was saying to poorer Israelites: ‘I realize that you cannot offer as much as others can, but I also know that what you are giving me is your best.’ Truly, Jehovah displays reasonableness by taking into account his servants’ limitations and their circumstances.—[Ps. 103:14].

^ par. 16 (Ps. 103:14) For he well knows how we are formed, Remembering that we are dust.

^ ***w10 11/15 p. 25 Jehovah Is Our Sovereign Lord!***

5. Why should we be moved to uphold Jehovah’s sovereignty?

5 As the Creator, Jehovah God is the Sovereign of the earth and the entire universe. (Read Revelation 4:11.) Jehovah is also our Judge, Statute-Giver, and King, for within himself he combines the judicial, legislative, and executive branches of universal government. ([Isa. 33:22]) Since we owe our very existence to God and are dependent on him, we should view him as our Sovereign Lord. We will be motivated to uphold his lofty position if we always bear in mind that “Jehovah himself has firmly established his throne in the very heavens; and over everything his own kingship has held domination.”—[Ps. 103:19;][Acts 4:24].

^ par. 5 (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

^ par. 5 (Isa. 33:22) For Jehovah is our Judge, Jehovah is our Lawgiver, Jehovah is our King; He is the One who will save us.

^ par. 5 (Ps. 103:19) Jehovah has firmly established his throne in the heavens; And his kingship rules over everything.

^ par. 5 (Acts 4:24) On hearing this, they raised their voices with one accord to God and said: “Sovereign Lord, you are the One who made the heaven and the earth and the sea and all the things in them,

^ ***w07 12/1 p. 21 Jehovah’s Sovereignty and the Kingdom of God***

1. Why is Jehovah the rightful Sovereign of the universe?

“JEHOVAH himself has firmly established his throne in the very heavens; and over everything his own kingship has held domination.” ([Psalm 103:19]) With those words, the psalmist pointed to the fundamental concept of rulership. Jehovah God, being the Creator, is rightfully the Sovereign Ruler of the universe.

^ par. 1 (Ps. 103:19) Jehovah has firmly established his throne in the heavens; And his kingship rules over everything.

^ ***w14 3/15 p. 16 How to Maintain a Positive Viewpoint***

THE “PRAYER OF THE OPPRESSED ONE”

19. What situation did the writer of [Psalm 102] face?

19 The writer of [Psalm 102] was desperate. He was “oppressed,” suffering great physical or emotional distress, and he lacked the strength to deal with his problems. ([Ps. 102], superscription) We find in his words an indication that he was absorbed in his pain, loneliness, and personal feelings. (Ps. 102:3, 4,[6,][11]) He believed that Jehovah wanted to cast him aside.—[Ps. 102:10].

20. How can prayer help someone who battles negative thoughts?

20 Yet, the psalmist could still use his life to praise Jehovah. (Read Psalm 102:19-21.) As we see from [Psalm 102], even those who are in the faith can be in pain and be struggling to focus on anything else. The psalmist felt “like a solitary bird on a roof,” as if he had only his troubles for company. ([Ps. 102:7]) If you ever feel that way, pour out your heart to Jehovah as the psalmist did. The prayers of the oppressed one—your prayers—can help you as you battle negative thoughts. Jehovah promises that “he will pay attention to the prayer of the destitute; he will not despise their prayer.” ([Ps. 102:17]) Trust that promise.

21. How might one who is battling negative feelings gain a more positive viewpoint?

21 [Psalm 102] also shows how you might gain a more positive viewpoint. The psalmist did so by shifting attention to his relationship with Jehovah. ([Ps. 102:12,][27]) He found comfort in knowing that Jehovah would always be there to sustain His people through trials. So if negative feelings temporarily keep you from doing as much as you want to in God’s service, pray about it. Ask God to hear your prayer not only so that you may experience some relief from your distress but also “so that the name of Jehovah will be declared.”—Ps. 102:20, 21.

^ (Ps. 102:0-28) A prayer of the oppressed one when he is in despair* and pours out his concern before Jehovah. 102 O Jehovah, hear my prayer; Let my cry for help reach you.  2 Do not hide your face from me in my time of distress. Incline your ear* to me; Do answer me quickly when I call.  3 For my days are vanishing like smoke, And my bones are charred like a fireplace.  4 My heart has been struck down like grass and has withered, For I forget to eat my food.  5 Because of my loud groaning, My bones cling to my flesh.  6 I resemble the pelican of the wilderness; I am like a little owl among the ruins.  7 I lie awake;* I am like a solitary bird on a roof.  8 All day long my enemies taunt me. Those who mock me* use my name as a curse.  9 For I eat ashes as my bread, And my drink is mingled with tears, 10 Because of your anger and your indignation, For you lifted me up only to cast me aside. 11 My days are like a fading shadow,* And I am withering like grass. 12 But you remain forever, O Jehovah, And your fame* will endure for all generations. 13 Surely you will rise up and show mercy on Zion, For it is time to show her your favor; The appointed time has come. 14 For your servants find pleasure in her stones And have affection even for her dust. 15 The nations will fear the name of Jehovah, And all the kings of the earth your glory. 16 For Jehovah will rebuild Zion; He will appear in his glory. 17 He will pay attention to the prayer of the destitute; He will not despise their prayer. 18 This is written for the future generation, So that a people yet to be brought forth* will praise Jah. 19 For he looks down from his holy height, From the heavens Jehovah views the earth, 20 To hear the sighing of the prisoner, To release those sentenced to death, 21 So that the name of Jehovah will be declared in Zion And his praise in Jerusalem, 22 When the peoples and kingdoms Gather together to serve Jehovah. 23 He prematurely robbed me of my strength; He cut short my days. 24 I said: “O my God, Do not do away with me in the middle of my life, You whose years span all generations. 25 Long ago you laid the foundations of the earth, And the heavens are the work of your hands. 26 They will perish, but you will remain; Just like a garment they will all wear out. Just like clothing you will replace them, and they will pass away. 27 But you are the same, and your years will never end. 28 The children of your servants will dwell securely, And their offspring will be firmly established before you.”

Or “he grows weak.”

Or “Bend down and listen.”

Or possibly, “I am emaciated.”

Or “make a fool of me.”

Or “a lengthening shadow.”

Or “name.” Lit., “memorial.”

Lit., “be created.”

^ par. 19 (Ps. 102:0-28) A prayer of the oppressed one when he is in despair* and pours out his concern before Jehovah. 102 O Jehovah, hear my prayer; Let my cry for help reach you.  2 Do not hide your face from me in my time of distress. Incline your ear* to me; Do answer me quickly when I call.  3 For my days are vanishing like smoke, And my bones are charred like a fireplace.  4 My heart has been struck down like grass and has withered, For I forget to eat my food.  5 Because of my loud groaning, My bones cling to my flesh.  6 I resemble the pelican of the wilderness; I am like a little owl among the ruins.  7 I lie awake;* I am like a solitary bird on a roof.  8 All day long my enemies taunt me. Those who mock me* use my name as a curse.  9 For I eat ashes as my bread, And my drink is mingled with tears, 10 Because of your anger and your indignation, For you lifted me up only to cast me aside. 11 My days are like a fading shadow,* And I am withering like grass. 12 But you remain forever, O Jehovah, And your fame* will endure for all generations. 13 Surely you will rise up and show mercy on Zion, For it is time to show her your favor; The appointed time has come. 14 For your servants find pleasure in her stones And have affection even for her dust. 15 The nations will fear the name of Jehovah, And all the kings of the earth your glory. 16 For Jehovah will rebuild Zion; He will appear in his glory. 17 He will pay attention to the prayer of the destitute; He will not despise their prayer. 18 This is written for the future generation, So that a people yet to be brought forth* will praise Jah. 19 For he looks down from his holy height, From the heavens Jehovah views the earth, 20 To hear the sighing of the prisoner, To release those sentenced to death, 21 So that the name of Jehovah will be declared in Zion And his praise in Jerusalem, 22 When the peoples and kingdoms Gather together to serve Jehovah. 23 He prematurely robbed me of my strength; He cut short my days. 24 I said: “O my God, Do not do away with me in the middle of my life, You whose years span all generations. 25 Long ago you laid the foundations of the earth, And the heavens are the work of your hands. 26 They will perish, but you will remain; Just like a garment they will all wear out. Just like clothing you will replace them, and they will pass away. 27 But you are the same, and your years will never end. 28 The children of your servants will dwell securely, And their offspring will be firmly established before you.”

Or “he grows weak.”

Or “Bend down and listen.”

Or possibly, “I am emaciated.”

Or “make a fool of me.”

Or “a lengthening shadow.”

Or “name.” Lit., “memorial.”

Lit., “be created.”

^ par. 19 (Ps. 102:0-28) A prayer of the oppressed one when he is in despair* and pours out his concern before Jehovah. 102 O Jehovah, hear my prayer; Let my cry for help reach you.  2 Do not hide your face from me in my time of distress. Incline your ear* to me; Do answer me quickly when I call.  3 For my days are vanishing like smoke, And my bones are charred like a fireplace.  4 My heart has been struck down like grass and has withered, For I forget to eat my food.  5 Because of my loud groaning, My bones cling to my flesh.  6 I resemble the pelican of the wilderness; I am like a little owl among the ruins.  7 I lie awake;* I am like a solitary bird on a roof.  8 All day long my enemies taunt me. Those who mock me* use my name as a curse.  9 For I eat ashes as my bread, And my drink is mingled with tears, 10 Because of your anger and your indignation, For you lifted me up only to cast me aside. 11 My days are like a fading shadow,* And I am withering like grass. 12 But you remain forever, O Jehovah, And your fame* will endure for all generations. 13 Surely you will rise up and show mercy on Zion, For it is time to show her your favor; The appointed time has come. 14 For your servants find pleasure in her stones And have affection even for her dust. 15 The nations will fear the name of Jehovah, And all the kings of the earth your glory. 16 For Jehovah will rebuild Zion; He will appear in his glory. 17 He will pay attention to the prayer of the destitute; He will not despise their prayer. 18 This is written for the future generation, So that a people yet to be brought forth* will praise Jah. 19 For he looks down from his holy height, From the heavens Jehovah views the earth, 20 To hear the sighing of the prisoner, To release those sentenced to death, 21 So that the name of Jehovah will be declared in Zion And his praise in Jerusalem, 22 When the peoples and kingdoms Gather together to serve Jehovah. 23 He prematurely robbed me of my strength; He cut short my days. 24 I said: “O my God, Do not do away with me in the middle of my life, You whose years span all generations. 25 Long ago you laid the foundations of the earth, And the heavens are the work of your hands. 26 They will perish, but you will remain; Just like a garment they will all wear out. Just like clothing you will replace them, and they will pass away. 27 But you are the same, and your years will never end. 28 The children of your servants will dwell securely, And their offspring will be firmly established before you.”

Or “he grows weak.”

Or “Bend down and listen.”

Or possibly, “I am emaciated.”

Or “make a fool of me.”

Or “a lengthening shadow.”

Or “name.” Lit., “memorial.”

Lit., “be created.”

^ par. 19 (Ps. 102:3, 4) For my days are vanishing like smoke, And my bones are charred like a fireplace.  4 My heart has been struck down like grass and has withered, For I forget to eat my food.

^ par. 19 (Ps. 102:6) I resemble the pelican of the wilderness; I am like a little owl among the ruins.

^ par. 19 (Ps. 102:11) My days are like a fading shadow,* And I am withering like grass.

Or “a lengthening shadow.”

^ par. 19 (Ps. 102:10) Because of your anger and your indignation, For you lifted me up only to cast me aside.

^ par. 20 (Ps. 102:19-21) For he looks down from his holy height, From the heavens Jehovah views the earth, 20 To hear the sighing of the prisoner, To release those sentenced to death, 21 So that the name of Jehovah will be declared in Zion And his praise in Jerusalem,

^ par. 20 (Ps. 102:0-28) A prayer of the oppressed one when he is in despair* and pours out his concern before Jehovah. 102 O Jehovah, hear my prayer; Let my cry for help reach you.  2 Do not hide your face from me in my time of distress. Incline your ear* to me; Do answer me quickly when I call.  3 For my days are vanishing like smoke, And my bones are charred like a fireplace.  4 My heart has been struck down like grass and has withered, For I forget to eat my food.  5 Because of my loud groaning, My bones cling to my flesh.  6 I resemble the pelican of the wilderness; I am like a little owl among the ruins.  7 I lie awake;* I am like a solitary bird on a roof.  8 All day long my enemies taunt me. Those who mock me* use my name as a curse.  9 For I eat ashes as my bread, And my drink is mingled with tears, 10 Because of your anger and your indignation, For you lifted me up only to cast me aside. 11 My days are like a fading shadow,* And I am withering like grass. 12 But you remain forever, O Jehovah, And your fame* will endure for all generations. 13 Surely you will rise up and show mercy on Zion, For it is time to show her your favor; The appointed time has come. 14 For your servants find pleasure in her stones And have affection even for her dust. 15 The nations will fear the name of Jehovah, And all the kings of the earth your glory. 16 For Jehovah will rebuild Zion; He will appear in his glory. 17 He will pay attention to the prayer of the destitute; He will not despise their prayer. 18 This is written for the future generation, So that a people yet to be brought forth* will praise Jah. 19 For he looks down from his holy height, From the heavens Jehovah views the earth, 20 To hear the sighing of the prisoner, To release those sentenced to death, 21 So that the name of Jehovah will be declared in Zion And his praise in Jerusalem, 22 When the peoples and kingdoms Gather together to serve Jehovah. 23 He prematurely robbed me of my strength; He cut short my days. 24 I said: “O my God, Do not do away with me in the middle of my life, You whose years span all generations. 25 Long ago you laid the foundations of the earth, And the heavens are the work of your hands. 26 They will perish, but you will remain; Just like a garment they will all wear out. Just like clothing you will replace them, and they will pass away. 27 But you are the same, and your years will never end. 28 The children of your servants will dwell securely, And their offspring will be firmly established before you.”

Or “he grows weak.”

Or “Bend down and listen.”

Or possibly, “I am emaciated.”

Or “make a fool of me.”

Or “a lengthening shadow.”

Or “name.” Lit., “memorial.”

Lit., “be created.”

^ par. 20 (Ps. 102:7) I lie awake;* I am like a solitary bird on a roof.

Or possibly, “I am emaciated.”

^ par. 20 (Ps. 102:17) He will pay attention to the prayer of the destitute; He will not despise their prayer.

^ par. 21 (Ps. 102:0-28) A prayer of the oppressed one when he is in despair* and pours out his concern before Jehovah. 102 O Jehovah, hear my prayer; Let my cry for help reach you.  2 Do not hide your face from me in my time of distress. Incline your ear* to me; Do answer me quickly when I call.  3 For my days are vanishing like smoke, And my bones are charred like a fireplace.  4 My heart has been struck down like grass and has withered, For I forget to eat my food.  5 Because of my loud groaning, My bones cling to my flesh.  6 I resemble the pelican of the wilderness; I am like a little owl among the ruins.  7 I lie awake;* I am like a solitary bird on a roof.  8 All day long my enemies taunt me. Those who mock me* use my name as a curse.  9 For I eat ashes as my bread, And my drink is mingled with tears, 10 Because of your anger and your indignation, For you lifted me up only to cast me aside. 11 My days are like a fading shadow,* And I am withering like grass. 12 But you remain forever, O Jehovah, And your fame* will endure for all generations. 13 Surely you will rise up and show mercy on Zion, For it is time to show her your favor; The appointed time has come. 14 For your servants find pleasure in her stones And have affection even for her dust. 15 The nations will fear the name of Jehovah, And all the kings of the earth your glory. 16 For Jehovah will rebuild Zion; He will appear in his glory. 17 He will pay attention to the prayer of the destitute; He will not despise their prayer. 18 This is written for the future generation, So that a people yet to be brought forth* will praise Jah. 19 For he looks down from his holy height, From the heavens Jehovah views the earth, 20 To hear the sighing of the prisoner, To release those sentenced to death, 21 So that the name of Jehovah will be declared in Zion And his praise in Jerusalem, 22 When the peoples and kingdoms Gather together to serve Jehovah. 23 He prematurely robbed me of my strength; He cut short my days. 24 I said: “O my God, Do not do away with me in the middle of my life, You whose years span all generations. 25 Long ago you laid the foundations of the earth, And the heavens are the work of your hands. 26 They will perish, but you will remain; Just like a garment they will all wear out. Just like clothing you will replace them, and they will pass away. 27 But you are the same, and your years will never end. 28 The children of your servants will dwell securely, And their offspring will be firmly established before you.”

Or “he grows weak.”

Or “Bend down and listen.”

Or possibly, “I am emaciated.”

Or “make a fool of me.”

Or “a lengthening shadow.”

Or “name.” Lit., “memorial.”

Lit., “be created.”

^ par. 21 (Ps. 102:12) But you remain forever, O Jehovah, And your fame* will endure for all generations.

Or “name.” Lit., “memorial.”

^ par. 21 (Ps. 102:27) But you are the same, and your years will never end.

^ par. 21 (Ps. 102:20, 21) To hear the sighing of the prisoner, To release those sentenced to death, 21 So that the name of Jehovah will be declared in Zion And his praise in Jerusalem,

^ ***w15 4/15 p. 25 Always Trust in Jehovah!***

7. Why does Jehovah not always answer our prayers immediately?

7 Why does Jehovah not give us an immediate response to our every request? Recall that he likens our relationship with him to that of children with a father. ([Ps. 103:13]) A child cannot rightly expect a parent to grant every request or to do so right away. Some of a child’s requests may be mere passing whims. Others must wait till the time is right. Still others may not be in the child’s best interests or in the best interests of others involved. Furthermore, to concede immediately to a child’s every request would change the relationship to one of master and slave, the child being the master. Similarly, Jehovah may in our best interests allow time to pass before his response to our prayers becomes evident. That is his prerogative as our wise Creator, loving Master, and heavenly Father. Fulfilling all our requests right away would distort the proper relationship between us and him.—Compare Isaiah 29:16;[45:9].

^ par. 7 (Ps. 103:13) As a father shows mercy to his sons, Jehovah has shown mercy to those who fear him.

^ par. 7 (Isa. 29:16) How you twist things!* Should the potter be regarded the same as the clay? Should what is made say about its maker: “He did not make me”? And does what is formed say about its former: “He shows no understanding”?

Or “How perverse of you!”

^ par. 7 (Isa. 45:9) Woe to the one who contends* with his Maker,* For he is just an earthenware fragment Among the other earthenware fragments lying on the ground! Should the clay say to the Potter:* “What are you making?” Or should your work say: “He has no hands”?*

Or “argues.”

Or “with the One who formed him.”

Or “the One who formed it.”

Or possibly, “Or should the clay say: ‘Your work has no handles’?”

^ ***g16 pp. 10-11 How to Deal With Change***

HELP FOR THE FAMILY | YOUNG PEOPLE

How to Deal With Change

THE CHALLENGE

Your dad’s job requires that your family relocate.

Your best friend is moving far away.

Your older sibling is leaving home to get married.

How well would you adapt to such changes?

A tree that can bend with the wind is more likely to survive a storm. Like that tree, you can learn to “bend” with changes over which you have little or no control. Before discussing how you can do that, though, consider a few things you should know about change.

WHAT YOU SHOULD KNOW

Change is inevitable. The Bible states a fundamental truth about humans: “Unexpected events overtake them all.” (Ecclesiastes 9:11) Sooner or later, you will be confronted with the reality of those words. Of course, not all unexpected events are bad. And some changes that at first seem to be bad might turn out to be advantageous. Nevertheless, most people thrive on routine, while change—whether good or bad—rattles their comfort zone.

Change can be particularly stressful for adolescents. Why? “You’re already going through internal changes,” explains a young man named Alex.* “External changes just add to the stress.”

Here is another reason: When adults face a change, they can refer to their personal ‘book of experience’ to see how they dealt with similar situations in the past. But young people have less history on which to draw.

You can learn to adapt. Resilience is the ability to recover from misfortune or adjust to change. A resilient person can not only endure a new circumstance but also look at a seeming obstacle and see an opportunity in it. Resilient teens are less likely to turn to drugs or alcohol when they feel overwhelmed.

WHAT YOU CAN DO

Accept reality. No doubt you would like to have total control of your life, but that is simply not possible. Friends will move away or marry; siblings will grow up and leave home; circumstances may force your family to move, leaving behind friends and all that is familiar. It is better to accept reality than to let negative thoughts overwhelm you.—Bible principle: Ecclesiastes 7:10.

Look ahead. Focusing on the past is like driving on a highway with your eyes fixed on the rearview mirror. An occasional glance is beneficial, but you really need to concentrate on the road ahead. The same is true when you are confronted with change. Try to keep your eyes fixed on the future. (Proverbs 4:25) For example, what goal could you set for the next month, or six months?

Focus on the positive. “Resilience is about attitude,” says a young woman named Laura. “Find positive aspects of the circumstance you are in.” Can you list at least one advantage that your new circumstance offers?—Bible principle: Ecclesiastes 6:9.

A young woman named Victoria recalls that in her teen years, all her close friends moved away. “I felt so lonely, and I wished that everything could have stayed the way it was,” she says. “But looking back, that’s when I really started to grow. I came to realize that growth requires change. That’s also when I started seeing possibilities for new friendships that were all around me.”—Bible principle: Proverbs 27:10.

Focusing on the past is like driving on a highway with your eyes fixed on the rearview mirror

Do things for others. The Bible says: “Look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.” (Philippians 2:4) A good antidote to your own challenge is helping others with theirs. Anna, 17, says: “As I grew older, I came to realize that when I could help someone else who might be going through a similar situation—or a worse one—it was rewarding!”

^ par. 11 Some names in this article have been changed.

KEY SCRIPTURES

“Do not say, ‘Why were the former days better than these?’”—Ecclesiastes 7:10.

“Better to enjoy what the eyes see than to wander after one’s desires.”—Ecclesiastes 6:9.

“Better is a neighbor nearby than a brother far away.”—Proverbs 27:10.

JUAN

“Young people can develop resilience by analyzing the situation they are coping with and realizing that change is a part of life. The quicker a person accepts that reality, the easier it will be to move on with life. Things do get better.”

CARISSA

“Once a difficulty has passed, I try not to relive it over and over in my mind. I just move on to the next challenge in life. Part of being resilient, I believe, is looking ahead rather than looking behind.”

^ (Eccl. 9:11) I have seen something further under the sun, that the swift do not always win the race, nor do the mighty win the battle, nor do the wise always have the food, nor do the intelligent always have the riches, nor do those with knowledge always have success, because time and unexpected events* overtake them all.

Or “unforeseen occurrence.”

^ (Eccl. 7:10) Do not say, “Why were the former days better than these?” for it is not out of wisdom that you ask this.

^ (Prov. 4:25) Your eyes should look straight ahead, Yes, fix your gaze* straight ahead of you.

Or “beaming eyes.”

^ (Eccl. 6:9) Better to enjoy what the eyes see than to wander after one’s desires.* This too is futility, a chasing after the wind.

Or “than the walking about of the soul.”

^ (Prov. 27:10) Do not forsake your friend or your father’s friend, And do not enter your own brother’s house on the day of your disaster; Better is a neighbor nearby than a brother far away.

^ (Phil. 2:4) as you look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.

^ (Eccl. 7:10) Do not say, “Why were the former days better than these?” for it is not out of wisdom that you ask this.

^ (Eccl. 6:9) Better to enjoy what the eyes see than to wander after one’s desires.* This too is futility, a chasing after the wind.

Or “than the walking about of the soul.”

^ (Prov. 27:10) Do not forsake your friend or your father’s friend, And do not enter your own brother’s house on the day of your disaster; Better is a neighbor nearby than a brother far away.

^ ***g16 pp. 10-11 How to Deal With Change***

HELP FOR THE FAMILY | YOUNG PEOPLE

How to Deal With Change

THE CHALLENGE

Your dad’s job requires that your family relocate.

Your best friend is moving far away.

Your older sibling is leaving home to get married.

How well would you adapt to such changes?

A tree that can bend with the wind is more likely to survive a storm. Like that tree, you can learn to “bend” with changes over which you have little or no control. Before discussing how you can do that, though, consider a few things you should know about change.

WHAT YOU SHOULD KNOW

Change is inevitable. The Bible states a fundamental truth about humans: “Unexpected events overtake them all.” (Ecclesiastes 9:11) Sooner or later, you will be confronted with the reality of those words. Of course, not all unexpected events are bad. And some changes that at first seem to be bad might turn out to be advantageous. Nevertheless, most people thrive on routine, while change—whether good or bad—rattles their comfort zone.

Change can be particularly stressful for adolescents. Why? “You’re already going through internal changes,” explains a young man named Alex.* “External changes just add to the stress.”

Here is another reason: When adults face a change, they can refer to their personal ‘book of experience’ to see how they dealt with similar situations in the past. But young people have less history on which to draw.

You can learn to adapt. Resilience is the ability to recover from misfortune or adjust to change. A resilient person can not only endure a new circumstance but also look at a seeming obstacle and see an opportunity in it. Resilient teens are less likely to turn to drugs or alcohol when they feel overwhelmed.

WHAT YOU CAN DO

Accept reality. No doubt you would like to have total control of your life, but that is simply not possible. Friends will move away or marry; siblings will grow up and leave home; circumstances may force your family to move, leaving behind friends and all that is familiar. It is better to accept reality than to let negative thoughts overwhelm you.—Bible principle: Ecclesiastes 7:10.

Look ahead. Focusing on the past is like driving on a highway with your eyes fixed on the rearview mirror. An occasional glance is beneficial, but you really need to concentrate on the road ahead. The same is true when you are confronted with change. Try to keep your eyes fixed on the future. (Proverbs 4:25) For example, what goal could you set for the next month, or six months?

Focus on the positive. “Resilience is about attitude,” says a young woman named Laura. “Find positive aspects of the circumstance you are in.” Can you list at least one advantage that your new circumstance offers?—Bible principle: Ecclesiastes 6:9.

A young woman named Victoria recalls that in her teen years, all her close friends moved away. “I felt so lonely, and I wished that everything could have stayed the way it was,” she says. “But looking back, that’s when I really started to grow. I came to realize that growth requires change. That’s also when I started seeing possibilities for new friendships that were all around me.”—Bible principle: Proverbs 27:10.

Focusing on the past is like driving on a highway with your eyes fixed on the rearview mirror

Do things for others. The Bible says: “Look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.” (Philippians 2:4) A good antidote to your own challenge is helping others with theirs. Anna, 17, says: “As I grew older, I came to realize that when I could help someone else who might be going through a similar situation—or a worse one—it was rewarding!”

^ par. 11 Some names in this article have been changed.

KEY SCRIPTURES

“Do not say, ‘Why were the former days better than these?’”—Ecclesiastes 7:10.

“Better to enjoy what the eyes see than to wander after one’s desires.”—Ecclesiastes 6:9.

“Better is a neighbor nearby than a brother far away.”—Proverbs 27:10.

JUAN

“Young people can develop resilience by analyzing the situation they are coping with and realizing that change is a part of life. The quicker a person accepts that reality, the easier it will be to move on with life. Things do get better.”

CARISSA

“Once a difficulty has passed, I try not to relive it over and over in my mind. I just move on to the next challenge in life. Part of being resilient, I believe, is looking ahead rather than looking behind.”

^ (Eccl. 9:11) I have seen something further under the sun, that the swift do not always win the race, nor do the mighty win the battle, nor do the wise always have the food, nor do the intelligent always have the riches, nor do those with knowledge always have success, because time and unexpected events* overtake them all.

Or “unforeseen occurrence.”

^ (Eccl. 7:10) Do not say, “Why were the former days better than these?” for it is not out of wisdom that you ask this.

^ (Prov. 4:25) Your eyes should look straight ahead, Yes, fix your gaze* straight ahead of you.

Or “beaming eyes.”

^ (Eccl. 6:9) Better to enjoy what the eyes see than to wander after one’s desires.* This too is futility, a chasing after the wind.

Or “than the walking about of the soul.”

^ (Prov. 27:10) Do not forsake your friend or your father’s friend, And do not enter your own brother’s house on the day of your disaster; Better is a neighbor nearby than a brother far away.

^ (Phil. 2:4) as you look out not only for your own interests, but also for the interests of others.

^ (Eccl. 7:10) Do not say, “Why were the former days better than these?” for it is not out of wisdom that you ask this.

^ (Eccl. 6:9) Better to enjoy what the eyes see than to wander after one’s desires.* This too is futility, a chasing after the wind.

Or “than the walking about of the soul.”

^ (Prov. 27:10) Do not forsake your friend or your father’s friend, And do not enter your own brother’s house on the day of your disaster; Better is a neighbor nearby than a brother far away.

^ ***bh pp. 164-166 Draw Close to God in Prayer***

3. What is one important reason why we should pray to Jehovah?

3 One important reason why we should pray to Jehovah is that he invites us to do so. His Word encourages us: “Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers by means of Christ Jesus.” (Philippians 4:6, 7) Surely we would not want to ignore such a kind provision made for us by the Supreme Ruler of the universe!

4. How does regular prayer to Jehovah strengthen our relationship with him?

4 Another reason to pray is that regularly praying to Jehovah is a way to strengthen our relationship with him. True friends do not communicate only when they need something. Rather, good friends are interested in each other, and their friendship becomes stronger as they freely express their thoughts, concerns, and feelings. In some respects, the situation is similar when it comes to our relationship with Jehovah God. With the help of this book, you have learned much about what the Bible teaches regarding Jehovah, his personality, and his purposes. You have come to know him as a real Person. Prayer gives you the opportunity to express your thoughts and innermost feelings to your heavenly Father. As you do, you draw closer to Jehovah.—[James 4:8].

^ par. 3 (Phil. 4:6, 7) Do not be anxious over anything, but in everything by prayer and supplication along with thanksgiving, let your petitions be made known to God; 7 and the peace of God that surpasses all understanding will guard your hearts and your mental powers* by means of Christ Jesus.

Or “your minds; your thoughts.”

^ par. 4 (Jas. 4:8) Draw close to God, and he will draw close to you. Cleanse your hands, you sinners, and purify your hearts, you indecisive ones.

^ ***sn song 91 My Father, My God and Friend***

Song 91

My Father, My God and Friend

([Hebrews 6:10])

1. Life in this world can be hard.

Life in this world can bring tears and pain.

Still ev’ry day I will say,

“My life is not in vain.”

(CHORUS)

For God is not unrighteous,

And he remembers the love I’ve shown.

So he is ever near me;

With Jehovah, I’m not alone.

Yes, God is my provider

and my protector down to the end.

Yes, Jehovah is my Father,

My God and Friend.

2. Gone are the days of my youth;

Days of calamity now are here.

Still through the eyes of my faith,

My hope is bright and clear.

(CHORUS)

For God is not unrighteous,

And he remembers the love I’ve shown.

So he is ever near me;

With Jehovah, I’m not alone.

Yes, God is my provider

and my protector down to the end.

Yes, Jehovah is my Father,

My God and Friend.

(See also Ps. 71:17, 18.)

^ (Heb. 6:10) For God is not unrighteous so as to forget your work and the love you showed for his name by ministering and continuing to minister to the holy ones.

^ (Ps. 71:17, 18) O God, you have taught me from my youth, And until now I keep declaring your wonderful works. 18 Even when I am old and gray, O God, do not abandon me. Let me tell the next generation about your power* And about your mightiness to all those who are to come.

Lit., “arm.”

^ ***ia pp. 188-191 He Was Loyal in the Face of Tests***

1, 2. What was Peter likely hoping for as Jesus spoke in Capernaum, yet what happened instead?

PETER gazed anxiously around at the faces of Jesus’ audience. The setting was the synagogue in Capernaum. Peter’s home was in this town; his fishing business was here, on the northern shore of the Sea of Galilee; many of his friends, relatives, and business acquaintances lived here. No doubt Peter was hoping that his townsmen would see Jesus as he did and that they would share the thrill of learning about God’s Kingdom from the greatest of all teachers. No such outcome seemed likely that day.

2 Many had stopped listening. Some were murmuring audibly, objecting to the thrust of Jesus’ message. Most troubling to Peter, though, was the reaction of some of Jesus’ own disciples. Their faces no longer bore that happy expression of enlightenment, the thrill of discovery, the joy of learning the truth. Now, they looked upset, even bitter. Some spoke up, calling Jesus’ speech shocking. Refusing to listen anymore, they left the synagogue—and quit following Jesus as well.—Read John 6:60, 66.

3. What did Peter’s faith help him to do a number of times?

3 It was a difficult time for Peter and for his fellow apostles. Peter did not fully grasp what Jesus said that day. No doubt he could see why Jesus’ words might seem offensive if taken at face value. What would Peter do? It was not the first time that his loyalty to his Master was tested; nor would it be the last. Let us see how Peter’s faith helped him to rise to such challenges and remain loyal.

Loyal When Others Turned Disloyal

4, 5. How had Jesus acted in ways that were contrary to what people expected of him?

4 Peter often found himself surprised by Jesus. Again and again, his Master acted and spoke in a way that was contrary to what people expected of Him. Just a day earlier, Jesus had miraculously fed a crowd of thousands. In response, they had attempted to make him king. Yet, he surprised many by withdrawing from them, directing his disciples to board a boat and sail toward Capernaum. As the disciples made their way over water during the night, Jesus surprised them again by walking across the stormy Sea of Galilee, giving Peter an important lesson in faith.

5 In the morning, they soon found that those crowds had followed them around the lake. Evidently, though, the people were driven by a desire to see Jesus produce more food miraculously, not by any hunger for spiritual truths. Jesus rebuked them for their materialistic spirit. ([John 6:25-27]) That discussion continued at the synagogue in Capernaum, where Jesus again went against expectations in an effort to teach a vital but difficult truth.

6. What illustration did Jesus give, and how did his listeners react?

6 Jesus wanted those people to see him, not as a source of mere physical food, but as a spiritual provision from God, as the one whose life and death as a man would make eternal life possible for others. So he gave an illustration comparing himself to manna, the bread that came down from heaven in Moses’ day. When some objected, he used a vivid illustration, explaining that it was necessary to partake of his flesh and his blood in order to attain life. It was at this point that the objections became insistent. Some said: “This speech is shocking; who can listen to it?” Many of Jesus’ own disciples decided to quit following him.*—John 6:48-60,[66].

7, 8. (a) What did Peter not yet grasp about Jesus’ role? (b) How did Peter answer Jesus’ question to the apostles?

7 What would Peter do? He too must have been baffled by Jesus’ speech. He did not yet grasp that Jesus must die in order to carry out God’s will. Was Peter tempted to slink off like those fickle disciples who left Jesus that day? No; something important set Peter apart from those men. What was it?

8 Jesus turned to his apostles and said: “You do not want to go also, do you?” ([John 6:67]) He addressed the 12, but it was Peter who spoke up. It was often so. Peter may have been the oldest of them. In any case, he was certainly the most outspoken of the group; rarely, it seems, did Peter hesitate to say what was on his mind. In this case, what was on his mind was this beautiful and memorable statement: “Lord, whom shall we go away to? You have sayings of everlasting life.”—[John 6:68].

9. How did Peter show loyalty to Jesus?

9 Do not those words touch your heart? Peter’s faith in Jesus had helped him to build a priceless quality—loyalty. Peter saw clearly that Jesus was the only Savior Jehovah had provided and that Jesus saved by means of his sayings—his teachings about the Kingdom of God. Peter knew that even if there were some things that puzzled him, there was nowhere else to go if he wanted God’s favor and the blessing of everlasting life.

We need to be loyal to Jesus’ teachings, even when they run contrary to our expectations or personal preference

10. How can we today imitate Peter’s loyalty?

10 Is that how you feel? Sadly, many in today’s world claim to love Jesus but fail the test of loyalty. Genuine loyalty to Christ requires that we share Peter’s view of Jesus’ teachings. We need to learn them, to grasp their meaning, and to live by them—even when they surprise us by running contrary to our expectations or personal preferences. Only by proving loyal can we hope to attain to the everlasting life that Jesus wants for us.—Read Psalm 97:10.

Loyal When Corrected

11. Jesus led his followers on what trek? (See also footnote.)

11 Not long after that busy time, Jesus led his apostles and some disciples on a long trek northward. The snowcapped peak of Mount Hermon, at the northernmost limit of the Promised Land, was at times visible even from the blue waters of the Sea of Galilee. Gradually, that mountain loomed higher as the group approached, following the rising terrain up to the villages near Caesarea Philippi.* In this lovely setting, with a perspective over much of the Promised Land to the south, Jesus asked his followers an important question.

12, 13. (a) Why did Jesus ask about the crowds and their view of him? (b) In his words to Jesus, how did Peter show genuine faith?

12 “Who are the crowds saying that I am?” he wanted to know. We can just imagine Peter looking into Jesus’ keen eyes, sensing again his Master’s kindness and his powerful, clear intelligence. Jesus was interested in the conclusions his audiences were drawing from what they saw and heard. Jesus’ disciples answered the question, repeating some of the popular misconceptions surrounding Jesus’ identity. But Jesus wanted to know more. Were his closest followers making the same mistakes? “You, though, who do you say I am?” he asked.—[Luke 9:18-20].

13 Again, Peter was quick to respond. He put into clear, bold words the conclusion that had formed in the hearts of many there. “You are the Christ, the Son of the living God,” he said. We can imagine Jesus giving Peter a smile of approval as He commended him warmly. Jesus reminded Peter that it was Jehovah God—not any man—who had made this vital truth so plain to those with genuine faith. Peter had been enabled to discern one of the greatest truths Jehovah had yet revealed—the identity of the long-promised Messiah, or Christ!—Read Matthew 16:16, 17.

^ par. 2 (John 6:60) When they heard this, many of his disciples said: “This speech is shocking; who can listen to it?”

^ par. 2 (John 6:66) Because of this, many of his disciples went off to the things behind and would no longer walk with him.

^ par. 5 (John 6:25-27) When they found him across the sea, they said to him: “Rabbi, when did you get here?” 26 Jesus answered them: “Most truly I say to you, you are looking for me, not because you saw signs, but because you ate from the loaves and were satisfied. 27 Work, not for the food that perishes, but for the food that remains for everlasting life, which the Son of man will give you; for on this one the Father, God himself, has put his seal of approval.”

^ par. 6 (John 6:48-60) “I am the bread of life. 49 Your forefathers ate the manna in the wilderness and yet they died. 50 This is the bread that comes down from heaven, so that anyone may eat of it and not die. 51 I am the living bread that came down from heaven. If anyone eats of this bread he will live forever; and for a fact, the bread that I will give is my flesh in behalf of the life of the world.” 52 Then the Jews began to argue with one another, saying: “How can this man give us his flesh to eat?” 53 So Jesus said to them: “Most truly I say to you, unless you eat the flesh of the Son of man and drink his blood, you have no life in yourselves. 54 Whoever feeds on my flesh and drinks my blood has everlasting life, and I will resurrect him on the last day; 55 for my flesh is true food and my blood is true drink. 56 Whoever feeds on my flesh and drinks my blood remains in union with me, and I in union with him. 57 Just as the living Father sent me and I live because of the Father, so also the one who feeds on me will live because of me. 58 This is the bread that came down from heaven. It is not as when your forefathers ate and yet died. Whoever feeds on this bread will live forever.” 59 He said these things as he was teaching in a synagogue* in Ca·perʹna·um. 60 When they heard this, many of his disciples said: “This speech is shocking; who can listen to it?”

Or “public assembly.”

^ par. 6 (John 6:66) Because of this, many of his disciples went off to the things behind and would no longer walk with him.

^ par. 8 (John 6:67) So Jesus said to the Twelve: “You do not want to go also, do you?”

^ par. 8 (John 6:68) Simon Peter answered him: “Lord, whom shall we go away to? You have sayings of everlasting life.

^ par. 10 (Ps. 97:10) O you who love Jehovah, hate what is bad. He is guarding the lives* of his loyal ones; He rescues them from the hand* of the wicked.

Or “souls.”

Or “power.”

^ par. 12 (Luke 9:18-20) Later, while he was praying alone, the disciples came to him, and he questioned them, saying: “Who are the crowds saying that I am?” 19 In reply they said: “John the Baptist, but others say E·liʹjah, and still others say that one of the ancient prophets has risen.” 20 Then he said to them: “You, though, who do you say I am?” Peter answered: “The Christ of God.”

^ par. 13 (Matt. 16:16, 17) Simon Peter answered: “You are the Christ, the Son of the living God.” 17 In response Jesus said to him: “Happy you are, Simon son of Joʹnah, because flesh and blood* did not reveal it to you, but my Father in the heavens did.

Or “because a human.”

^ par. 6 We can see the inconstancy of the crowd at the synagogue if we compare their reactions to Jesus’ speech here with their expressions just the day before when they enthusiastically proclaimed him a prophet of God.—[John 6:14].

^ par. 11 From the shores of the Sea of Galilee, that 30-mile (50 km) journey took the group from about 700 feet (210 m) below sea level to 1,150 feet (350 m) above, through regions of great natural beauty.

^ (John 6:14) When the people saw the sign he performed, they began to say: “This really is the Prophet who was to come into the world.”

^ ***sn song 131 Jehovah Provides Escape***

Song 131

Jehovah Provides Escape

(2 Samuel 22:1-8)

1. The living God, Jehovah, you have proved to be;

Your mighty works abound in earth and sky and sea.

No rival god can equal what you have done—there is none.

Our foes will be consumed.

(CHORUS)

Jehovah provides escape for the loyal.

His servants will see what a mighty Crag is he.

So with courage and faith in our God, we spread the fame

Of Jehovah, our Source of escape, and praise his name.

2. Though ropes of death encircle me, I call to you,

“Jehovah, give me strength, and give me courage too.”

From your own temple dwelling, you hear my plea, “Shelter me;

Rescue me, O my God.”

(CHORUS)

Jehovah provides escape for the loyal.

His servants will see what a mighty Crag is he.

So with courage and faith in our God, we spread the fame

Of Jehovah, our Source of escape, and praise his name.

3. From heaven you will thunder and give forth your voice.

Your enemies will quake; your servants will rejoice.

You prove to be whatever you need to be; all will see

How you provide escape.

(CHORUS)

Jehovah provides escape for the loyal.

His servants will see what a mighty Crag is he.

So with courage and faith in our God, we spread the fame

Of Jehovah, our Source of escape, and praise his name.

(See also [Ps. 18:1, 2;][144:1, 2].)

^ (2 Sam. 22:1-8) And David spoke to Jehovah the words of this song in the day that Jehovah rescued him out of the hand of all his enemies and out of Saul’s hand. 2 He said: “Jehovah is my crag and my stronghold and the One who rescues me.  3 My God is my rock, in whom I take refuge, My shield and my horn* of salvation,* my secure refuge* And my place to flee, my savior; you who save me from violence.  4 I call on Jehovah, who is worthy of praise, And I will be saved from my enemies.  5 The waves of death broke all around me; Flash floods of worthless men terrified me.  6 The ropes of the Grave* surrounded me; The snares of death confronted me.  7 In my distress I called on Jehovah, To my God I kept calling. Then from his temple he heard my voice, And my cry for help reached his ears.  8 Back and forth the earth began to shake and rock; The foundations of the heavens trembled And shook back and forth because he had been angered.

See Glossary.

Or “my powerful savior.”

Or “secure height.”

Or “Sheol,” that is, the common grave of mankind. See Glossary.

^ (Ps. 18:1, 2) I have affection for you, O Jehovah, my strength.  2 Jehovah is my crag and my stronghold and the One who rescues me. My God is my rock, in whom I take refuge, My shield and my horn* of salvation,* my secure refuge.*

See Glossary.

Or “my powerful savior.”

Or “secure height.”

^ (Ps. 144:1, 2) May Jehovah, my Rock, be praised, Who trains my hands for battle, My fingers for warfare.  2 He is my loyal love and my stronghold, My secure refuge* and my rescuer, My shield and the One in whom I have taken shelter, The One subduing peoples under me.

Or “secure height.”

^ (Pss. 102:0-105:45) A prayer of the oppressed one when he is in despair* and pours out his concern before Jehovah. 102 O Jehovah, hear my prayer; Let my cry for help reach you.  2 Do not hide your face from me in my time of distress. Incline your ear* to me; Do answer me quickly when I call.  3 For my days are vanishing like smoke, And my bones are charred like a fireplace.  4 My heart has been struck down like grass and has withered, For I forget to eat my food.  5 Because of my loud groaning, My bones cling to my flesh.  6 I resemble the pelican of the wilderness; I am like a little owl among the ruins.  7 I lie awake;* I am like a solitary bird on a roof.  8 All day long my enemies taunt me. Those who mock me* use my name as a curse.  9 For I eat ashes as my bread, And my drink is mingled with tears, 10 Because of your anger and your indignation, For you lifted me up only to cast me aside. 11 My days are like a fading shadow,* And I am withering like grass. 12 But you remain forever, O Jehovah, And your fame* will endure for all generations. 13 Surely you will rise up and show mercy on Zion, For it is time to show her your favor; The appointed time has come. 14 For your servants find pleasure in her stones And have affection even for her dust. 15 The nations will fear the name of Jehovah, And all the kings of the earth your glory. 16 For Jehovah will rebuild Zion; He will appear in his glory. 17 He will pay attention to the prayer of the destitute; He will not despise their prayer. 18 This is written for the future generation, So that a people yet to be brought forth* will praise Jah. 19 For he looks down from his holy height, From the heavens Jehovah views the earth, 20 To hear the sighing of the prisoner, To release those sentenced to death, 21 So that the name of Jehovah will be declared in Zion And his praise in Jerusalem, 22 When the peoples and kingdoms Gather together to serve Jehovah. 23 He prematurely robbed me of my strength; He cut short my days. 24 I said: “O my God, Do not do away with me in the middle of my life, You whose years span all generations. 25 Long ago you laid the foundations of the earth, And the heavens are the work of your hands. 26 They will perish, but you will remain; Just like a garment they will all wear out. Just like clothing you will replace them, and they will pass away. 27 But you are the same, and your years will never end. 28 The children of your servants will dwell securely, And their offspring will be firmly established before you.”

Of David. 103 Let me* praise Jehovah; Let everything within me praise his holy name.  2 Let me* praise Jehovah; May I never forget all that he has done.  3 He forgives all your errors And heals all your ailments;  4 He reclaims your life from the pit* And crowns you with his loyal love and mercy.  5 He satisfies you with good things all your life, So that your youth is renewed like that of an eagle.  6 Jehovah acts with righteousness and justice For all who are oppressed.  7 He made known his ways to Moses, His deeds to the sons of Israel.  8 Jehovah is merciful and compassionate,* Slow to anger and abundant in loyal love.*  9 He will not always find fault, Nor will he stay resentful forever. 10 He has not dealt with us according to our sins, Nor has he repaid us what our errors deserve. 11 For as the heavens are higher than the earth, So great is his loyal love toward those who fear him. 12 As far off as the sunrise is from the sunset, So far off from us he has put our transgressions. 13 As a father shows mercy to his sons, Jehovah has shown mercy to those who fear him. 14 For he well knows how we are formed, Remembering that we are dust. 15 As for mortal man, his days are like those of grass; He blooms like a blossom of the field. 16 But when a wind blows, it is no more, As though it was never there.* 17 But the loyal love of Jehovah is for all eternity* Toward those who fear him, And his righteousness toward their children’s children, 18 Toward those who keep his covenant And those who are careful to observe his orders. 19 Jehovah has firmly established his throne in the heavens; And his kingship rules over everything. 20 Praise Jehovah, all you his angels, mighty in power, Who carry out his word, obeying his voice.* 21 Praise Jehovah, all his armies, His ministers who do his will. 22 Praise Jehovah, all his works, In all the places where he rules.* Let my whole being* praise Jehovah.

104 Let me* praise Jehovah. O Jehovah my God, you are very great. With majesty* and splendor you are clothed.  2 You are wrapped in light as with a garment; You stretch out the heavens like a tent cloth.  3 He lays beams of his upper rooms in the waters above,* Making the clouds his chariot, Moving on the wings of the wind.  4 He makes his angels spirits, His ministers a consuming fire.  5 He has established the earth on its foundations; It will not be moved from its place* forever and ever.  6 You covered it with deep waters as with a garment. The waters stood above the mountains.  7 At your rebuke they fled; At the sound of your thunder they ran away in panic  8 —Mountains ascended and valleys descended— To the place you established for them.  9 You set a boundary that they should not pass, That they should never again cover the earth. 10 He sends springs into the valleys;* Between the mountains they flow. 11 They provide water for all the wild beasts of the field; The wild donkeys quench their thirst. 12 Above them roost the birds of the sky; They sing among the thick foliage. 13 He is watering the mountains from his upper rooms. With the fruitage of your works the earth is satisfied. 14 He is making grass grow for the cattle And vegetation for mankind’s use, To grow food from the land 15 And wine that makes man’s heart rejoice, Oil that makes the face shine, And bread that sustains the heart of mortal man. 16 The trees of Jehovah are satisfied, The cedars of Lebʹa·non that he planted, 17 Where the birds make nests. The home of the stork is in the juniper trees. 18 The high mountains are for the mountain goats; The crags are a refuge for the rock badgers. 19 He has made the moon to mark the appointed times; The sun well knows when to set. 20 You bring darkness, and night falls, When all the wild animals of the forest roam about. 21 The young lions* roar for their prey And seek their food from God. 22 When the sun rises, They withdraw and lie down in their dens. 23 Man goes to his work, And he labors until evening. 24 How many your works are, O Jehovah! You have made all of them in wisdom. The earth is full of what you have made. 25 There is the sea, so great and wide, Teeming with countless living things, both small and great. 26 There the ships travel, And Le·viʹa·than,* which you formed to play in it. 27 All of them wait for you To give them their food in its season. 28 What you give them, they gather. When you open your hand, they are satisfied with good things. 29 When you hide your face, they are disturbed. If you take away their spirit, they die and return to the dust. 30 If you send out your spirit, they are created, And you renew the surface of the ground. 31 The glory of Jehovah will last forever. Jehovah will rejoice in his works. 32 He looks at the earth, and it trembles; He touches the mountains, and they smoke. 33 I will sing to Jehovah throughout my life; I will sing praises* to my God as long as I live. 34 Let my thoughts be pleasing to him.* I will rejoice in Jehovah. 35 The sinners will vanish from the earth, And the wicked will no longer exist. Let me* praise Jehovah. Praise Jah!*

105 Give thanks to Jehovah, call on his name, Make his deeds known among the peoples!  2 Sing to him, sing praises* to him, Ponder over* all his wonderful works.  3 Boast about his holy name. Let the hearts of those seeking Jehovah rejoice.  4 Search for Jehovah and his strength. Seek his face* constantly.  5 Remember the wonderful works he has performed, His miracles and the judgments he has pronounced,  6 You offspring* of Abraham his servant, You sons of Jacob, his chosen ones.  7 He is Jehovah our God. His judgments are throughout the earth.  8 He remembers his covenant forever, The promise he made,* to a thousand generations,  9 The covenant he made with Abraham, And the oath he swore to Isaac, 10 Which he established as a decree to Jacob And as a lasting covenant to Israel, 11 Saying, “I will give you the land of Caʹnaan As your allotted inheritance.” 12 This was when they were few in number, Yes, very few, and they were foreigners in the land. 13 They walked about from nation to nation, From one kingdom to another people. 14 He did not allow any man to oppress them, But on their account he reproved kings, 15 Saying, “Do not touch my anointed ones, And to my prophets do nothing bad.” 16 He called down a famine on the land; He cut off their supply of bread.* 17 He sent ahead of them a man Who was sold to be a slave, Joseph. 18 With fetters they bound* his feet, His neck was put in irons;* 19 Until the time that his word proved true, The saying of Jehovah is what refined him. 20 The king sent to release him, The ruler of the peoples set him free. 21 He made him master of his household, Ruler over all his property, 22 To have authority over* his princes as he pleased* And to teach his elders wisdom. 23 Then Israel came into Egypt, And Jacob lived as a foreigner in the land of Ham. 24 God made his people very fruitful; He made them mightier than their adversaries, 25 Whose hearts he let change to hate his people, To plot against his servants. 26 He sent his servant Moses, And Aaron, whom he had chosen. 27 They performed his signs among them, His miracles in the land of Ham. 28 He sent darkness and the land became dark; They did not rebel against his words. 29 He changed their waters into blood And killed their fish. 30 Their land swarmed with frogs, Even in the royal chambers. 31 He ordered the gadflies to invade And gnats in all their territories. 32 He turned their rain to hail And sent lightning* on their land. 33 He struck their vines and their fig trees And shattered the trees of their territory. 34 He said that the locusts should invade, Young locusts without number. 35 They devoured all the vegetation in the land, And they devoured the produce of the ground. 36 Then he struck down every firstborn in their land, The beginning of their procreative power. 37 He brought his people out with silver and gold; And no one among his tribes stumbled. 38 Egypt rejoiced when they left, For the dread of Israel* had fallen on them. 39 He spread a cloud to screen them off And fire to give light by night. 40 They asked, and he brought quail; He kept satisfying them with bread from heaven. 41 He opened a rock, and waters flowed out; These flowed through the desert like a river. 42 For he remembered the holy promise he had made to Abraham his servant. 43 So he brought out his people with exultation, His chosen ones with a joyful cry. 44 He gave them the lands of nations; They inherited what other peoples had worked hard to produce, 45 So that they would keep his decrees And observe his laws. Praise Jah!*

Or “he grows weak.”

Or “Bend down and listen.”

Or possibly, “I am emaciated.”

Or “make a fool of me.”

Or “a lengthening shadow.”

Or “name.” Lit., “memorial.”

Lit., “be created.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “grave.”

Or “gracious.”

Or “loving-kindness.”

Lit., “And its place no longer knows it.”

Or “from eternity to eternity.”

Lit., “hearing the voice (sound) of his word.”

Or “the places of his sovereignty.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “dignity.”

Lit., “in the waters.”

Or “will not totter.”

Or “wadis.”

Or “maned young lions.”

See Glossary.

Or “make music.”

Or possibly, “Let my meditation about him be pleasurable.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “make music.”

Or possibly, “Speak about.”

Or “presence.”

Or “descendants.” Lit., “seed.”

Lit., “The word he commanded.”

Lit., “broke every bread rod.” Possibly referring to rods used for storing bread.

Lit., “afflicted.”

Or “His soul came into iron.”

Lit., “To bind.”

Or “agreeably to his soul.”

Or “flames of fire.”

Lit., “them.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

^ (Pss. 106:1-109:31) Praise Jah!* Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; His loyal love endures forever.  2 Who can fully declare Jehovah’s mighty acts Or proclaim all his praiseworthy deeds?  3 Happy are those who act with justice, Who always do what is right.  4 Remember me, O Jehovah, when you show favor* toward your people. Take care of me with your acts of salvation,  5 So that I may enjoy the goodness you show your chosen ones, That I may rejoice along with your nation, That I may proudly praise* you along with your inheritance.  6 We have sinned just as our forefathers did; We have done wrong; we have acted wickedly.  7 Our forefathers in Egypt did not appreciate* your wonderful works. They did not remember your abundant loyal love, But they rebelled at the sea, by the Red Sea.  8 But he saved them for the sake of his name, To make his mightiness known.  9 He rebuked the Red Sea, and it dried up; He led them through its depths as through a desert;* 10 He saved them from the hand of their foe And reclaimed them from the hand of the enemy. 11 The waters covered their adversaries; Not one of them survived.* 12 Then they had faith in his promise; They began to sing his praise. 13 But they quickly forgot what he did; They did not wait for his counsel. 14 They gave way to their selfish desires in the wilderness; They tested God in the desert. 15 He gave them what they requested, But then struck them with disease that made them* waste away. 16 In the camp they grew jealous of Moses And of Aaron, the holy one of Jehovah. 17 The earth then opened up and swallowed Daʹthan And covered those assembled with A·biʹram. 18 A fire blazed among their group; A flame consumed the wicked. 19 They made a calf in Hoʹreb And bowed down to a statue of metal;* 20 They exchanged my glory For the representation of a grass-eating bull. 21 They forgot God their Savior, Who did great things in Egypt, 22 Wonderful works in the land of Ham, Awe-inspiring deeds at the Red Sea. 23 He was about to order their annihilation, But Moses his chosen one interceded with him* To avert his destructive anger. 24 Then they despised the desirable land; They had no faith in his promise. 25 They kept grumbling in their tents; They did not listen to the voice of Jehovah. 26 So he raised his hand in an oath concerning them That he would make them fall in the wilderness; 27 He would make their descendants fall among the nations, And he would scatter them throughout the lands. 28 Then they joined in worship of* Baʹal of Peʹor, And they ate sacrifices offered to the dead.* 29 They provoked Him by their actions, And a scourge broke out among them. 30 But when Phinʹe·has stood up and intervened, The scourge was halted. 31 And it was counted to him as righteousness Through all generations forever. 32 They provoked Him at the waters of Merʹi·bah,* And it went badly for Moses because of them. 33 They embittered his spirit, And he spoke rashly with his lips. 34 They did not annihilate the peoples, As Jehovah had commanded them. 35 But they mingled with the nations And adopted* their ways. 36 They kept serving their idols, And these became a snare to them. 37 They would sacrifice their sons And their daughters to demons. 38 They kept spilling innocent blood, The blood of their own sons and daughters Whom they sacrificed to the idols of Caʹnaan; And the land was polluted with bloodshed. 39 They became unclean by their works; They committed spiritual prostitution by their deeds. 40 So the anger of Jehovah blazed against his people, And he grew to detest his inheritance. 41 He repeatedly handed them over to the nations, So that those who hated them might rule over them. 42 Their enemies oppressed them, And they were subject to their power.* 43 Many times he rescued them, But they would rebel and disobey, And they would be brought low for their error. 44 But he would see their distress And hear their cry for help. 45 For their sake he would remember his covenant, And he would feel pity,* moved by his great* loyal love. 46 He would cause them to be pitied By all who held them captive. 47 Save us, O Jehovah our God, And gather us from the nations So that we may give thanks to your holy name And exult in praising you.* 48 May Jehovah, the God of Israel, be praised Throughout all eternity.* And let all the people say, “Amen!”* Praise Jah!*

107 Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; His loyal love endures forever.  2 Let those reclaimed* by Jehovah say this, Those whom he reclaimed from the hand* of the adversary,  3 Whom he gathered together from the lands, From the east and from the west,* From the north and from the south.  4 They wandered about in the wilderness, in the desert; They did not find a way to a city where they could live.  5 They were hungry and thirsty; They were* faint from exhaustion.  6 They kept crying out to Jehovah in their distress; He rescued them from their plight.  7 He had them walk in the right way To come to a city where they could live.  8 Let people give thanks to Jehovah for his loyal love And for his wonderful works in behalf of the sons of men.  9 For he has satisfied the thirsty* And filled the hungry* with good things. 10 Some were living in deepest darkness, Prisoners in affliction and in irons. 11 For they had rebelled against the word of God; They disrespected the counsel of the Most High. 12 So he humbled their hearts through hardship; They stumbled, and there was no one to help them. 13 They called to Jehovah for help in their distress; He saved them from their plight. 14 He brought them out of deepest darkness, And he tore off their shackles. 15 Let people give thanks to Jehovah for his loyal love And for his wonderful works in behalf of the sons of men. 16 For he has broken down the doors of copper And cut through the bars of iron. 17 They were foolish and suffered affliction On account of their transgressions and their errors. 18 They lost their appetite for* all food; They drew near the gates of death. 19 They would call to Jehovah for help in their distress; He would save them from their plight. 20 He would send his word and heal them And rescue them from the pits they were trapped in. 21 Let people give thanks to Jehovah for his loyal love And for his wonderful works in behalf of the sons of men. 22 Let them offer the sacrifices of thanksgiving And declare his works with a joyful cry. 23 Those who travel on the sea in ships, Who ply their trade over the vast waters, 24 They have seen the works of Jehovah And his wonderful works in the deep; 25 How by his word a windstorm arises, Lifting up the waves of the sea. 26 They rise up to the sky; They plunge down to the depths. Their courage* melts away because of the impending calamity. 27 They reel and stagger like a drunken man, And all their skill proves useless. 28 Then they cry out to Jehovah in their distress, And he rescues them from their plight. 29 He calms the windstorm; The waves of the sea grow quiet. 30 They rejoice when these grow still, And he leads them to their desired harbor. 31 Let people give thanks to Jehovah for his loyal love And for his wonderful works in behalf of the sons of men. 32 Let them exalt him in the congregation of the people, And let them praise him in the council* of the elders. 33 He turns rivers into a desert And springs of water into parched ground, 34 Fruitful land into salty wasteland, Because of the wickedness of those dwelling in it. 35 He turns the desert into reedy pools of water, And dry land into springs of water. 36 He causes the hungry to dwell there, So that they may establish a city where they can live. 37 They sow fields and plant vineyards That yield fruitful crops. 38 He blesses them and they increase greatly; He does not let their cattle diminish. 39 But again they become few and are humiliated Because of oppression, calamity, and grief. 40 He pours out contempt upon nobles And makes them wander in trackless wastelands. 41 But he protects* the poor from oppression And makes their families as numerous as a flock. 42 The upright see this and rejoice; But all the unrighteous shut their mouths. 43 Whoever is wise will observe these things And will carefully consider Jehovah’s acts of loyal love.

A song. A melody of David. 108 My heart is steadfast, O God. I will sing and make music with my whole being.*  2 Do awake, O stringed instrument; you too, O harp. I will awaken the dawn.  3 I will praise you among the peoples, O Jehovah, And I will sing praises* to you among the nations.  4 For your loyal love is great, as high as the heavens, And your faithfulness, up to the skies.  5 Be exalted above the heavens, O God; May your glory be over all the earth.  6 So that your loved ones may be rescued, Save us with your right hand and answer me.  7 God has spoken in his holiness:* “I will exult, I will give out Sheʹchem as an inheritance, And I will measure off the Valley* of Sucʹcoth.  8 Gilʹe·ad belongs to me, as does Ma·nasʹseh, And Eʹphra·im is the helmet* for my head; Judah is my commander’s staff.  9 Moʹab is my washbasin. Over Eʹdom I will throw my sandal. Over Phi·lisʹti·a I will shout in triumph.” 10 Who will bring me to the fortified city? Who will lead me as far as Eʹdom? 11 Is it not you, O God, who have rejected us, Our God, who no longer goes out with our armies? 12 Help us in our distress, For salvation by humans is worthless. 13 By God we will gain power, And he will trample on our adversaries.

To the director. Of David. A melody. 109 O God whom I praise, do not remain silent.  2 For the wicked and the deceitful open their mouths against me. They speak about me with lying tongues;  3 They surround me with hateful words, And they attack me without cause.  4 They resist me in response to my love; But I continue to pray.  5 They repay me with bad for good And hatred for my love.  6 Appoint a wicked man over him; May a resister* stand at his right hand.  7 When he is judged, may he be found guilty;* May even his prayer be counted as a sin.  8 Let his days be few; His office of oversight let someone else take.  9 Let his children* become fatherless, And his wife, a widow. 10 May his children* become wandering beggars, Foraging for food from their ruined homes. 11 May his creditor seize* all that he has, And may strangers plunder his possessions. 12 May no one extend kindness* to him, And may no one show favor to his fatherless children. 13 Let his descendants* be cut off; May their name be erased within a generation. 14 Let the error of his forefathers be remembered by Jehovah, And may the sin of his mother not be erased. 15 May Jehovah always be mindful of what they have done; And may he cut off the memory of them from the earth. 16 For he did not remember to show kindness,* But he kept pursuing the oppressed, poor, and brokenhearted man To put him to death. 17 He loved to pronounce a curse, so that is what came upon him; He had no desire to bless, so he received no blessing. 18 He was clothed with curses as his garment. And they were poured into his body like water, Into his bones like oil. 19 May his curses be like the clothing in which he wraps himself And like a belt he always wears. 20 This is the payment from Jehovah for the one who resists me And for those who speak evil things against me.* 21 But you, Jehovah the Sovereign Lord, Act in my behalf for the sake of your name. Rescue me, because your loyal love is good. 22 For I am helpless and poor, And my heart has been pierced within me. 23 I am passing away like a fading shadow; I have been shaken off like a locust. 24 My knees give way from fasting; My body is thin, and I am wasting away.* 25 I have become the object of their taunts. When they see me, they shake their heads. 26 Help me, O Jehovah my God; Save me by your loyal love. 27 May they know that this is by your hand; That you, O Jehovah, have done it. 28 Let them pronounce a curse, but may you give a blessing. When they rise up against me, may they be put to shame, But let your servant rejoice. 29 Let those who resist me be clothed with humiliation; May they be wrapped in their shame as in a robe.* 30 My mouth will fervently praise Jehovah; I will praise him in front of many people. 31 For he will stand at the right hand of the poor To save him from those who condemn him.*

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “goodwill.”

Or “may boast about.”

Or “grasp the meaning of.”

Or “wilderness.”

Or “was left.”

Or “their soul.”

Or “molten statue.”

Lit., “stood in the breach before him.”

Or “attached themselves to.”

That is, sacrifices offered either to dead people or to lifeless gods.

Meaning “Quarreling.”

Or “learned.”

Lit., “hand.”

Or “feel regret.”

Or “abundant.”

Or “exult in your praise.”

Or “From eternity to eternity.”

Or “So be it!”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “repurchased.”

Or “power.”

Or “From sunrise and from sunset.”

Or “Their soul was.”

Or “the parched soul.”

Or “the hungry soul.”

Or “Their soul detested.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “seat.”

Or “puts on high,” that is, out of reach.

Lit., “even my glory.”

Or “make music.”

Or possibly, “in his holy place.”

Or “Low Plain.”

Lit., “stronghold.”

Or “an accuser.”

Or “wicked.”

Lit., “sons.”

Lit., “sons.”

Or “May usurers lay out traps for.”

Or “loyal love.”

Or “posterity.”

Or “loyal love.”

Or “my soul.”

Lit., “My flesh has grown lean, without fatness (oil).”

Or “sleeveless coat.”

Or “his soul.”

^ (Ps. 106:1-22) Praise Jah!* Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; His loyal love endures forever.  2 Who can fully declare Jehovah’s mighty acts Or proclaim all his praiseworthy deeds?  3 Happy are those who act with justice, Who always do what is right.  4 Remember me, O Jehovah, when you show favor* toward your people. Take care of me with your acts of salvation,  5 So that I may enjoy the goodness you show your chosen ones, That I may rejoice along with your nation, That I may proudly praise* you along with your inheritance.  6 We have sinned just as our forefathers did; We have done wrong; we have acted wickedly.  7 Our forefathers in Egypt did not appreciate* your wonderful works. They did not remember your abundant loyal love, But they rebelled at the sea, by the Red Sea.  8 But he saved them for the sake of his name, To make his mightiness known.  9 He rebuked the Red Sea, and it dried up; He led them through its depths as through a desert;* 10 He saved them from the hand of their foe And reclaimed them from the hand of the enemy. 11 The waters covered their adversaries; Not one of them survived.* 12 Then they had faith in his promise; They began to sing his praise. 13 But they quickly forgot what he did; They did not wait for his counsel. 14 They gave way to their selfish desires in the wilderness; They tested God in the desert. 15 He gave them what they requested, But then struck them with disease that made them* waste away. 16 In the camp they grew jealous of Moses And of Aaron, the holy one of Jehovah. 17 The earth then opened up and swallowed Daʹthan And covered those assembled with A·biʹram. 18 A fire blazed among their group; A flame consumed the wicked. 19 They made a calf in Hoʹreb And bowed down to a statue of metal;* 20 They exchanged my glory For the representation of a grass-eating bull. 21 They forgot God their Savior, Who did great things in Egypt, 22 Wonderful works in the land of Ham, Awe-inspiring deeds at the Red Sea.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “goodwill.”

Or “may boast about.”

Or “grasp the meaning of.”

Or “wilderness.”

Or “was left.”

Or “their soul.”

Or “molten statue.”

^ ***sn song 2 We Thank You, Jehovah***

Song 2

We Thank You, Jehovah

(1 Thessalonians 5:18)

1. We thank you, Jehovah, each day and each night,

That you shed upon us your precious light.

We thank you that we have the priv’lege of prayer,

That we can approach you with ev’ry care.

2. We thank you, Jehovah, for your loving Son,

Who conquered the world; By his faith he won.

We thank you for guidance in doing your will,

For thus you do help us our vows fulfill.

3. We thank you, our God, for the honor to preach

About your great name and the truth to teach.

We thank you that soon all earth’s woes will be past,

While your Kingdom blessings forever last.

(See also [Ps. 50:14;][95:2;][147:7;][Col. 3:15].)

^ (1 Thess. 5:18) Give thanks for everything. This is God’s will for you in Christ Jesus.

^ (Ps. 50:14) Offer thanksgiving as your sacrifice to God, And pay your vows to the Most High;

^ (Ps. 95:2) Let us come into his presence* with thanksgiving; Let us sing and shout in triumph to him.

Lit., “before his face.”

^ (Ps. 147:7) Sing to Jehovah with thanksgiving; Sing praises to our God, accompanied by the harp,

^ (Col. 3:15) Also, let the peace of the Christ rule in your hearts,* for you were called to that peace in one body. And show yourselves thankful.

Or “control your hearts.”

^ ***w15 1/15 p. 8 Give Thanks to Jehovah and Be Blessed***

How can reflecting on our blessings help us to cope with trials?

1. Why is Jehovah worthy of our thanks?

JEHOVAH, the Giver of “every good gift and every perfect present,” is indeed worthy of our thanks. ([Jas. 1:17]) As our loving Shepherd, he tenderly cares for all our physical and spiritual needs. ([Ps. 23:1-3]) He has proved to be “our refuge and strength”—especially in times of distress! ([Ps. 46:1]) Surely we have many reasons to agree wholeheartedly with the psalmist who wrote: “Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; his loyal love endures forever.”—[Ps. 106:1].

Our yeartext for 2015: “Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good.”—[Psalm 106:1]

^ par. 1 (Jas. 1:17) Every good gift and every perfect present is from above, coming down from the Father of the celestial lights, who does not vary or change like the shifting shadows.*

Or “with whom there is not a variation of the turning of the shadow.”

^ par. 1 (Ps. 23:1-3) Jehovah is my Shepherd. I will lack nothing.  2 In grassy pastures he makes me lie down; He leads me to well-watered resting-places.*  3 He refreshes me.* He leads me in the paths* of righteousness for the sake of his name.

Or possibly, “to tranquil waters.”

Or “my soul.”

Lit., “tracks.”

^ par. 1 (Ps. 46:1) God is our refuge and strength, A help that is readily found in times of distress.

^ par. 1 (Ps. 106:1) Praise Jah!* Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; His loyal love endures forever.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

^ (Ps. 106:1) Praise Jah!* Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; His loyal love endures forever.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

^ ***w02 6/1 p. 18 Find Delight in Jehovah’s Righteousness***

19. What blessings can be ours if we find delight in God’s righteousness?

19 In these perilous and uncertain days, taking delight in Jehovah’s righteousness is a source of security and protection. To the question: “O Jehovah, who will be a guest in your tent? Who will reside in your holy mountain?” King David answered: “He who is walking faultlessly and practicing righteousness.” (Psalm 15:1, 2) By pursuing God’s righteousness and finding delight in it, we can maintain a good relationship with him and continue to enjoy his favor and blessing. Thus, ours is a life of contentment, self-respect, and peace of mind. “He that is pursuing righteousness and loving-kindness will find life, righteousness and glory,” says God’s Word. (Proverbs 21:21) Furthermore, trying our best to do what is just and right in all our endeavors means happy personal relationships and an improved quality of life—morally and spiritually. The psalmist declared: “Happy are those observing justice, doing righteousness all the time.”—[Psalm 106:3].

^ par. 19 (Ps. 15:1, 2) O Jehovah, who may be a guest in your tent? Who may reside in your holy mountain?  2 The one who is walking faultlessly,* Practicing what is right And speaking the truth in his heart.

Or “with integrity.”

^ par. 19 (Prov. 21:21) Whoever pursues righteousness and loyal love Will find life, righteousness, and glory.

^ par. 19 (Ps. 106:3) Happy are those who act with justice, Who always do what is right.

^ ***w15 1/15 pp. 8-9 Give Thanks to Jehovah and Be Blessed***

2, 3. (a) What are the dangers of taking our blessings for granted? (b) What questions will we consider in this article?

2 Why is it important for us to consider this matter of giving thanks? As foretold, people in these last days have become increasingly unthankful. ([2 Tim. 3:2]) Many take their blessings for granted. Influenced by the commercial world and its advertising, millions of people strive to obtain more instead of being content with what they have. We too can be affected by this unappreciative spirit. Like the ancient Israelites, we could become ungrateful and lose appreciation for our precious relationship with Jehovah and for the blessings that we have received from him.—[Ps. 106:7,][11-13].

3 Then, too, consider what can happen when we undergo difficult trials. At such times, we could easily become overwhelmed and lose sight of our blessings. ([Ps. 116:3]) Therefore, how can we cultivate a grateful heart and maintain it? And what will help us to remain positive even when we are undergoing severe trials? Let us see.

^ par. 2 (2 Tim. 3:2) For men will be lovers of themselves, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, disloyal,

^ par. 2 (Ps. 106:7) Our forefathers in Egypt did not appreciate* your wonderful works. They did not remember your abundant loyal love, But they rebelled at the sea, by the Red Sea.

Or “grasp the meaning of.”

^ par. 2 (Ps. 106:11-13) The waters covered their adversaries; Not one of them survived.* 12 Then they had faith in his promise; They began to sing his praise. 13 But they quickly forgot what he did; They did not wait for his counsel.

Or “was left.”

^ par. 3 (Ps. 116:3) The ropes of death encircled me; The Grave had me in its grip.* I was overcome by distress and grief.

Lit., “The distresses of Sheol found me.”

^ ***w01 6/15 p. 13 Do Not Become Forgetful Hearers***

1. What miracles were the people of ancient Israel privileged to witness?

“UNFORGETTABLE” would be a good word to describe the miracles performed by Jehovah in ancient Egypt. Each one of the Ten Plagues was undeniably awesome. Those blows were followed by the amazing deliverance of the people of Israel through the parted waters of the Red Sea. (Deuteronomy 34:10-12) If you had been an eyewitness of those events, hopefully you would never have forgotten the One responsible for them. Yet, the psalmist sang: “They [the Israelites] forgot God their Savior, the Doer of great things in Egypt, wonderful works in the land of Ham, fear-inspiring things at the Red Sea.”—Psalm 106:21, 22.

2. What shows that Israel’s appreciation for God’s mighty acts was short-lived?

2 After crossing the Red Sea, the Israelites “began to fear Jehovah and to put faith in Jehovah.” ([Exodus 14:31]) The men of Israel joined Moses in a victory song to Jehovah, and Miriam and other women responded by playing tambourines and dancing. ([Exodus 15:1,][20]) Yes, God’s people were impressed with Jehovah’s mighty acts. But their appreciation for the One who performed those acts was short-lived. Soon afterward many of them behaved as though they had suffered a major memory loss. They became murmurers and complainers against Jehovah. Some engaged in idolatry and sexual immorality.—Numbers 14:27;[25:1-9].

What Could Make Us Forget?

3. Because of our imperfect nature, what could we forget?

3 Israel’s lack of appreciation is indeed perplexing. Still, the same thing could happen to us. True, we have not witnessed such divine miracles. In our relationship with God, however, there surely have been occasions that were unforgettable. Some of us may remember when we accepted the truth from the Bible. Other joyful times may include our prayer of dedication to Jehovah and our water baptism as true Christians. Many of us have experienced Jehovah’s helping hand at other points in our life. ([Psalm 118:15]) Above all, through the sacrificial death of God’s own Son, Jesus Christ, we have received the hope of salvation. ([John 3:16]) Nevertheless, because of our imperfect nature, when faced with wrong desires and the anxieties of life, we may too easily forget the good things that Jehovah has done for us.

^ par. 1 (Deut. 34:10-12) But there has never again arisen a prophet in Israel like Moses, whom Jehovah knew face-to-face. 11 He performed all the signs and the miracles that Jehovah had sent him to do in the land of Egypt to Pharʹaoh and all his servants and all his land, 12 along with the mighty hand and the awesome power that Moses displayed before the eyes of all Israel.

^ par. 1 (Ps. 106:21, 22) They forgot God their Savior, Who did great things in Egypt, 22 Wonderful works in the land of Ham, Awe-inspiring deeds at the Red Sea.

^ par. 2 (Ex. 14:31) Israel also saw the great power* that Jehovah wielded against the Egyptians, and the people began to fear Jehovah and to put faith in Jehovah and in his servant Moses.

Lit., “hand.”

^ par. 2 (Ex. 15:1) At that time Moses and the Israelites sang this song to Jehovah: “Let me sing to Jehovah, for he has become highly exalted. The horse and its rider he has hurled into the sea.

^ par. 2 (Ex. 15:20) Then Mirʹi·am the prophetess, Aaron’s sister, took a tambourine in her hand, and all the women followed her with tambourines and with dances.

^ par. 2 (Num. 14:27) “How much longer will this evil assembly keep up this murmuring against me? I have heard what the Israelites are murmuring against me.

^ par. 2 (Num. 25:1-9) When Israel was dwelling in Shitʹtim, the people started to commit sexual immorality with the daughters of Moʹab. 2 The women invited the people to the sacrifices of their gods, and the people began to eat and to bow down to their gods. 3 So Israel joined in worship of* the Baʹal of Peʹor, and Jehovah became enraged with Israel. 4 Jehovah said to Moses: “Take all the leaders* of these people and hang them up before Jehovah in broad daylight,* that the burning anger of Jehovah may turn back from Israel.” 5 Then Moses said to the judges of Israel: “Each one of you should kill his men who joined in worship of* the Baʹal of Peʹor.” 6 But just then, there came one of the Israelites bringing near to his brothers a Midʹi·an·ite woman before the eyes of Moses and of all the assembly of the Israelites, while they were weeping at the entrance of the tent of meeting. 7 When Phinʹe·has the son of El·e·aʹzar the son of Aaron the priest saw it, he immediately rose up from the midst of the assembly and took a spear* in his hand. 8 Then he went after the man of Israel into the tent and pierced both of them through, the man of Israel and the woman through her genital parts. At that the scourge on the Israelites was halted. 9 Those who died from the scourge amounted to 24,000.

Or “attached itself to.”

Lit., “heads.”

Lit., “in front of the sun.”

Or “attached themselves to.”

Or “lance.”

^ par. 3 (Ps. 118:15) The sound of rejoicing and salvation* Is in the tents of the righteous. The right hand of Jehovah is demonstrating its power.

Or “victory.”

^ par. 3 (John 3:16) “For God loved the world so much that he gave his only-begotten Son, so that everyone exercising faith in him might not be destroyed but have everlasting life.

^ ***w11 10/15 pp. 5-6 Let Us Rejoice Together!***

The situation of fellow Christians, however, is different, and so is their spirit. The apostle Paul wrote: “Always be rejoicing.” (1 Thess. 5:16) There are many reasons for us to be joyful and to rejoice together. We worship the Most High God, Jehovah; we understand the Bible’s message of truth; we have the hope of salvation and eternal life; and we can also help others to attain the same blessings.—Ps. 106:4, 5;[Jer. 15:16;][Rom. 12:12].

^ (1 Thess. 5:16) Always be rejoicing.

^ (Ps. 106:4, 5) Remember me, O Jehovah, when you show favor* toward your people. Take care of me with your acts of salvation,  5 So that I may enjoy the goodness you show your chosen ones, That I may rejoice along with your nation, That I may proudly praise* you along with your inheritance.

Or “goodwill.”

Or “may boast about.”

^ (Jer. 15:16) Your words were found, and I ate them; And your word became to me the exultation and the rejoicing of my heart, For your name has been called on me, O Jehovah God of armies.

^ (Rom. 12:12) Rejoice in the hope. Endure under tribulation. Persevere in prayer.

^ ***w03 12/1 pp. 15-16 “Show Yourselves Thankful”***

Reasons for Being Thankful

3. For what are we thankful to Jehovah?

3 It is to Jehovah God, our Creator and Life-Giver, that we owe our gratitude, especially as we consider some of the bounteous gifts he has showered upon us. ([James 1:17]) Daily, we thank Jehovah that we are alive. ([Psalm 36:9]) Around us, we observe abundant evidence of Jehovah’s handiwork, such as the sun, moon, and stars. Our planet’s rich storehouse of life-sustaining minerals, the atmosphere’s finely balanced mixture of vital gases, and the intricate cycles in nature all testify to the debt we owe our loving heavenly Father. “Many things you yourself have done, O Jehovah my God,” sang King David, “even your wonderful works and your thoughts toward us; there is none to be compared to you. Were I inclined to tell and speak of them, they have become more numerous than I can recount.”—[Psalm 40:5].

4. Why should we thank Jehovah for the happy association we enjoy in our congregations?

4 Though far removed from a physical paradise, Jehovah’s servants today relish living in a spiritual paradise. In our Kingdom Halls and at our conventions and assemblies, we experience the fruitage of God’s spirit at work in our fellow believers. Indeed, when preaching to people who have little or no religious background, some Witnesses refer to what Paul described in his letter to the Galatians. They first draw attention to “the works of the flesh” and ask their listeners what they have observed. (Galatians 5:19-23) Most readily agree that these characterize human society today. When shown the description of the fruitage of God’s spirit and upon being invited to the local Kingdom Hall to see evidence of this for themselves, many quickly acknowledge: “God is really among you.” (1 Corinthians 14:25) And this is not limited to the local Kingdom Hall. Travel where you may, when you meet any of the more than six million Witnesses of Jehovah, you find the same happy, joyous spirit. Truly, this upbuilding association is reason for giving thanks to Jehovah, the one who supplies his spirit to make it possible.—Zephaniah 3:9; Ephesians 3:20, 21.

5, 6. How can we show ourselves thankful for God’s greatest gift, the ransom?

5 The greatest gift, the most perfect present that Jehovah has bestowed, is that of his Son, Jesus, by means of whom the ransom sacrifice was provided. “If this is how God loved us,” wrote the apostle John, “then we are ourselves under obligation to love one another.” ([1 John 4:11]) Yes, we show ourselves thankful for the ransom not only by expressing love and gratitude to Jehovah but also by living our lives in a way that manifests love for others.—Matthew 22:37-39.

6 We can learn more about showing gratitude by considering the way Jehovah dealt with Israel of old. By means of the Law, which he gave to the nation through Moses, Jehovah taught the people many lessons. Through “the framework of the knowledge and of the truth in the Law,” we can learn much that will help us follow Paul’s counsel: “Show yourselves thankful.”—[Romans 2:20;] Colossians 3:15.

^ par. 3 (Jas. 1:17) Every good gift and every perfect present is from above, coming down from the Father of the celestial lights, who does not vary or change like the shifting shadows.*

Or “with whom there is not a variation of the turning of the shadow.”

^ par. 3 (Ps. 36:9) With you is the source of life; By your light we can see light.

^ par. 3 (Ps. 40:5) How many things you have done, O Jehovah my God, Your wonderful works and your thoughts toward us. None can compare to you; If I were to try to tell and speak of them, They would be too numerous to recount!

^ par. 4 (Gal. 5:19-23) Now the works of the flesh are plainly seen, and they are sexual immorality,* uncleanness, brazen conduct,* 20 idolatry, spiritism,* hostility, strife, jealousy, fits of anger, dissensions, divisions, sects, 21 envy, drunkenness, wild parties,* and things like these. I am forewarning you about these things, the same way I already warned you, that those who practice such things will not inherit God’s Kingdom. 22 On the other hand, the fruitage of the spirit is love, joy, peace, patience,* kindness, goodness, faith, 23 mildness, self-control. Against such things there is no law.

Greek, por·neiʹa. See Glossary.

Or “shameless conduct.” Greek, a·selʹgei·a. See Glossary.

Or “sorcery; druggery.”

Or “revelries.”

Or “long-suffering.”

^ par. 4 (1 Cor. 14:25) The secrets of his heart then become evident, so that he will fall facedown and worship God, declaring: “God is really among you.”

^ par. 4 (Zeph. 3:9) For then I will change the language of the peoples to a pure language, So that all of them may call on the name of Jehovah, To serve him shoulder to shoulder.’*

Or “worship him in unity.”

^ par. 4 (Eph. 3:20, 21) Now to the one who can, according to his power that is operating in us, do more than superabundantly beyond all the things we ask or conceive, 21 to him be the glory by means of the congregation and by means of Christ Jesus to all generations forever and ever. Amen.

^ par. 5 (1 John 4:11) Beloved ones, if this is how God loved us, then we are also under obligation to love one another.

^ par. 5 (Matt. 22:37-39) He said to him: “‘You must love Jehovah* your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul* and with your whole mind.’ 38 This is the greatest and first commandment. 39 The second, like it, is this: ‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’

See App. A5.

See Glossary.

^ par. 6 (Rom. 2:20) a corrector of the unreasonable ones, a teacher of young children, and having the framework of the knowledge and of the truth in the Law—

^ par. 6 (Col. 3:15) Also, let the peace of the Christ rule in your hearts,* for you were called to that peace in one body. And show yourselves thankful.

Or “control your hearts.”

^ ***w00 12/15 p. 24 Stand Complete With Firm Conviction***

20. If a relatively few deflect from the Christian way, why need this be no cause for discouragement?

20 You should not be distracted or discouraged by the fact that not all stand complete and with firm conviction. Some may fail, be deflected, or simply give up. That happened among those closest to Jesus, his apostles. But when Judas turned traitor, did the other apostles slow down or quit? No, indeed! Peter applied [Psalm 109:8] to show that another would take Judas’ place. A replacement was selected, and God’s loyal ones actively got on with their preaching assignment. ([Acts 1:15-26]) They were determined to stand complete with firm conviction.

^ par. 20 (Ps. 109:8) Let his days be few; His office of oversight let someone else take.

^ par. 20 (Acts 1:15-26) During those days Peter stood up in the midst of the brothers (the number* of people was altogether about 120) and said: 16 “Men, brothers, it was necessary for the scripture to be fulfilled that the holy spirit spoke prophetically through David about Judas, who became a guide to those who arrested Jesus. 17 For he had been numbered among us and he obtained a share in this ministry. 18 (This very man, therefore, purchased a field with the wages for unrighteousness, and falling headfirst, his body burst open* and all his insides spilled out. 19 This became known to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that the field was called in their language A·kelʹda·ma, that is, “Field of Blood.”) 20 For it is written in the book of Psalms, ‘Let his dwelling become desolate, and let there be no inhabitant in it’ and, ‘His office of oversight let someone else take.’ 21 It is therefore necessary that of the men who accompanied us during all the time in which the Lord Jesus carried on his activities* among us, 22 starting with his baptism by John until the day he was taken up from us, one of these men should become a witness with us of his resurrection.” 23 So they proposed two, Joseph called Barʹsab·bas, who was also called Justus, and Mat·thiʹas. 24 Then they prayed and said: “You, O Jehovah,* who know the hearts of all, designate which one of these two men you have chosen 25 to take the place of this ministry and apostleship, from which Judas deviated to go to his own place.” 26 So they cast lots over them, and the lot fell to Mat·thiʹas, and he was counted* along with the 11 apostles.

Or “crowd.”

Or “he burst open in the middle.”

Lit., “went in and out.”

See App. A5.

Or “reckoned,” that is, viewed the same as the other 11.

^ ***it-1 pp. 857-858 Foreknowledge, Foreordination***

Did God predestine Judas to betray Jesus in order to fulfill prophecy?

The traitorous course of Judas Iscariot fulfilled divine prophecy and demonstrated Jehovah’s foreknowledge as well as that of his Son. ([Ps 41:9;][55:12, 13;][109:8;][Ac 1:16-20]) Yet it cannot be said that God foreordained or predestinated Judas himself to such a course. The prophecies foretold that some intimate acquaintance of Jesus would be his betrayer, but they did not specify which of those sharing such acquaintance it would be. Again, Bible principles rule against God’s having foreordained Judas’ actions. The divine standard stated by the apostle is: “Never lay your hands hastily upon any man; neither be a sharer in the sins of others; preserve yourself chaste.” ([1Ti 5:22]; compare [3:6].) Evidencing his concern that the selection of his 12 apostles be wisely and properly made, Jesus spent the night in prayer to his Father before making known his decision. ([Lu 6:12-16]) If Judas were already divinely foreordained to be a traitor, this would result in inconsistency in God’s direction and guidance and, according to the rule, would make him a sharer in the sins that one committed.

Thus, it seems evident that at the time of his being selected as an apostle, Judas’ heart presented no definite evidence of a treasonous attitude. He allowed a ‘poisonous root to spring up’ and defile him, resulting in his deviation and in his accepting, not God’s direction, but the Devil’s leading in a course of thievery and treachery. (Heb 12:14, 15;[Joh 13:2;] Ac 1:24, 25; Jas 1:14, 15; see JUDAS No. 4.) By the time such deviation reached a certain point, Jesus himself could read Judas’ heart and foretell his betrayal.—Joh 13:10, 11.

True, in the account at [John 6:64], on the occasion of some disciples stumbling over certain teachings of Jesus, we read that “from the beginning [“from the outset,” JB] Jesus knew who were the ones not believing and who was the one that would betray him.” While the word “beginning” (Gr., ar·kheʹ) is used at [2 Peter 3:4] to refer to the start of creation, it can also refer to other times. ([Lu 1:2;][Joh 15:27]) For example, when the apostle Peter spoke of the holy spirit falling on Gentiles “just as it did also upon us in the beginning,” he obviously was not referring to the beginning of his discipleship or apostleship but to an important point in his ministry, the day of Pentecost, 33 C.E., “the beginning” of the outpouring of the holy spirit for a certain purpose. ([Ac 11:15;][2:1-4]) It is therefore interesting to note this comment on [John 6:64] in Lange’s Commentary on the Holy Scriptures (p. 227): “Beginning . . . means not, metaphysically from the beginning of all things, . . . nor from the beginning of His [Jesus’] acquaintance with each one, . . . nor from the beginning of His collecting of the disciples around Him, or the beginning of His Messianic ministry, . . . but from the first secret germs of unbelief [that produced the stumbling of some disciples]. So also He knew His betrayer from the beginning.”—Translated and edited by P. Schaff, 1976; compare [1Jo 3:8,][11, 12].

^ (Ps. 41:9) Even the man at peace with me, one whom I trusted, Who was eating my bread, has lifted his heel against me.*

Or “turned against me.”

^ (Ps. 55:12, 13) For it is not an enemy who taunts me; Otherwise I could put up with it. It is not a foe who has risen up against me; Otherwise I could conceal myself from him. 13 But it is you, a man like me,* My own companion whom I know well.

Or “a man, my equal.”

^ (Ps. 109:8) Let his days be few; His office of oversight let someone else take.

^ (Acts 1:16-20) “Men, brothers, it was necessary for the scripture to be fulfilled that the holy spirit spoke prophetically through David about Judas, who became a guide to those who arrested Jesus. 17 For he had been numbered among us and he obtained a share in this ministry. 18 (This very man, therefore, purchased a field with the wages for unrighteousness, and falling headfirst, his body burst open* and all his insides spilled out. 19 This became known to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that the field was called in their language A·kelʹda·ma, that is, “Field of Blood.”) 20 For it is written in the book of Psalms, ‘Let his dwelling become desolate, and let there be no inhabitant in it’ and, ‘His office of oversight let someone else take.’

Or “he burst open in the middle.”

^ (1 Tim. 5:22) Never lay your hands hastily on any man;* neither become a sharer in the sins of others; keep yourself chaste.

That is, do not appoint any man hastily.

^ (1 Tim. 3:6) not a newly converted man, for fear that he might get puffed up with pride and fall into the judgment passed on the Devil.

^ (Luke 6:12-16) On one of those days he went out to the mountain to pray, and he spent the whole night in prayer to God. 13 And when it became day, he called his disciples to him and chose from among them 12, whom he also named apostles: 14 Simon, whom he also named Peter, Andrew his brother, James, John, Philip, Bar·tholʹo·mew, 15 Matthew, Thomas, James the son of Al·phaeʹus, Simon who is called “the zealous one,” 16 Judas the son of James, and Judas Is·carʹi·ot, who turned traitor.

^ (Heb. 12:14, 15) Pursue peace with all people and the sanctification* without which no man will see the Lord. 15 Carefully watch that no one fails to obtain the undeserved kindness of God, so that no poisonous root springs up to cause trouble and many are defiled by it;

Or “holiness.”

^ (John 13:2) The evening meal was going on, and the Devil had already put it into the heart of Judas Is·carʹi·ot, the son of Simon, to betray him.

^ (Acts 1:24, 25) Then they prayed and said: “You, O Jehovah,* who know the hearts of all, designate which one of these two men you have chosen 25 to take the place of this ministry and apostleship, from which Judas deviated to go to his own place.”

See App. A5.

^ (Jas. 1:14, 15) But each one is tried by being drawn out and enticed* by his own desire. 15 Then the desire, when it has become fertile,* gives birth to sin; in turn sin, when it has been carried out, brings forth death.

Or “caught as by bait.”

Lit., “has conceived.”

^ (John 13:10, 11) Jesus said to him: “Whoever has bathed does not need to have more than his feet washed, but is completely clean. And you men are clean, but not all of you.” 11 For he knew the man who was betraying him. This is why he said: “Not all of you are clean.”

^ (John 6:64) But there are some of you who do not believe.” For Jesus knew from the beginning those who did not believe and the one who would betray him.

^ (2 Pet. 3:4) and saying: “Where is this promised presence of his? Why, from the day our forefathers fell asleep in death, all things are continuing exactly as they were from creation’s beginning.”

^ (Luke 1:2) just as these were handed down to us by those who from the beginning were eyewitnesses and attendants of the message,

^ (John 15:27) and you, in turn, are to bear witness, because you have been with me from the beginning.

^ (Acts 11:15) But when I started to speak, the holy spirit fell on them just as it did also on us in the beginning.

^ (Acts 2:1-4) Now while the day of the Festival of Pentecost was in progress, they were all together at the same place. 2 Suddenly there was a noise from heaven, just like that of a rushing, stiff breeze, and it filled the whole house where they were sitting. 3 And tongues as if of fire became visible to them and were distributed, and one came to rest on each one of them, 4 and they all became filled with holy spirit and started to speak in different languages,* just as the spirit enabled them to speak.

Or “tongues.”

^ (John 6:64) But there are some of you who do not believe.” For Jesus knew from the beginning those who did not believe and the one who would betray him.

^ (1 John 3:8) The one who practices sin originates with the Devil, because the Devil has been sinning from the beginning.* For this purpose the Son of God was made manifest, to break up* the works of the Devil.

Or “from when he began.”

Or “destroy.”

^ (1 John 3:11, 12) For this is the message that you have heard from the beginning, that we should love one another; 12 not like Cain, who originated with the wicked one and slaughtered his brother. And for what reason did he slaughter him? Because his own works were wicked, but those of his brother were righteous.

^ ***w06 9/1 p. 14 par. 8 Highlights From Book Five of Psalms***

109:30, 31; 110:5. The sword-wielding right hand of a soldier normally lacks the protection of the shield, which was held on the left. Metaphorically, Jehovah is “at the right hand” of his servants, to fight for them. Thus he gives them protection and help—a fine reason for us to “laud [him] very much”!

^ par. 8 (Ps. 109:30, 31) My mouth will fervently praise Jehovah; I will praise him in front of many people. 31 For he will stand at the right hand of the poor To save him from those who condemn him.*

Or “his soul.”

^ par. 8 (Ps. 110:5) Jehovah will be at your right hand; He will crush kings on the day of his anger.

^ ***ll p. 6 Who Is the True God?***

Part 2

Who Is the True God?

There is only one true God, and his name is Jehovah. ([Psalm 83:18]) He is a Spirit; we cannot see him. He loves us and wants us to love him in return. He also wants us to love other people. (Matthew 22:35-40) He is the Supreme One, the Creator of all things.

The first of God’s creations was a mighty spirit person who later came to be known as Jesus Christ. Jehovah also created the angels.

Jehovah created everything in heaven . . . and on earth. Revelation 4:11

^ (Ps. 83:18) May people know that you, whose name is Jehovah, You alone are the Most High over all the earth.

^ (Matt. 22:35-40) And one of them, versed in the Law, tested him by asking: 36 “Teacher, which is the greatest commandment in the Law?” 37 He said to him: “‘You must love Jehovah* your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul* and with your whole mind.’ 38 This is the greatest and first commandment. 39 The second, like it, is this: ‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’ 40 On these two commandments the whole Law hangs, and the Prophets.”

See App. A5.

See Glossary.

^ (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

^ ***ll pp. 6-7 Who Is the True God?***

Jehovah created everything in heaven . . . and on earth. Revelation 4:11

Jehovah God created the stars as well as the earth and all that is on it.—[Genesis 1:1].

He formed Adam, the first man, from the dust of the ground.—[Genesis 2:7].

Why should we honor Jehovah?—[Isaiah 42:5].

What are some of God’s qualities?—[Exodus 34:6].

^ (Rev. 4:11) “You are worthy, Jehovah* our God, to receive the glory and the honor and the power, because you created all things, and because of your will they came into existence and were created.”

See App. A5.

^ (Gen. 1:1) In the beginning God created the heavens and the earth.

^ (Gen. 2:7) And Jehovah God went on to form the man out of dust from the ground and to blow into his nostrils the breath of life, and the man became a living person.*

Or “soul.” Hebrew, neʹphesh, which literally means “a breathing creature.” See Glossary.

^ (Isa. 42:5) This is what the true God, Jehovah, says, The Creator of the heavens and the Grand One who stretched them out, The One who spread out the earth and its produce, The One who gives breath to the people on it And spirit to those who walk on it:

^ (Ex. 34:6) Jehovah was passing before him and declaring: “Jehovah, Jehovah, a God merciful and compassionate,* slow to anger and abundant in loyal love* and truth,*

Or “gracious.”

Or “loving-kindness.”

Or “faithfulness.”

^ ***bh pp. 178-179 Baptism and Your Relationship With God***

MAKING A PERSONAL DEDICATION

14. What important step must you take before getting baptized?

14 There is another important step to take before getting baptized. You must dedicate yourself to Jehovah God.

15, 16. What does it mean to dedicate yourself to God, and what moves a person to do this?

15 When you dedicate yourself to Jehovah God in earnest prayer, you promise to give him your exclusive devotion forever. (Deuteronomy 6:15) Why, though, would someone want to do that? Well, suppose a man has begun to court a woman. The more he learns about her and sees that she has fine qualities, the more he finds himself drawn to her. In time, it is natural that he would ask her to marry him. True, getting married will mean taking on additional responsibilities. But love will move him to take that important step.

16 When you come to know and love Jehovah, you are moved to serve him without holding anything back or setting any limits in worshipping him. Anyone who wants to follow God’s Son, Jesus Christ, has to “disown himself.” ([Mark 8:34]) We disown ourselves by making sure that personal desires and goals do not stand in the way of our complete obedience to God. Before you can get baptized, then, doing Jehovah God’s will must be your main purpose in life.—Read 1 Peter 4:2.

^ par. 15 (Deut. 6:15) for Jehovah your God who is in your midst is a God who requires exclusive devotion. Otherwise, the anger of Jehovah your God will blaze against you and he will annihilate you from the face of the earth.

^ par. 16 (Mark 8:34) He now called the crowd to him with his disciples and said to them: “If anyone wants to come after me, let him disown himself and pick up his torture stake* and keep following me.

See Glossary.

^ par. 16 (1 Pet. 4:2) so that he may live the remainder of his time in the flesh, no more for the desires of men, but for God’s will.

^ ***sn song 94 Content With God’s Good Gifts***

Song 94

Content With God’s Good Gifts

([James 1:17])

1. All perfect presents, each good gift,

The things we’re fondest of,

The truly worthy things in life,

Come down from God above.

With him there is no wavering,

No change, however slight.

Jehovah is our Grand Provider,

The Source of life and light.

2. We have no cause for anxious care

Concerning daily needs;

We know the loving care by him

Who birds of heaven feeds.

We give no place to worthless things,

No years to hurtful strife.

But satisfied with God’s provisions,

We lead a simple life.

3. The lofty things in human eyes,

To God are merely vain.

Let’s use the days we’re granted now

For things of lasting gain.

The riches that we store with God

Are safe, though we may die.

We prize the gift of true contentment

And keep a simple eye.

(See also [Jer. 45:5;] Matt. 6:25-34;[1 Tim. 6:8;][Heb. 13:5].)

^ (Jas. 1:17) Every good gift and every perfect present is from above, coming down from the Father of the celestial lights, who does not vary or change like the shifting shadows.*

Or “with whom there is not a variation of the turning of the shadow.”

^ (Jer. 45:5) But you are seeking* great things for yourself. Stop seeking such things.”’ “‘For I am about to bring a calamity on all flesh,’* declares Jehovah, ‘and wherever you may go, I will grant you your life* as a spoil.’”*

Or “expecting.”

Or “people.”

Or “soul.”

Or “will let you escape with your life.”

^ (Matt. 6:25-34) “On this account I say to you: Stop being anxious about your lives* as to what you will eat or what you will drink, or about your bodies as to what you will wear. Does not life* mean more than food and the body than clothing? 26 Observe intently the birds of heaven; they do not sow seed or reap or gather into storehouses, yet your heavenly Father feeds them. Are you not worth more than they are? 27 Who of you by being anxious can add one cubit* to his life span? 28 Also, why are you anxious about clothing? Take a lesson from the lilies of the field, how they grow; they do not toil, nor do they spin; 29 but I tell you that not even Solʹo·mon in all his glory was arrayed as one of these. 30 Now if this is how God clothes the vegetation of the field that is here today and tomorrow is thrown into the oven, will he not much rather clothe you, you with little faith? 31 So never be anxious and say, ‘What are we to eat?’ or, ‘What are we to drink?’ or, ‘What are we to wear?’ 32 For all these are the things the nations are eagerly pursuing. Your heavenly Father knows that you need all these things. 33 “Keep on, then, seeking first the Kingdom and his righteousness, and all these other things will be added to you. 34 So never be anxious about the next day, for the next day will have its own anxieties. Each day has enough of its own troubles.

Or “souls.”

Or “the soul.”

See App. B14.

^ (1 Tim. 6:8) So, having food* and clothing,* we will be content with these things.

Or “sustenance.”

Or “shelter.” Lit., “covering.”

^ (Heb. 13:5) Let your way of life be free of the love of money, while you are content with the present things. For he has said: “I will never leave you, and I will never abandon you.”

^ ***ia pp. 191-194 He Was Loyal in the Face of Tests***

14. Jesus bestowed on Peter what important privileges?

14 This Christ was the one called in ancient prophecy a stone that the builders would reject. ([Ps. 118:22;][Luke 20:17]) With such prophecies in mind, Jesus revealed that Jehovah would establish a congregation on the very stone, or rock-mass, that Peter had just identified. Then he bestowed on Peter some very important privileges in that congregation. He did not give Peter primacy over the other apostles, as some have assumed, but he gave him responsibilities. He gave Peter “the keys of the kingdom.” ([Matt. 16:19]) It would be Peter’s privilege to open the hope of entering God’s Kingdom to three different fields of mankind—first to the Jews, then to the Samaritans, and finally to the Gentiles, or non-Jews.

15. What led Peter to rebuke Jesus, and in what words?

15 However, Jesus later stated that those given much would have more to answer for, and the truth of those words is borne out in Peter’s case. ([Luke 12:48]) Jesus continued to reveal vital truths about the Messiah, including the certainty of his own impending suffering and death at Jerusalem. Peter was disturbed to hear such things. He took Jesus aside and rebuked him, saying: “Be kind to yourself, Lord; you will not have this destiny at all.”—Matt. 16:21, 22.

16. How did Jesus correct Peter, and what practical counsel may all of us find in Jesus’ words?

16 Peter surely meant well, so Jesus’ reply must have come as a surprise. He turned his back on Peter, looked at the rest of the disciples—who had likely been thinking something similar—and said: “Get behind me, Satan! You are a stumbling block to me, because you think, not God’s thoughts, but those of men.” ([Matt. 16:23;] Mark 8:32, 33) Jesus’ words contain practical counsel for us all. It is only too easy to allow human thinking to take priority over godly thinking. If we do so, even when we mean to help, we may inadvertently become proponents of Satan’s purpose rather than God’s. How, though, did Peter respond?

17. What did Jesus mean by telling Peter to “get behind” him?

17 Peter must have realized that Jesus was not calling him Satan the Devil in any literal sense. After all, Jesus did not speak to Peter as he had to Satan. To Satan, Jesus had said: “Go away”; to Peter, he said: “Get behind me.” ([Matt. 4:10]) Jesus did not cast off this apostle in whom he saw a great deal of good, but he simply corrected Peter’s wrong thinking in this matter. It is not hard to see that Peter needed to stop getting in front of his Master as a stumbling block and needed to get back behind him as a supportive follower.

Only if we humbly accept discipline and learn from it can we continue to grow closer to Jesus Christ and his Father, Jehovah God

18. How did Peter demonstrate loyalty, and how can we imitate him?

18 Did Peter argue, get angry, or sulk? No; he humbly accepted correction. He thus demonstrated loyalty again. All those who follow Christ will need correction at times. Only if we humbly accept discipline and learn from it can we continue to grow closer to Jesus Christ and his Father, Jehovah God.—Read Proverbs 4:13.

Loyalty Rewarded

19. Jesus made what startling statement, and what may Peter have wondered?

19 Jesus soon made another startling statement: “Truly I say to you that there are some of those standing here that will not taste death at all until first they see the Son of man coming in his kingdom.” ([Matt. 16:28]) No doubt those words filled Peter with curiosity. What could Jesus possibly mean? Perhaps Peter wondered if the strong correction he had just received meant that no such special privileges would be coming his way.

20, 21. (a) Describe the vision that Peter witnessed. (b) How did the conversation among the figures in the vision help to correct Peter?

20 About a week later, however, Jesus took James, John, and Peter up into “a lofty mountain”—perhaps Mount Hermon, which was not many miles (25 km) distant. It was likely nighttime, since the three men were combating sleepiness. But as Jesus prayed, something happened that drove away any drowsiness.—[Matt. 17:1;] Luke 9:28, 29,[32].

21 Jesus began to change before their eyes. His face started to shine, to glow, until it became as brilliant as the sun. His clothes too were glistening white. Then two figures appeared with Jesus, one representing Moses and the other, Elijah. They conversed with him about “his departure that he was destined to fulfill at Jerusalem”—evidently his death and resurrection. How clear it was that Peter had been wrong to deny that Jesus had such a painful experience ahead of him!—Luke 9:30, 31.

22, 23. (a) How did Peter show an enthusiastic and warm spirit? (b) Peter, James, and John received what other reward that night?

22 Peter felt compelled to participate somehow in this extraordinary vision—and perhaps to prolong it. It looked as if Moses and Elijah were parting from Jesus. So Peter spoke up: “Instructor, it is fine for us to be here, so let us erect three tents, one for you and one for Moses and one for Elijah.” Of course, these visionary representations of two of Jehovah’s long-dead servants did not need tents. Peter really did not know what he was saying. Are you not drawn to the man, though, for his enthusiastic and warm spirit?—[Luke 9:33].

23 Peter, James, and John received another reward that night. A cloud formed and loomed over them on the mountain. From it came a voice—the voice of Jehovah God! He said: “This is my Son, the one that has been chosen. Listen to him.” Then the vision was over, and they were alone with Jesus on the mountain.—[Luke 9:34-36].

24. (a) How did the transfiguration vision benefit Peter? (b) How may we today benefit from the transfiguration vision?

24 What a gift that transfiguration vision was for Peter—and for us! Decades later he wrote of the privilege he had that night of actually seeing a preview of Jesus as a glorious heavenly King and of being one of the “eyewitnesses of his magnificence.” That vision confirmed many prophecies of God’s Word and strengthened Peter’s faith for the trials he had yet to face. (Read 2 Peter 1:16-19.) It can do the same for us if, like Peter, we remain loyal to the Master whom Jehovah has appointed over us, learning from him, accepting his discipline and correction, and humbly following him day by day.

^ par. 14 (Ps. 118:22) The stone that the builders rejected Has become the chief cornerstone.*

Lit., “the head of the corner.”

^ par. 14 (Luke 20:17) But he looked straight at them and said: “What, then, does this mean where it is written: ‘The stone that the builders rejected, this has become the chief cornerstone’?*

Lit., “the head of the corner.”

^ par. 14 (Matt. 16:19) I will give you the keys of the Kingdom of the heavens, and whatever you may bind on earth will already be bound in the heavens, and whatever you may loosen on earth will already be loosened in the heavens.”

^ par. 15 (Luke 12:48) But the one who did not understand and yet did things deserving of strokes will be beaten with few. Indeed, everyone to whom much was given, much will be demanded of him, and the one who was put in charge of much will have more than usual demanded of him.

^ par. 15 (Matt. 16:21, 22) From that time forward, Jesus began explaining to his disciples that he must go to Jerusalem and suffer many things from the elders and chief priests and scribes and be killed, and on the third day be raised up. 22 At this Peter took him aside and began to rebuke him, saying: “Be kind to yourself, Lord; you will not have this happen to you at all.”

^ par. 16 (Matt. 16:23) But turning his back, he said to Peter: “Get behind me, Satan! You are a stumbling block to me, because you think, not God’s thoughts, but those of men.”

^ par. 16 (Mark 8:32, 33) Indeed, he was making that statement openly. But Peter took him aside and began to rebuke him. 33 At this he turned, looked at his disciples, and rebuked Peter, saying: “Get behind me, Satan! because you think, not God’s thoughts, but those of men.”

^ par. 17 (Matt. 4:10) Then Jesus said to him: “Go away, Satan! For it is written: ‘It is Jehovah* your God you must worship, and it is to him alone you must render sacred service.’”

See App. A5.

^ par. 18 (Prov. 4:13) Hold on to discipline; do not let it go. Safeguard it, for it means your life.

^ par. 19 (Matt. 16:28) Truly I say to you that there are some of those standing here who will not taste death at all until first they see the Son of man coming in his Kingdom.”

^ par. 20 (Matt. 17:1) Six days later Jesus took Peter and James and his brother John along and led them up into a lofty mountain by themselves.

^ par. 20 (Luke 9:28, 29) In fact, about eight days after saying these words, he took Peter, John, and James along and climbed up the mountain to pray. 29 And as he was praying, the appearance of his face changed and his clothing became glitteringly white.

^ par. 20 (Luke 9:32) Now Peter and those with him were weighed down with sleep, but when they became fully awake, they saw his glory and the two men standing with him.

^ par. 21 (Luke 9:30, 31) And look! two men were conversing with him; they were Moses and E·liʹjah. 31 These appeared with glory and began talking about his departure, which he was about to fulfill at Jerusalem.

^ par. 22 (Luke 9:33) And as these were departing from him, Peter said to Jesus: “Instructor, it is fine for us to be here. So let us erect three tents, one for you, one for Moses, and one for E·liʹjah.” He did not realize what he was saying.

^ par. 23 (Luke 9:34-36) But as he was saying these things, a cloud formed and began to overshadow them. As they entered into the cloud, they became afraid. 35 Then a voice came out of the cloud, saying: “This is my Son, the one who has been chosen. Listen to him.” 36 As the voice spoke, Jesus was found alone. But they kept quiet and did not report to anyone in those days any of the things they saw.

^ par. 24 (2 Pet. 1:16-19) No, it was not by following artfully contrived false stories that we made known to you the power and presence of our Lord Jesus Christ, but rather, we were eyewitnesses of his magnificence. 17 For he received from God the Father honor and glory when words such as these* were conveyed to him by the magnificent glory: “This is my Son, my beloved, whom I myself have approved.” 18 Yes, these words we heard coming from heaven while we were with him in the holy mountain. 19 So we have the prophetic word made more sure, and you are doing well in paying attention to it as to a lamp shining in a dark place (until day dawns and a daystar rises) in your hearts.

Lit., “such a voice.”

^ ***ia chap. 22 He Was Loyal in the Face of Tests***

TO THINK ABOUT . . .

How did Peter’s faith move him to be loyal when many abandoned Jesus?

How did Peter’s faith and loyalty help him to accept correction?

How did the transfiguration vision strengthen Peter’s faith?

In what further ways would you like to imitate Peter’s faith?

^ ***snnw song 149 Grateful for the Ransom***

Song 149

Grateful for the Ransom

Download:

Lyrics Only

Lead Sheet

([Luke 22:20])

Today, Jehovah God,

we stand before your throne,

For you showed the greatest love

that could ever be shown.

You gave the gift of your dear Son,

that we might live.

No greater sacrifice than this

could you ever give.

(CHORUS)

He gave his life to set us free.

His precious blood provides the key.

With all our hearts,

we’ll go on thanking you eternally.

It was a willing sacrifice

that Jesus made.

Out of love, his perfect life

was the price that he paid.

We had no hope until he came

to save mankind.

But now our hope is finding life,

leaving death behind.

(CHORUS)

He gave his life to set us free.

His precious blood provides the key.

With all our hearts,

we’ll go on thanking you eternally.

(See also Heb. 9:13, 14; 1 Pet. 1:18, 19.)

^ (Luke 22:20) Also, he did the same with the cup after they had the evening meal, saying: “This cup means the new covenant by virtue of my blood, which is to be poured out in your behalf.

^ (Heb. 9:13, 14) For if the blood of goats and of bulls and the ashes of a heifer* sprinkled on those who have been defiled sanctifies for the cleansing of the flesh, 14 how much more will the blood of the Christ, who through an everlasting spirit offered himself without blemish to God, cleanse our consciences from dead works so that we may render sacred service to the living God?

Or “young cow.”

^ (1 Pet. 1:18, 19) For you know that it was not with corruptible things, with silver or gold, that you were set free* from your futile way of life handed down to you by your forefathers.* 19 But it was with precious blood, like that of an unblemished and spotless lamb, that of Christ.

Lit., “you were ransomed; you were redeemed.”

Or “by tradition.”

^ (Pss. 106:1-109:31) Praise Jah!* Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; His loyal love endures forever.  2 Who can fully declare Jehovah’s mighty acts Or proclaim all his praiseworthy deeds?  3 Happy are those who act with justice, Who always do what is right.  4 Remember me, O Jehovah, when you show favor* toward your people. Take care of me with your acts of salvation,  5 So that I may enjoy the goodness you show your chosen ones, That I may rejoice along with your nation, That I may proudly praise* you along with your inheritance.  6 We have sinned just as our forefathers did; We have done wrong; we have acted wickedly.  7 Our forefathers in Egypt did not appreciate* your wonderful works. They did not remember your abundant loyal love, But they rebelled at the sea, by the Red Sea.  8 But he saved them for the sake of his name, To make his mightiness known.  9 He rebuked the Red Sea, and it dried up; He led them through its depths as through a desert;* 10 He saved them from the hand of their foe And reclaimed them from the hand of the enemy. 11 The waters covered their adversaries; Not one of them survived.* 12 Then they had faith in his promise; They began to sing his praise. 13 But they quickly forgot what he did; They did not wait for his counsel. 14 They gave way to their selfish desires in the wilderness; They tested God in the desert. 15 He gave them what they requested, But then struck them with disease that made them* waste away. 16 In the camp they grew jealous of Moses And of Aaron, the holy one of Jehovah. 17 The earth then opened up and swallowed Daʹthan And covered those assembled with A·biʹram. 18 A fire blazed among their group; A flame consumed the wicked. 19 They made a calf in Hoʹreb And bowed down to a statue of metal;* 20 They exchanged my glory For the representation of a grass-eating bull. 21 They forgot God their Savior, Who did great things in Egypt, 22 Wonderful works in the land of Ham, Awe-inspiring deeds at the Red Sea. 23 He was about to order their annihilation, But Moses his chosen one interceded with him* To avert his destructive anger. 24 Then they despised the desirable land; They had no faith in his promise. 25 They kept grumbling in their tents; They did not listen to the voice of Jehovah. 26 So he raised his hand in an oath concerning them That he would make them fall in the wilderness; 27 He would make their descendants fall among the nations, And he would scatter them throughout the lands. 28 Then they joined in worship of* Baʹal of Peʹor, And they ate sacrifices offered to the dead.* 29 They provoked Him by their actions, And a scourge broke out among them. 30 But when Phinʹe·has stood up and intervened, The scourge was halted. 31 And it was counted to him as righteousness Through all generations forever. 32 They provoked Him at the waters of Merʹi·bah,* And it went badly for Moses because of them. 33 They embittered his spirit, And he spoke rashly with his lips. 34 They did not annihilate the peoples, As Jehovah had commanded them. 35 But they mingled with the nations And adopted* their ways. 36 They kept serving their idols, And these became a snare to them. 37 They would sacrifice their sons And their daughters to demons. 38 They kept spilling innocent blood, The blood of their own sons and daughters Whom they sacrificed to the idols of Caʹnaan; And the land was polluted with bloodshed. 39 They became unclean by their works; They committed spiritual prostitution by their deeds. 40 So the anger of Jehovah blazed against his people, And he grew to detest his inheritance. 41 He repeatedly handed them over to the nations, So that those who hated them might rule over them. 42 Their enemies oppressed them, And they were subject to their power.* 43 Many times he rescued them, But they would rebel and disobey, And they would be brought low for their error. 44 But he would see their distress And hear their cry for help. 45 For their sake he would remember his covenant, And he would feel pity,* moved by his great* loyal love. 46 He would cause them to be pitied By all who held them captive. 47 Save us, O Jehovah our God, And gather us from the nations So that we may give thanks to your holy name And exult in praising you.* 48 May Jehovah, the God of Israel, be praised Throughout all eternity.* And let all the people say, “Amen!”* Praise Jah!*

107 Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; His loyal love endures forever.  2 Let those reclaimed* by Jehovah say this, Those whom he reclaimed from the hand* of the adversary,  3 Whom he gathered together from the lands, From the east and from the west,* From the north and from the south.  4 They wandered about in the wilderness, in the desert; They did not find a way to a city where they could live.  5 They were hungry and thirsty; They were* faint from exhaustion.  6 They kept crying out to Jehovah in their distress; He rescued them from their plight.  7 He had them walk in the right way To come to a city where they could live.  8 Let people give thanks to Jehovah for his loyal love And for his wonderful works in behalf of the sons of men.  9 For he has satisfied the thirsty* And filled the hungry* with good things. 10 Some were living in deepest darkness, Prisoners in affliction and in irons. 11 For they had rebelled against the word of God; They disrespected the counsel of the Most High. 12 So he humbled their hearts through hardship; They stumbled, and there was no one to help them. 13 They called to Jehovah for help in their distress; He saved them from their plight. 14 He brought them out of deepest darkness, And he tore off their shackles. 15 Let people give thanks to Jehovah for his loyal love And for his wonderful works in behalf of the sons of men. 16 For he has broken down the doors of copper And cut through the bars of iron. 17 They were foolish and suffered affliction On account of their transgressions and their errors. 18 They lost their appetite for* all food; They drew near the gates of death. 19 They would call to Jehovah for help in their distress; He would save them from their plight. 20 He would send his word and heal them And rescue them from the pits they were trapped in. 21 Let people give thanks to Jehovah for his loyal love And for his wonderful works in behalf of the sons of men. 22 Let them offer the sacrifices of thanksgiving And declare his works with a joyful cry. 23 Those who travel on the sea in ships, Who ply their trade over the vast waters, 24 They have seen the works of Jehovah And his wonderful works in the deep; 25 How by his word a windstorm arises, Lifting up the waves of the sea. 26 They rise up to the sky; They plunge down to the depths. Their courage* melts away because of the impending calamity. 27 They reel and stagger like a drunken man, And all their skill proves useless. 28 Then they cry out to Jehovah in their distress, And he rescues them from their plight. 29 He calms the windstorm; The waves of the sea grow quiet. 30 They rejoice when these grow still, And he leads them to their desired harbor. 31 Let people give thanks to Jehovah for his loyal love And for his wonderful works in behalf of the sons of men. 32 Let them exalt him in the congregation of the people, And let them praise him in the council* of the elders. 33 He turns rivers into a desert And springs of water into parched ground, 34 Fruitful land into salty wasteland, Because of the wickedness of those dwelling in it. 35 He turns the desert into reedy pools of water, And dry land into springs of water. 36 He causes the hungry to dwell there, So that they may establish a city where they can live. 37 They sow fields and plant vineyards That yield fruitful crops. 38 He blesses them and they increase greatly; He does not let their cattle diminish. 39 But again they become few and are humiliated Because of oppression, calamity, and grief. 40 He pours out contempt upon nobles And makes them wander in trackless wastelands. 41 But he protects* the poor from oppression And makes their families as numerous as a flock. 42 The upright see this and rejoice; But all the unrighteous shut their mouths. 43 Whoever is wise will observe these things And will carefully consider Jehovah’s acts of loyal love.

A song. A melody of David. 108 My heart is steadfast, O God. I will sing and make music with my whole being.*  2 Do awake, O stringed instrument; you too, O harp. I will awaken the dawn.  3 I will praise you among the peoples, O Jehovah, And I will sing praises* to you among the nations.  4 For your loyal love is great, as high as the heavens, And your faithfulness, up to the skies.  5 Be exalted above the heavens, O God; May your glory be over all the earth.  6 So that your loved ones may be rescued, Save us with your right hand and answer me.  7 God has spoken in his holiness:* “I will exult, I will give out Sheʹchem as an inheritance, And I will measure off the Valley* of Sucʹcoth.  8 Gilʹe·ad belongs to me, as does Ma·nasʹseh, And Eʹphra·im is the helmet* for my head; Judah is my commander’s staff.  9 Moʹab is my washbasin. Over Eʹdom I will throw my sandal. Over Phi·lisʹti·a I will shout in triumph.” 10 Who will bring me to the fortified city? Who will lead me as far as Eʹdom? 11 Is it not you, O God, who have rejected us, Our God, who no longer goes out with our armies? 12 Help us in our distress, For salvation by humans is worthless. 13 By God we will gain power, And he will trample on our adversaries.

To the director. Of David. A melody. 109 O God whom I praise, do not remain silent.  2 For the wicked and the deceitful open their mouths against me. They speak about me with lying tongues;  3 They surround me with hateful words, And they attack me without cause.  4 They resist me in response to my love; But I continue to pray.  5 They repay me with bad for good And hatred for my love.  6 Appoint a wicked man over him; May a resister* stand at his right hand.  7 When he is judged, may he be found guilty;* May even his prayer be counted as a sin.  8 Let his days be few; His office of oversight let someone else take.  9 Let his children* become fatherless, And his wife, a widow. 10 May his children* become wandering beggars, Foraging for food from their ruined homes. 11 May his creditor seize* all that he has, And may strangers plunder his possessions. 12 May no one extend kindness* to him, And may no one show favor to his fatherless children. 13 Let his descendants* be cut off; May their name be erased within a generation. 14 Let the error of his forefathers be remembered by Jehovah, And may the sin of his mother not be erased. 15 May Jehovah always be mindful of what they have done; And may he cut off the memory of them from the earth. 16 For he did not remember to show kindness,* But he kept pursuing the oppressed, poor, and brokenhearted man To put him to death. 17 He loved to pronounce a curse, so that is what came upon him; He had no desire to bless, so he received no blessing. 18 He was clothed with curses as his garment. And they were poured into his body like water, Into his bones like oil. 19 May his curses be like the clothing in which he wraps himself And like a belt he always wears. 20 This is the payment from Jehovah for the one who resists me And for those who speak evil things against me.* 21 But you, Jehovah the Sovereign Lord, Act in my behalf for the sake of your name. Rescue me, because your loyal love is good. 22 For I am helpless and poor, And my heart has been pierced within me. 23 I am passing away like a fading shadow; I have been shaken off like a locust. 24 My knees give way from fasting; My body is thin, and I am wasting away.* 25 I have become the object of their taunts. When they see me, they shake their heads. 26 Help me, O Jehovah my God; Save me by your loyal love. 27 May they know that this is by your hand; That you, O Jehovah, have done it. 28 Let them pronounce a curse, but may you give a blessing. When they rise up against me, may they be put to shame, But let your servant rejoice. 29 Let those who resist me be clothed with humiliation; May they be wrapped in their shame as in a robe.* 30 My mouth will fervently praise Jehovah; I will praise him in front of many people. 31 For he will stand at the right hand of the poor To save him from those who condemn him.*

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “goodwill.”

Or “may boast about.”

Or “grasp the meaning of.”

Or “wilderness.”

Or “was left.”

Or “their soul.”

Or “molten statue.”

Lit., “stood in the breach before him.”

Or “attached themselves to.”

That is, sacrifices offered either to dead people or to lifeless gods.

Meaning “Quarreling.”

Or “learned.”

Lit., “hand.”

Or “feel regret.”

Or “abundant.”

Or “exult in your praise.”

Or “From eternity to eternity.”

Or “So be it!”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “repurchased.”

Or “power.”

Or “From sunrise and from sunset.”

Or “Their soul was.”

Or “the parched soul.”

Or “the hungry soul.”

Or “Their soul detested.”

Or “soul.”

Lit., “seat.”

Or “puts on high,” that is, out of reach.

Lit., “even my glory.”

Or “make music.”

Or possibly, “in his holy place.”

Or “Low Plain.”

Lit., “stronghold.”

Or “an accuser.”

Or “wicked.”

Lit., “sons.”

Lit., “sons.”

Or “May usurers lay out traps for.”

Or “loyal love.”

Or “posterity.”

Or “loyal love.”

Or “my soul.”

Lit., “My flesh has grown lean, without fatness (oil).”

Or “sleeveless coat.”

Or “his soul.”

^ (Pss. 110:0-118:29) Of David. A melody. 110 Jehovah declared to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand Until I place your enemies as a stool for your feet.”  2 Jehovah will extend the scepter of your power out of Zion, saying: “Go subduing in the midst of your enemies.”  3 Your people will offer themselves willingly on the day of your military force.* In splendid holiness, from the womb of the dawn, You have your company of young men just like dewdrops.  4 Jehovah has sworn an oath, and he will not change his mind:* “You are a priest forever In the manner of Mel·chizʹe·dek!”  5 Jehovah will be at your right hand; He will crush kings on the day of his anger.  6 He will execute judgment against* the nations; He will fill the land with dead bodies. He will crush the leader* of a vast land.*  7 He* will drink from the stream along the road. Therefore, he will hold his head high.

111 Praise Jah!* I will praise Jehovah with all my heart In the assembled group of upright ones and in the congregation.  2 The works of Jehovah are great; They are studied by all those finding pleasure in them.  3 His activity is glorious and splendid, And his righteousness endures forever.  4 He causes his wonderful works to be remembered. Jehovah is compassionate* and merciful.  5 Food he gives to those fearing him. He remembers his covenant forever.  6 He has revealed to his people his powerful works By giving them the inheritance of the nations.  7 The works of his hands are truth and justice; Trustworthy are all his orders.  8 They are always reliable,* now and forever; They are made in truth and righteousness.  9 He has given redemption to his people. He commanded that his covenant should last forever. His name is holy and awe-inspiring. 10 The fear of Jehovah is the beginning of wisdom. All those observing his orders* show good insight. His praise endures forever.

112 Praise Jah!* Happy is the man who fears Jehovah, Who takes great pleasure in his commandments.  2 His descendants will be mighty in the earth, And the generation of the upright will be blessed.  3 Wealth and riches are in his house, And his righteousness continues forever.  4 To the upright he shines like a light in the darkness. He is compassionate* and merciful and righteous.  5 It goes well for the man who generously* lends. He conducts his affairs with justice.  6 He will never be shaken. The righteous will be remembered forever.  7 He will not fear bad news. His heart is steadfast, trusting in Jehovah.  8 His heart is unshakable;* he is not afraid; In the end he will look in triumph on his adversaries.  9 He has distributed widely;* he has given to the poor. His righteousness continues forever. His own strength* will be exalted with glory. 10 The wicked one will see and be upset. He will grind his teeth and melt away. The desires of the wicked will perish.

113 Praise Jah!* Offer praise, you servants of Jehovah, Praise the name of Jehovah.  2 May Jehovah’s name be praised From now on and forever.  3 From the rising of the sun to its setting, Let Jehovah’s name be praised.  4 Jehovah is high above all the nations; His glory is above the heavens.  5 Who is like Jehovah our God, The one who dwells* on high?  6 He stoops down to look on heaven and earth,  7 Raising the lowly from the dust. He lifts up the poor from the ash heap*  8 In order to make him sit with nobles, With the nobles of his people.  9 He gives the barren woman a home As a happy mother with children.* Praise Jah!*

114 When Israel went out of Egypt, The house of Jacob from a people speaking a foreign language,  2 Judah became his sanctuary,* Israel, his dominion.  3 The sea saw it and fled; The Jordan turned back.  4 The mountains skipped about like rams, The hills, like lambs.  5 What made you flee, O sea? Why, O Jordan, did you turn back?  6 Why did you skip about like rams, O mountains, Like lambs, O hills?  7 Tremble, O earth, because of the Lord, Because of the God of Jacob,  8 Who turns the rock into a reedy pool of water, The flinty rock into springs of water.

115 Not to us, O Jehovah, not to us,* But to your name give glory Because of your loyal love and your faithfulness.  2 Why should the nations say: “Where is their God?”  3 Our God is in the heavens; He does whatever he pleases.  4 Their idols are silver and gold, The work of human hands.  5 A mouth they have, but they cannot speak; Eyes, but they cannot see;  6 Ears they have, but they cannot hear; A nose, but they cannot smell;  7 Hands they have, but they cannot feel; Feet, but they cannot walk; They make no sound with their throat.  8 The people who make them will become just like them, As will all those who trust in them.  9 O Israel, trust in Jehovah —He is their help and their shield. 10 O house of Aaron, trust in Jehovah —He is their help and their shield. 11 You who fear Jehovah, trust in Jehovah —He is their help and their shield. 12 Jehovah remembers us and will bless; He will bless the house of Israel; He will bless the house of Aaron. 13 He will bless those who fear Jehovah, The small as well as the great. 14 Jehovah will give you an increase, To you and your children.* 15 May you be blessed by Jehovah, The Maker of heaven and earth. 16 As for the heavens, they belong to Jehovah, But the earth he has given to the sons of men. 17 The dead do not praise Jah; Nor do any who go down into the silence of death.* 18 But we will praise Jah From now on and forever. Praise Jah!*

116 I love Jehovah Because he hears* my voice, my pleas for help.  2 For he inclines his ear* to me, And I will call on him as long as I live.*  3 The ropes of death encircled me; The Grave had me in its grip.* I was overcome by distress and grief.  4 But I called on the name of Jehovah: “O Jehovah, rescue me!”*  5 Jehovah is compassionate* and righteous; Our God is merciful.  6 Jehovah is guarding the inexperienced. I was brought low, and he saved me.  7 Let my soul* rest once again, For Jehovah has dealt kindly with me.  8 You have rescued me* from death, My eye from tears, my foot from stumbling.  9 I will walk before Jehovah in the land of the living. 10 I had faith, for I spoke; I was greatly afflicted. 11 As for me, I panicked and said: “Every man is a liar.” 12 With what will I repay Jehovah For all the good he has done for me? 13 I will take up the cup of salvation,* And I will call on the name of Jehovah. 14 I will pay my vows to Jehovah In the presence of all his people. 15 Costly* in the eyes of Jehovah Is the death of his loyal ones. 16 I beg you, O Jehovah, For I am your servant. I am your servant, the son of your slave girl. You have freed me from my bonds. 17 I will offer to you the sacrifice of thanksgiving; I will call on the name of Jehovah. 18 I will pay my vows to Jehovah In the presence of all his people, 19 In the courtyards of the house of Jehovah, In your midst, O Jerusalem. Praise Jah!*

117 Praise Jehovah, all you nations; Glorify him, all you peoples.*  2 For his loyal love toward us is great; The faithfulness of Jehovah endures forever. Praise Jah!*

118 Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; His loyal love endures forever.  2 Let Israel now say: “His loyal love endures forever.”  3 Let those of the house of Aaron now say: “His loyal love endures forever.”  4 Let those fearing Jehovah now say: “His loyal love endures forever.”  5 I called on Jah* in my distress; Jah answered and brought me into a place of safety.*  6 Jehovah is on my side; I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?  7 Jehovah is on my side as my helper;* I will look in triumph on those who hate me.  8 It is better to take refuge in Jehovah Than to trust in humans.  9 It is better to take refuge in Jehovah Than to trust in princes. 10 All the nations surrounded me, But in the name of Jehovah, I warded them off. 11 They surrounded me, yes, I was completely surrounded, But in the name of Jehovah, I warded them off. 12 They surrounded me like bees, But they were extinguished as quickly as a fire among thorns. In the name of Jehovah, I warded them off. 13 I was pushed hard* to make me fall, But Jehovah helped me. 14 Jah is my shelter and my strength, And he has become my salvation. 15 The sound of rejoicing and salvation* Is in the tents of the righteous. The right hand of Jehovah is demonstrating its power. 16 The right hand of Jehovah is exalting itself; The right hand of Jehovah is demonstrating its power. 17 I will not die, no, I will live, In order to declare the works of Jah. 18 Jah disciplined me severely, But he did not hand me over to death. 19 Open to me the gates of righteousness; I will enter them and praise Jah. 20 This is the gate of Jehovah. The righteous will enter through it. 21 I will praise you, for you answered me And you became my salvation. 22 The stone that the builders rejected Has become the chief cornerstone.* 23 This has come from Jehovah; It is wonderful in our eyes. 24 This is the day that Jehovah has made; We will be joyful and rejoice in it. 25 Jehovah, save us, please, we beg! Jehovah, grant us victory, please! 26 Blessed is the one who comes in the name of Jehovah; We bless you from the house of Jehovah. 27 Jehovah is God; He gives us light. Join in the festival procession with branches in hand, Up to the horns of the altar. 28 You are my God, and I will praise you; My God, I will exalt you. 29 Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; His loyal love endures forever.

Or “on the day your army mobilizes.”

Or “he will feel no regret.”

Or “among.”

Lit., “head.”

Or “of the entire earth.”

Referring to “my Lord” in vs. 1.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “gracious.”

Or “well-founded.”

Lit., “them.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “gracious.”

Or “graciously.”

Or “resolute; steady.”

Or “generously.”

Lit., “horn.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “sits enthroned.”

Or possibly, “garbage dump.”

Lit., “sons.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “holy place.”

Or “To us belongs nothing, O Jehovah, to us belongs nothing.”

Lit., “sons.”

Lit., “into silence.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or possibly, “I love because Jehovah hears.”

Or “bends down to listen.”

Lit., “in my days.”

Lit., “The distresses of Sheol found me.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “gracious.”

See Glossary.

Or “my soul.”

Or “grand salvation.”

Lit., “Precious.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “clans.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

“Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “a roomy place.”

Or possibly, “along with those helping me.”

Or possibly, “You pushed me hard.”

Or “victory.”

Lit., “the head of the corner.”

^ (Pss. 110:1-111:10) Jehovah declared to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand Until I place your enemies as a stool for your feet.”  2 Jehovah will extend the scepter of your power out of Zion, saying: “Go subduing in the midst of your enemies.”  3 Your people will offer themselves willingly on the day of your military force.* In splendid holiness, from the womb of the dawn, You have your company of young men just like dewdrops.  4 Jehovah has sworn an oath, and he will not change his mind:* “You are a priest forever In the manner of Mel·chizʹe·dek!”  5 Jehovah will be at your right hand; He will crush kings on the day of his anger.  6 He will execute judgment against* the nations; He will fill the land with dead bodies. He will crush the leader* of a vast land.*  7 He* will drink from the stream along the road. Therefore, he will hold his head high.

111 Praise Jah!* I will praise Jehovah with all my heart In the assembled group of upright ones and in the congregation.  2 The works of Jehovah are great; They are studied by all those finding pleasure in them.  3 His activity is glorious and splendid, And his righteousness endures forever.  4 He causes his wonderful works to be remembered. Jehovah is compassionate* and merciful.  5 Food he gives to those fearing him. He remembers his covenant forever.  6 He has revealed to his people his powerful works By giving them the inheritance of the nations.  7 The works of his hands are truth and justice; Trustworthy are all his orders.  8 They are always reliable,* now and forever; They are made in truth and righteousness.  9 He has given redemption to his people. He commanded that his covenant should last forever. His name is holy and awe-inspiring. 10 The fear of Jehovah is the beginning of wisdom. All those observing his orders* show good insight. His praise endures forever.

Or “on the day your army mobilizes.”

Or “he will feel no regret.”

Or “among.”

Lit., “head.”

Or “of the entire earth.”

Referring to “my Lord” in vs. 1.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “gracious.”

Or “well-founded.”

Lit., “them.”

^ ***sn song 61 What Sort of Person I Should Be***

Song 61

What Sort of Person I Should Be

([2 Peter 3:11])

1. How can I repay you, what gift can I give

To thank you, Jehovah, for the life that I live?

I look in my heart with your Word as my mirror;

The person I see, may you help me see clearer.

My life I have promised in service to you,

But not from mere duty will I do what I do.

Whole-souled and wholehearted I serve you by choice;

May I be one more who makes you rejoice.

2. Help me to examine, and help me to see

Just what sort of person you desire me to be.

Those loyal to you, you will loyally treasure;

May I be among those who bring your heart pleasure.

(See also [Ps. 18:25;][116:12;][119:37;][Prov. 11:20].)

^ (2 Pet. 3:11) Since all these things are to be dissolved in this way, consider what sort of people you ought to be in holy acts of conduct and deeds of godly devotion,

^ (Ps. 18:25) With someone loyal you act in loyalty; With the blameless man you deal blamelessly;

^ (Ps. 116:12) With what will I repay Jehovah For all the good he has done for me?

^ (Ps. 119:37) Turn my eyes away from looking at what is worthless; Preserve me alive in your way.

^ (Prov. 11:20) Those crooked at heart are detestable to Jehovah, But those whose way is blameless bring pleasure to him.

^ ***w87 3/15 p. 24 Happy God, Happy People!***

◆ [116:3]—What are “the ropes of death”?

It seemed as if death had so tightly bound the psalmist with unbreakable ropes that escape was impossible. Ropes tied tightly about limbs produce sharp pains, or pangs, and the Greek Septuagint version renders the Hebrew word for “ropes” as “pangs.” Hence, when Jesus Christ died, he was in the paralyzing grip, or pangs, of death. When Jehovah resurrected Jesus, therefore, He was “loosing the pangs of death.”—[Acts 2:24].

^ (Ps. 116:3) The ropes of death encircled me; The Grave had me in its grip.* I was overcome by distress and grief.

Lit., “The distresses of Sheol found me.”

^ (Acts 2:24) But God resurrected him by releasing him from the pangs* of death, because it was not possible for him to be held fast by it.

Or possibly, “cords.”

^ ***w09 7/15 p. 29 Accept Gratefully—Give Wholeheartedly***

The psalmist wondered: “What shall I repay to Jehovah for all his benefits to me?” ([Ps. 116:12]) What benefits had he received? Jehovah had sustained him during a period of “distress and grief.” Moreover, Jehovah had “rescued [his] soul from death.” Now he wanted to “repay” Jehovah somehow. What could the psalmist do? He said: “My vows I shall pay to Jehovah.” (Ps. 116:3, 4,[8,][10-14]) He resolved to keep all the solemn promises that he had made to Jehovah and to fulfill all his obligations to him.

You can do the same. How? By following a life course that at all times conforms to God’s laws and principles. Hence, make sure that your worship of Jehovah remains the most important thing in your life and that you let God’s spirit guide you in everything you do. ([Eccl. 12:13;] Gal. 5:16-18) In reality, of course, you can never fully repay Jehovah for all he has done for you. Still, it does ‘make Jehovah’s heart rejoice’ to see that you are wholeheartedly giving of yourself in his service. ([Prov. 27:11]) What a wonderful privilege it is to give Jehovah pleasure in this way!

^ (Ps. 116:12) With what will I repay Jehovah For all the good he has done for me?

^ (Ps. 116:3, 4) The ropes of death encircled me; The Grave had me in its grip.* I was overcome by distress and grief.  4 But I called on the name of Jehovah: “O Jehovah, rescue me!”*

Lit., “The distresses of Sheol found me.”

Or “my soul.”

^ (Ps. 116:8) You have rescued me* from death, My eye from tears, my foot from stumbling.

Or “my soul.”

^ (Ps. 116:10-14) I had faith, for I spoke; I was greatly afflicted. 11 As for me, I panicked and said: “Every man is a liar.” 12 With what will I repay Jehovah For all the good he has done for me? 13 I will take up the cup of salvation,* And I will call on the name of Jehovah. 14 I will pay my vows to Jehovah In the presence of all his people.

Or “grand salvation.”

^ (Eccl. 12:13) The conclusion of the matter, everything having been heard, is: Fear the true God and keep his commandments, for this is the whole obligation of man.

^ (Gal. 5:16-18) But I say, Keep walking by spirit and you will carry out no fleshly desire at all. 17 For the flesh is against the spirit in its desire, and the spirit against the flesh; these are opposed to each other, so that you do not do the very things you want to do. 18 Furthermore, if you are being led by spirit, you are not under law.

^ (Prov. 27:11) Be wise, my son, and make my heart rejoice, So that I can make a reply to him who taunts me.

^ ***w98 12/1 p. 24 Standing at the Threshold of Greater Activity***

Talks by three members of the Gilead faculty followed. Karl Adams spoke first, on the subject “What Will You Repay to Jehovah?” His talk was based on the 116th Psalm, which Jesus may have sung on the night before his death. (Matthew 26:30, footnote) What went through Jesus’ mind as he sang the words: “What shall I repay to Jehovah for all his benefits to me”? ([Psalm 116:12]) He may have been reflecting on the perfect body that Jehovah had prepared for him. ([Hebrews 10:5]) The following day, he would offer that body in sacrifice, proving the depth of his love. The students of the 105th class had tasted Jehovah’s goodness for the past five months. Now they would show their love for God by working hard in their missionary assignments.

^ (Matt. 26:30) Finally, after singing praises,* they went out to the Mount of Olives.

Or “hymns; psalms.”

^ (Ps. 116:12) With what will I repay Jehovah For all the good he has done for me?

^ (Heb. 10:5) So when he comes into the world, he says: “‘Sacrifice and offering you did not want, but you prepared a body for me.

^ ***w10 4/15 p. 27 Are You Fully Following the Christ?***

What Will Help You to Keep Following the Christ?

▪ Read God’s Word daily, and meditate on what you read.—[Ps. 1:1-3;][1 Tim. 4:15].

▪ Pray often for the support and guidance of God’s spirit.—[Zech. 4:6;][Luke 11:9,][13].

▪ Associate with those who demonstrate heartfelt zeal for the ministry.—[Prov. 13:20;] Heb. 10:24, 25.

▪ Appreciate the urgency of the times in which we are living.—Eph. 5:15, 16.

▪ Be conscious of the serious consequences of ‘begging off.’—[Luke 9:59-62].

▪ Reflect regularly on your dedication vow and the abundant blessings that result from serving Jehovah and following the Christ wholeheartedly.—Ps. 116:12-14;[133:3;][Prov. 10:22].

^ (Ps. 1:1-3) Happy is the man who does not walk according to the advice of the wicked And does not stand on the path of sinners And does not sit in the seat of scoffers.  2 But his delight is in the law of Jehovah, And he reads His law in an undertone* day and night.  3 He will be like a tree planted by streams of water, A tree that produces fruit in its season, The foliage of which does not wither. And everything he does will succeed.

Or “he meditates on His law.”

^ (1 Tim. 4:15) Ponder over* these things; be absorbed in them, so that your advancement may be plainly seen by all people.

Or “Meditate on.”

^ (Zech. 4:6) He then said to me: “This is the word of Jehovah to Ze·rubʹba·bel: ‘“Not by a military force, nor by power, but by my spirit,” says Jehovah of armies.

^ (Luke 11:9) So I say to you, keep on asking, and it will be given you; keep on seeking, and you will find; keep on knocking, and it will be opened to you.

^ (Luke 11:13) Therefore, if you, although being wicked, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more so will the Father in heaven give holy spirit to those asking him!”

^ (Prov. 13:20) The one walking with the wise will become wise, But the one who has dealings with the stupid will fare badly.

^ (Heb. 10:24, 25) And let us consider* one another so as to incite* to love and fine works, 25 not forsaking our meeting together, as some have the custom, but encouraging one another, and all the more so as you see the day drawing near.

Or “be concerned about; pay attention to.”

Or “motivate; stir up.”

^ (Eph. 5:15, 16) So keep strict watch that how you walk is not as unwise but as wise persons, 16 making the best use of your time,* because the days are wicked.

Lit., “buying out the appointed time.”

^ (Luke 9:59-62) Then he said to another: “Be my follower.” The man said: “Lord, permit me first to go and bury my father.” 60 But he said to him: “Let the dead bury their dead, but you go and declare abroad the Kingdom of God.” 61 And still another said: “I will follow you, Lord, but first permit me to say good-bye to those in my household.” 62 Jesus said to him: “No man who has put his hand to a plow and looks at the things behind is well-suited for the Kingdom of God.”

^ (Ps. 116:12-14) With what will I repay Jehovah For all the good he has done for me? 13 I will take up the cup of salvation,* And I will call on the name of Jehovah. 14 I will pay my vows to Jehovah In the presence of all his people.

Or “grand salvation.”

^ (Ps. 133:3) It is like the dew of Herʹmon That descends on the mountains of Zion. That is where Jehovah decreed his blessing —Life everlasting.

^ (Prov. 10:22) It is the blessing of Jehovah that makes one rich, And He adds no pain* with it.

Or “sorrow; hardship.”

^ ***w14 10/15 p. 11 Have Unshakable Faith in the Kingdom***

A COVENANT FILLS THE NEED FOR A PRIESTLY FUNCTION

15-17. According to the covenant for a priest like Melchizedek, in what additional capacity would the offspring serve, and why?

15 While the Abrahamic covenant and the Davidic covenant make it certain that the offspring of the woman would have a kingly function, that role alone would not suffice to bring blessings to people of all nations. For them to be truly blessed, they would have to be freed from their sinful state and brought into Jehovah’s universal family. To accomplish this requires that the offspring also serve in a priestly capacity. The wise Creator provided for this by means of another legal arrangement, the covenant for a priest like Melchizedek.

16 Jehovah revealed through King David that He would make a personal covenant with Jesus with a twofold objective: to have him “sit at [God’s] right hand” until he subdues his enemies and to be “a priest forever in the manner of Melchizedek.” (Read Psalm 110:1, 2, 4.) Why “in the manner of Melchizedek”? Because long before any descendants of Abraham inherited the Promised Land, Melchizedek, the king of Salem, served as “priest of the Most High God.” ([Heb. 7:1-3]) He was directly appointed by Jehovah to do so. He is the only one mentioned in the Hebrew Scriptures who served as both a king and a priest. Moreover, since he was without a recorded predecessor or successor, he can be called “a priest for all time,” or forever.

17 Jesus is directly appointed to be a priest by means of this personal covenant that Jehovah made with him, and he will remain “a priest forever in the manner of Melchizedek.” ([Heb. 5:4-6]) This clearly shows that Jehovah has legally bound himself to use the Messianic Kingdom to accomplish his original purpose concerning humans on earth.

^ par. 16 (Ps. 110:1, 2) Jehovah declared to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand Until I place your enemies as a stool for your feet.”  2 Jehovah will extend the scepter of your power out of Zion, saying: “Go subduing in the midst of your enemies.”

^ par. 16 (Ps. 110:4) Jehovah has sworn an oath, and he will not change his mind:* “You are a priest forever In the manner of Mel·chizʹe·dek!”

Or “he will feel no regret.”

^ par. 16 (Heb. 7:1-3) For this Mel·chizʹe·dek, king of Saʹlem, priest of the Most High God, met Abraham returning from the slaughter of the kings and blessed him, 2 and Abraham gave* him a tenth of everything. First, his name is translated “King of Righteousness,” and then also king of Saʹlem, that is, “King of Peace.” 3 In being fatherless, motherless, without genealogy, having neither a beginning of days nor an end of life, but being made like the Son of God, he remains a priest for all time.*

Lit., “apportioned.”

Or “perpetually.”

^ par. 17 (Heb. 5:4-6) A man does not take this honor of his own accord, but he receives it only when he is called by God, just as Aaron was. 5 So, too, the Christ did not glorify himself by becoming a high priest, but was glorified by the One who said to him: “You are my son; today I have become your father.” 6 As he also says in another place, “You are a priest forever in the manner of Mel·chizʹe·dek.”

^ ***w06 9/1 p. 14 par. 1 Highlights From Book Five of Psalms***

110:4—To what has Jehovah ‘sworn without feeling regret’? This oath is the covenant that Jehovah made with Jesus Christ to serve as King and High Priest.—[Luke 22:29].

^ par. 1 (Ps. 110:4) Jehovah has sworn an oath, and he will not change his mind:* “You are a priest forever In the manner of Mel·chizʹe·dek!”

Or “he will feel no regret.”

^ par. 1 (Luke 22:29) and I make a covenant with you, just as my Father has made a covenant with me, for a kingdom,

^ ***w12 5/15 p. 22 Questions From Readers***

When delivering a memorial talk for a Christian, it is not fitting to apply [Psalm 116:15] to the deceased person, even though he died as a loyal servant of Jehovah. Why? Because the psalmist’s statement has a broader significance. It means that God counts the death of the entire group of his loyal ones too costly for him to let it take place.—See [Psalm 72:14;][116:8].

^ (Ps. 116:15) Costly* in the eyes of Jehovah Is the death of his loyal ones.

Lit., “Precious.”

^ (Ps. 72:14) From oppression and from violence he will rescue them,* And their blood will be precious in his eyes.

Or “redeem their souls.”

^ (Ps. 116:8) You have rescued me* from death, My eye from tears, my foot from stumbling.

Or “my soul.”

^ ***ll p. 16 Who Was Jesus?***

Part 7

Who Was Jesus?

If we want to please Jehovah, we must listen to another important person. Long before creating Adam, Jehovah created a mighty spirit person in the heavens.

In time, Jehovah sent this one to be born in Bethlehem to a virgin named Mary. The child was given the name Jesus.—[John 6:38].

As a man on earth, Jesus perfectly reflected God’s qualities. He was kind, loving, and approachable. Fearlessly, he taught others the truth about Jehovah.

Jehovah sent Jesus to earth. 1 John 4:9

^ (John 6:38) for I have come down from heaven to do, not my own will, but the will of him who sent me.

^ (1 John 4:9) By this the love of God was revealed in our case, that God sent his only-begotten Son into the world so that we might gain life through him.

^ ***ll p. 17 Who Was Jesus?***

Jesus also healed the sick and raised to life some who had died.

The religious leaders hated Jesus because he exposed their false teachings and their evil ways.

The religious leaders persuaded the Romans to beat Jesus and to kill him.

Jesus did good but was hated. 1 Peter 2:21-24

Why is it important to know about Jesus?—[John 17:3].

What did Jesus do in heaven before he came to earth?—Colossians 1:15-17.

^ (1 Pet. 2:21-24) In fact, to this course you were called, because even Christ suffered for you, leaving a model for you to follow his steps closely. 22 He committed no sin, nor was deception found in his mouth. 23 When he was being insulted,* he did not insult* in return. When he was suffering, he did not threaten, but he entrusted himself to the One who judges righteously. 24 He himself bore our sins in his own body on the stake,* so that we might die to* sins and live to righteousness. And “by his wounds you were healed.”

Or “reviled.”

Or “revile.”

Or “tree.”

Or “be finished with.”

^ (John 17:3) This means everlasting life, their coming to know you,* the only true God, and the one whom you sent, Jesus Christ.

Or “their taking in knowledge of you.”

^ (Col. 1:15-17) He is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn of all creation; 16 because by means of him all other things were created in the heavens and on the earth, the things visible and the things invisible, whether they are thrones or lordships or governments or authorities. All other things have been created through him and for him. 17 Also, he is before all other things, and by means of him all other things were made to exist,

^ ***bh pp. 179-181 Baptism and Your Relationship With God***

17. Why might some hold back from making a dedication to God?

17 Some hold back from making a dedication to Jehovah because they are somewhat afraid of taking such a serious step. They may fear being accountable to God as a dedicated Christian. Being afraid that they may fail and disappoint Jehovah, they think that it is best not to make a dedication to him.

18. What can move you to make a dedication to Jehovah?

18 As you learn to love Jehovah, you will be moved to make a dedication to him and to do your best to live up to it. (Ecclesiastes 5:4) After making a dedication, surely you will want to “walk worthily of Jehovah in order to please him fully.” (Colossians 1:10) Because of your love for God, you will not think it is too hard to do his will. No doubt you will agree with the apostle John, who wrote: “This is what the love of God means, that we observe his commandments; and yet his commandments are not burdensome.”—[1 John 5:3].

19. Why do you not need to fear making a dedication to God?

19 You do not have to be perfect to make a dedication to God. Jehovah knows your limitations and never expects you to do more than you are able to do. ([Psalm 103:14]) He wants you to succeed and will support and help you. (Read Isaiah 41:10.) You can be sure that if you trust in Jehovah with all your heart, “he will make your paths straight.”—Proverbs 3:5, 6.

^ par. 18 (Eccl. 5:4) Whenever you make a vow to God, do not delay to pay it, for he finds no pleasure in the stupid ones. What you vow, pay.

^ par. 18 (Col. 1:10) so as to walk worthily of Jehovah* in order to please him fully as you go on bearing fruit in every good work and increasing in the accurate knowledge of God;

See App. A5.

^ par. 18 (1 John 5:3) For this is what the love of God means, that we observe his commandments; and yet his commandments are not burdensome,

^ par. 19 (Ps. 103:14) For he well knows how we are formed, Remembering that we are dust.

^ par. 19 (Isa. 41:10) Do not be afraid, for I am with you. Do not be anxious, for I am your God. I will fortify you, yes, I will help you, I will really hold on to you with my right hand of righteousness.’

^ par. 19 (Prov. 3:5, 6) Trust in Jehovah with all your heart, And do not rely* on your own understanding.  6 In all your ways take notice of him, And he will make your paths straight.

Lit., “lean.”

^ ***sn song 82 Imitate Christ’s Mildness***

Song 82

Imitate Christ’s Mildness

(Matthew 11:28-30)

1. The greatest of men was our Lord Jesus Christ;

By pride or ambition he was not enticed.

God’s purpose gave him the most prominent part;

Yet, always he proved himself lowly in heart.

2. All you who are toiling with burdensome cares,

He bids you come under the yoke that he bears.

Refreshment you’ll find as the Kingdom you seek.

Our Lord is mild-tempered; he favors the meek.

3. ‘All you are just brothers,’ our Lord Jesus said.

So never seek greatness; serve others instead.

The mild and the meek to our God have great worth;

He promises they will inherit the earth.

(See also [Matt. 5:5;][23:8;][Prov. 3:34;][Rom. 12:16].)

^ (Matt. 11:28-30) Come to me, all you who are toiling and loaded down, and I will refresh you. 29 Take my yoke upon you and learn from me, for I am mild-tempered and lowly in heart, and you will find refreshment for yourselves.* 30 For my yoke is kindly,* and my load is light.”

Or “your souls.”

Or “easy to bear.”

^ (Matt. 5:5) “Happy are the mild-tempered,* since they will inherit the earth.

Or “meek.”

^ (Matt. 23:8) But you, do not you be called Rabbi, for one is your Teacher, and all of you are brothers.

^ (Prov. 3:34) For he mocks those who ridicule, But he shows favor to the meek.

^ (Rom. 12:16) Have the same attitude toward others as toward yourselves; do not set your mind on lofty things,* but be led along with the lowly things. Do not become wise in your own eyes.

Or “cultivate lofty ideas.”

^ ***ia pp. 196-200 He Learned Forgiveness From the Master***

1. What may have been the worst moment of Peter’s life?

PETER would never forget that terrible moment when their eyes met. Did he see in Jesus’ gaze some hint of disappointment or reproach? We cannot venture so far; the inspired record says only that “the Lord turned and looked upon Peter.” ([Luke 22:61]) But in that one glance, Peter saw the depth of his own failure. He realized that he had just done the very thing that Jesus had foretold, the one thing that Peter had insisted he would never do—he had disowned his beloved Master. It was a low point for Peter, perhaps the worst moment of the worst day of his life.

2. Peter needed to learn what lesson, and how may we benefit from his story?

2 All was not lost, though. Because Peter was a man of great faith, he still had an opportunity to recover from his mistakes and to learn one of Jesus’ greatest lessons. It had to do with forgiveness. Each of us needs to learn the same lesson, so let us follow Peter on this difficult journey.

A Man With Much to Learn

3, 4. (a) What question did Peter ask Jesus, and what might Peter have thought? (b) How did Jesus show that Peter had been influenced by the spirit prevalent in those days?

3 About six months earlier in his hometown of Capernaum, Peter approached Jesus and asked: “Lord, how many times is my brother to sin against me and am I to forgive him? Up to seven times?” Peter likely thought that he was being generous. After all, the religious leaders of the day taught that one had to forgive only three times! Jesus replied: “Not, Up to seven times, but, Up to seventy-seven times.”—Matt. 18:21, 22.

4 Was Jesus suggesting that Peter keep a running tally of a transgressor’s actions? No; rather, by turning Peter’s 7 into a 77, he was saying that love does not allow us to set an arbitrary limit on forgiveness. (1 Cor. 13:4, 5) Jesus showed that Peter had been influenced by a hard-hearted and unforgiving spirit that was prevalent in those days, one that meted out forgiveness as if by an accountant’s ledger. However, divine forgiveness is expansive, generous.—Read 1 John 1:7-9.

5. When might we learn the most about forgiveness?

5 Peter did not argue with Jesus. But did Jesus’ lesson really reach his heart? Sometimes we learn the most about forgiveness when we realize how desperately we need it ourselves. So let us return to the events leading up to Jesus’ death. In those difficult hours, Peter gave his Master many things to forgive.

A Growing Need for Forgiveness

6. How did Peter respond as Jesus tried to teach the apostles about humility, yet how did Jesus treat him?

6 It was a momentous evening—the final night of Jesus’ earthly life. Jesus still had much to teach his apostles—for instance, about humility. Jesus set an example by humbly washing their feet, a job normally assigned to the lowliest of servants. At first, Peter questioned Jesus’ actions. Then he refused the service. Next he insisted that Jesus wash not only his feet but also his hands and head! Jesus did not lose his patience but calmly explained the importance and meaning of what he was doing.—[John 13:1-17].

7, 8. (a) In what ways did Peter further test Jesus’ patience? (b) How did Jesus continue to show a kind, forgiving spirit?

7 Shortly thereafter, Peter further tested Jesus’ patience. The apostles fell to bickering over who of them was the greatest, and Peter surely played a part in that shameful display of human pride. Nonetheless, Jesus corrected them kindly and even commended them for what they had done well; they had shown faithfulness in sticking to their Master. He foretold, however, that they would all abandon him. Peter countered that he would stick with Jesus even in the face of death. Jesus prophesied that, on the contrary, Peter would deny his Master three times that very night before a cock crowed twice. Peter then not only contradicted Jesus but boasted that he would prove more faithful than all the other apostles!—Matt. 26:31-35; Mark 14:27-31; Luke 22:24-28; John 13:36-38.

8 Was Jesus close to losing his patience with Peter? In fact, throughout this difficult time, Jesus kept looking for the good in his imperfect apostles. He knew that Peter would fail him, yet He said: “I have made supplication for you that your faith may not give out; and you, when once you have returned, strengthen your brothers.” ([Luke 22:32]) Jesus thus expressed confidence in Peter’s spiritual recovery and his return to faithful service. What a kind, forgiving spirit!

9, 10. (a) In the garden of Gethsemane, what correction did Peter need? (b) Peter’s case may remind us of what?

9 Later, in the garden of Gethsemane, Peter needed correction more than once. Jesus asked him, as well as James and John, to keep on the watch while He prayed. Jesus was in emotional agony and in need of support, but Peter and the others fell asleep repeatedly. Jesus made this empathetic and forgiving observation: “The spirit, of course, is eager, but the flesh is weak.”—Mark 14:32-41.

10 Before long, a mob arrived, bearing torches and armed with swords and clubs. Here was a time to act with caution and discretion. Yet, Peter rashly leaped into action, swinging a sword at the head of Malchus, a slave of the high priest, and lopping off one of the man’s ears. Jesus calmly corrected Peter, healed the wound, and explained a principle of nonviolence that guides His followers to this day. (Matt. 26:47-55; Luke 22:47-51; John 18:10, 11) Peter had already given his Master much to forgive. His case may remind us that we all sin frequently. (Read James 3:2.) Who of us does not need divine forgiveness every single day? For Peter, though, the night was far from over. The worst lay ahead.

Peter’s Worst Failure

11, 12. (a) How did Peter show a measure of courage after Jesus’ arrest? (b) In what way did Peter’s example fall short of what he himself had professed?

11 Jesus reasoned with the mob that if they were looking for him, they should let his apostles go. Peter watched helplessly as the mob bound Jesus. Then Peter fled, as did his fellow apostles.

12 Peter and John stopped in their flight, perhaps near the house of the former High Priest Annas, where Jesus was first taken for questioning. As Jesus was led from there, Peter and John followed but “at a good distance.” ([Matt. 26:58;] John 18:12, 13) Peter was no coward. It surely took a measure of courage to follow at all. The mob was armed, and Peter had already wounded one of them. Still, we do not here see in Peter’s example the kind of loyal love that he himself had professed—a willingness to die by his Master’s side if need be.—[Mark 14:31].

13. What is the only way to follow Christ properly?

13 Like Peter, many today seek to follow Christ “at a good distance”—in such a way that no one else will notice. But as Peter himself later wrote, the only way to follow Christ properly is to stick as close to Him as we can, imitating His example in all things, regardless of the consequences.—Read 1 Peter 2:21.

14. How did Peter pass the nighttime hours during Jesus’ trial?

14 Peter’s cautious steps finally brought him up to the gate of one of Jerusalem’s most imposing mansions. It was the home of Caiaphas, the wealthy and powerful high priest. Such homes were usually built around a courtyard, with a gate in the front. Peter reached the gate and was refused entrance. John, who knew the high priest and was already inside, came and got the doorkeeper to admit Peter. It seems that Peter did not stick close to John; nor did he try to get inside the house to stand at his Master’s side. He stayed in the courtyard, where some slaves and servants were passing the chilly night hours in front of a bright fire, watching as the false witnesses against Jesus paraded in and out of the trial going on inside.—Mark 14:54-57; John 18:15, 16,[18].

^ par. 1 (Luke 22:61) At this the Lord turned and looked straight at Peter, and Peter recalled the statement of the Lord when he had said to him: “Before a rooster crows today, you will disown me three times.”

^ par. 3 (Matt. 18:21, 22) Then Peter came and said to him: “Lord, how many times is my brother to sin against me and am I to forgive him? Up to seven times?” 22 Jesus said to him: “I say to you, not up to seven times, but up to 77 times.

^ par. 4 (1 Cor. 13:4, 5) Love is patient* and kind. Love is not jealous. It does not brag, does not get puffed up, 5 does not behave indecently,* does not look for its own interests, does not become provoked. It does not keep account of the injury.*

Or “long-suffering.”

Or “is not rude.”

Or “of wrongs.”

^ par. 4 (1 John 1:7-9) However, if we are walking in the light as he himself is in the light, we do have fellowship with one another, and the blood of Jesus his Son cleanses us from all sin. 8 If we make the statement, “We have no sin,” we are misleading ourselves and the truth is not in us. 9 If we confess our sins, he is faithful and righteous so as to forgive us our sins and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.

^ par. 6 (John 13:1-17) Now because he knew before the festival of the Passover that his hour had come for him to leave this world and go to the Father, Jesus, having loved his own who were in the world, loved them to the end. 2 The evening meal was going on, and the Devil had already put it into the heart of Judas Is·carʹi·ot, the son of Simon, to betray him. 3 So Jesus, knowing that the Father had given all things into his hands and that he came from God and was going to God, 4 got up from the evening meal and laid aside his outer garments. And taking a towel, he wrapped it around his waist.* 5 After that he put water into a basin and started to wash the feet of the disciples and to dry them off with the towel that was wrapped around him.* 6 Then he came to Simon Peter. He said to him: “Lord, are you washing my feet?” 7 Jesus answered him: “What I am doing you do not understand now, but you will understand after these things.” 8 Peter said to him: “You will certainly never wash my feet.” Jesus answered him: “Unless I wash you, you have no share with me.” 9 Simon Peter said to him: “Lord, wash not only my feet but also my hands and my head.” 10 Jesus said to him: “Whoever has bathed does not need to have more than his feet washed, but is completely clean. And you men are clean, but not all of you.” 11 For he knew the man who was betraying him. This is why he said: “Not all of you are clean.” 12 When, now, he had washed their feet and had put his outer garments on, he again reclined at the table and said to them: “Do you understand what I have done to you? 13 You address me as ‘Teacher’ and ‘Lord,’ and you are correct, for I am such. 14 Therefore, if I, the Lord and Teacher, washed your feet, you also should* wash the feet of one another. 15 For I set the pattern for you, that just as I did to you, you should also do. 16 Most truly I say to you, a slave is not greater than his master, nor is one who is sent greater than the one who sent him. 17 If you know these things, happy you are if you do them.

Or “girded himself.”

Or “with which he was girded.”

Or “you also are under obligation to.”

^ par. 7 (Matt. 26:31-35) Then Jesus said to them: “All of you will be stumbled in connection with me on this night, for it is written: ‘I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep of the flock will be scattered about.’ 32 But after I have been raised up, I will go ahead of you into Galʹi·lee.” 33 But Peter, in response, said to him: “Although all the others are stumbled in connection with you, I will never be stumbled!” 34 Jesus said to him: “Truly I say to you, on this night, before a rooster crows, you will disown me three times.” 35 Peter said to him: “Even if I should have to die with you, I will by no means disown you.” All the other disciples also said the same thing.

^ par. 7 (Mark 14:27-31) And Jesus said to them: “You will all be stumbled, for it is written: ‘I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep will be scattered about.’ 28 But after I have been raised up, I will go ahead of you into Galʹi·lee.” 29 But Peter said to him: “Even if all the others are stumbled, I will not be.” 30 At that Jesus said to him: “Truly I say to you that today, yes, on this very night, before a rooster crows twice, you will disown me three times.” 31 But he kept insisting: “If I have to die with you, I will by no means disown you.” Also, all the others began to say the same thing.

^ par. 7 (Luke 22:24-28) However, there also arose a heated dispute among them over which one of them was considered to be the greatest. 25 But he said to them: “The kings of the nations lord it over them, and those having authority over them are called Benefactors. 26 You, though, are not to be that way. But let the one who is the greatest among you become as the youngest, and the one taking the lead as the one ministering. 27 For which one is greater, the one dining* or the one serving?* Is it not the one dining?* But I am among you as the one serving.* 28 “However, you are the ones who have stuck with me in my trials;

Or “reclining at the table.”

Or “ministering.”

Or “reclining at the table.”

Or “ministering.”

^ par. 7 (John 13:36-38) Simon Peter said to him: “Lord, where are you going?” Jesus answered: “Where I am going, you cannot follow me now, but you will follow later.” 37 Peter said to him: “Lord, why is it I cannot follow you now? I will surrender my life* in your behalf.” 38 Jesus answered: “Will you surrender your life* in my behalf? Most truly I say to you, a rooster will by no means crow until you have disowned me three times.”

Or “soul.”

Or “soul.”

^ par. 8 (Luke 22:32) But I have made supplication for you that your faith may not give out; and you, once you have returned, strengthen your brothers.”

^ par. 9 (Mark 14:32-41) So they came to a spot named Geth·semʹa·ne, and he said to his disciples: “Sit down here while I pray.” 33 And he took Peter and James and John along with him, and he began to feel deeply distressed* and to be greatly troubled. 34 He said to them: “I am* deeply grieved, even to death. Stay here and keep on the watch.” 35 And going a little way forward, he fell to the ground and began praying that, if it were possible, the hour might pass away from him. 36 And he said: “Abba,* Father, all things are possible for you; remove this cup from me. Yet, not what I want, but what you want.” 37 He returned and found them sleeping, and he said to Peter: “Simon, are you sleeping? Did you not have the strength to keep on the watch for one hour? 38 Keep on the watch and pray continually, so that you do not come into temptation. The spirit, of course, is eager,* but the flesh is weak.” 39 And he went away again and prayed, saying the same thing. 40 And he came again and found them sleeping, for their eyes were weighed down, so they did not know what to answer him. 41 And he returned the third time and said to them: “At such a time as this, you are sleeping and resting! It is enough! The hour has come! Look! The Son of man is being betrayed into the hands of sinners.

Or “feel stunned.”

Or “My soul is.”

An Aramaic word meaning “O Father!”

Or “willing.”

^ par. 10 (Matt. 26:47-55) While he was still speaking, look! Judas, one of the Twelve, came and with him a large crowd with swords and clubs, sent from the chief priests and the elders of the people. 48 Now his betrayer had given them a sign, saying: “Whoever it is I kiss, he is the one; take him into custody.” 49 And going straight up to Jesus, he said: “Greetings, Rabbi!” and gave him a tender kiss. 50 But Jesus said to him: “Fellow, for what purpose are you present?” Then they came forward and seized Jesus and took him into custody. 51 But look! one of those with Jesus reached out his hand and drew his sword and struck the slave of the high priest, taking off his ear. 52 Then Jesus said to him: “Return your sword to its place, for all those who take up the sword will perish by the sword. 53 Or do you think that I cannot appeal to my Father to supply me at this moment more than 12 legions of angels? 54 In that case, how would the Scriptures be fulfilled that say it must take place this way?” 55 In that hour Jesus said to the crowds: “Did you come out to arrest me with swords and clubs as against a robber? Day after day I used to sit in the temple teaching, and yet you did not take me into custody.

^ par. 10 (Luke 22:47-51) While he was still speaking, look! a crowd, and the man called Judas, one of the Twelve, was leading them, and he approached Jesus to kiss him. 48 But Jesus said to him: “Judas, are you betraying the Son of man with a kiss?” 49 When those around him saw what was going to happen, they said: “Lord, should we strike with the sword?” 50 One of them even struck the slave of the high priest, taking off his right ear. 51 But in reply Jesus said: “That is enough.” And he touched the ear and healed him.

^ par. 10 (John 18:10, 11) Then Simon Peter, who had a sword, drew it and struck the slave of the high priest, cutting off his right ear. The name of the slave was Malchus. 11 Jesus, however, said to Peter: “Put the sword into its sheath. Should I not drink the cup that the Father has given me?”

^ par. 10 (Jas. 3:2) For we all stumble* many times. If anyone does not stumble in word, he is a perfect man, able to bridle also his whole body.

Or “make mistakes.”

^ par. 12 (Matt. 26:58) But Peter kept following him from a good distance, as far as the courtyard of the high priest, and after going inside, he sat with the house attendants to see the outcome.

^ par. 12 (John 18:12, 13) Then the soldiers and the military commander and the officers of the Jews seized* Jesus and bound him. 13 They led him first to Anʹnas, for he was the father-in-law of Caʹia·phas, who was high priest that year.

Or “arrested.”

^ par. 12 (Mark 14:31) But he kept insisting: “If I have to die with you, I will by no means disown you.” Also, all the others began to say the same thing.

^ par. 13 (1 Pet. 2:21) In fact, to this course you were called, because even Christ suffered for you, leaving a model for you to follow his steps closely.

^ par. 14 (Mark 14:54-57) But Peter, from a good distance, followed him as far as into the courtyard of the high priest; and he was sitting together with the house attendants and warming himself before a bright fire. 55 Now the chief priests and the entire Sanʹhe·drin were looking for testimony against Jesus in order to put him to death, but they were not finding any. 56 Many, indeed, were giving false witness against him, but their testimonies were not in agreement. 57 Also, certain ones were standing up and bearing false witness against him, saying:

^ par. 14 (John 18:15, 16) Now Simon Peter, as well as another disciple, was following Jesus. That disciple was known to the high priest, and he went with Jesus into the courtyard of the high priest, 16 but Peter was standing outside at the door.* So the other disciple, who was known to the high priest, went out and spoke to the doorkeeper and brought Peter in.

Or “entrance.”

^ par. 14 (John 18:18) Now the slaves and the officers were standing around a charcoal fire they had made, because it was cold and they were warming themselves. Peter also was standing with them and warming himself.

^ ***snnw song 144 It Means Their Life***

Song 144

It Means Their Life

Download:

Lyrics Only

Lead Sheet

(Ezekiel 3:17-19)

In this year of goodwill

by our God, all need to hear

That the day of his anger

will come, and it is near.

(CHORUS)

It means their life, but not just theirs;

It means our own life as well.

It means their life if they obey,

So all the nations we must tell;

We must tell.

There’s a message to preach,

so we spread it all abroad.

We invite all to come and

be reconciled to God.

(CHORUS)

It means their life, but not just theirs;

It means our own life as well.

It means their life if they obey,

So all the nations we must tell;

We must tell.

(BRIDGE)

It’s urgent, it’s important,

That people listen, learn, and live.

We tell them, and we teach them;

Life-giving truth we freely give.

(CHORUS)

It means their life, but not just theirs;

It means our own life as well.

It means their life if they obey,

So all the nations we must tell;

We must tell.

(See also 2 Chron. 36:15;[Isa. 61:2;][Ezek. 33:6;] 2 Thess. 1:8.)

^ (Ezek. 3:17-19) “Son of man, I have appointed you as a watchman to the house of Israel; and when you hear a word from my mouth, you must warn them from me. 18 When I say to someone wicked, ‘You will surely die,’ but you do not warn him, and you fail to speak in order to warn the wicked one to turn from his wicked course so that he may stay alive, he will die for his error because he is wicked, but I will ask his blood back from you.* 19 But if you warn someone wicked and he does not turn back from his wickedness and from his wicked course, he will die for his error, but you will certainly save your own life.*

Or “I will hold you accountable for his blood.”

Or “soul.”

^ (2 Chron. 36:15) Jehovah the God of their forefathers kept warning them by means of his messengers, warning them again and again, because he felt compassion for his people and for his dwelling place.

^ (Isa. 61:2) To proclaim the year of Jehovah’s goodwill* And the day of vengeance of our God, To comfort all who mourn,

Or “favor.”

^ (Ezek. 33:6) “‘But if the watchman sees the sword coming and he does not blow the horn and the people receive no warning and a sword comes and takes the life* of one of them, that person will die for his own error, but I will ask his blood back from the watchman.’*

Or “soul.”

Or “I will hold the watchman accountable for his blood.”

^ (2 Thess. 1:8) in a flaming fire, as he brings vengeance on those who do not know God and those who do not obey the good news about our Lord Jesus.

^ (Pss. 110:0-118:29) Of David. A melody. 110 Jehovah declared to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand Until I place your enemies as a stool for your feet.”  2 Jehovah will extend the scepter of your power out of Zion, saying: “Go subduing in the midst of your enemies.”  3 Your people will offer themselves willingly on the day of your military force.* In splendid holiness, from the womb of the dawn, You have your company of young men just like dewdrops.  4 Jehovah has sworn an oath, and he will not change his mind:* “You are a priest forever In the manner of Mel·chizʹe·dek!”  5 Jehovah will be at your right hand; He will crush kings on the day of his anger.  6 He will execute judgment against* the nations; He will fill the land with dead bodies. He will crush the leader* of a vast land.*  7 He* will drink from the stream along the road. Therefore, he will hold his head high.

111 Praise Jah!* I will praise Jehovah with all my heart In the assembled group of upright ones and in the congregation.  2 The works of Jehovah are great; They are studied by all those finding pleasure in them.  3 His activity is glorious and splendid, And his righteousness endures forever.  4 He causes his wonderful works to be remembered. Jehovah is compassionate* and merciful.  5 Food he gives to those fearing him. He remembers his covenant forever.  6 He has revealed to his people his powerful works By giving them the inheritance of the nations.  7 The works of his hands are truth and justice; Trustworthy are all his orders.  8 They are always reliable,* now and forever; They are made in truth and righteousness.  9 He has given redemption to his people. He commanded that his covenant should last forever. His name is holy and awe-inspiring. 10 The fear of Jehovah is the beginning of wisdom. All those observing his orders* show good insight. His praise endures forever.

112 Praise Jah!* Happy is the man who fears Jehovah, Who takes great pleasure in his commandments.  2 His descendants will be mighty in the earth, And the generation of the upright will be blessed.  3 Wealth and riches are in his house, And his righteousness continues forever.  4 To the upright he shines like a light in the darkness. He is compassionate* and merciful and righteous.  5 It goes well for the man who generously* lends. He conducts his affairs with justice.  6 He will never be shaken. The righteous will be remembered forever.  7 He will not fear bad news. His heart is steadfast, trusting in Jehovah.  8 His heart is unshakable;* he is not afraid; In the end he will look in triumph on his adversaries.  9 He has distributed widely;* he has given to the poor. His righteousness continues forever. His own strength* will be exalted with glory. 10 The wicked one will see and be upset. He will grind his teeth and melt away. The desires of the wicked will perish.

113 Praise Jah!* Offer praise, you servants of Jehovah, Praise the name of Jehovah.  2 May Jehovah’s name be praised From now on and forever.  3 From the rising of the sun to its setting, Let Jehovah’s name be praised.  4 Jehovah is high above all the nations; His glory is above the heavens.  5 Who is like Jehovah our God, The one who dwells* on high?  6 He stoops down to look on heaven and earth,  7 Raising the lowly from the dust. He lifts up the poor from the ash heap*  8 In order to make him sit with nobles, With the nobles of his people.  9 He gives the barren woman a home As a happy mother with children.* Praise Jah!*

114 When Israel went out of Egypt, The house of Jacob from a people speaking a foreign language,  2 Judah became his sanctuary,* Israel, his dominion.  3 The sea saw it and fled; The Jordan turned back.  4 The mountains skipped about like rams, The hills, like lambs.  5 What made you flee, O sea? Why, O Jordan, did you turn back?  6 Why did you skip about like rams, O mountains, Like lambs, O hills?  7 Tremble, O earth, because of the Lord, Because of the God of Jacob,  8 Who turns the rock into a reedy pool of water, The flinty rock into springs of water.

115 Not to us, O Jehovah, not to us,* But to your name give glory Because of your loyal love and your faithfulness.  2 Why should the nations say: “Where is their God?”  3 Our God is in the heavens; He does whatever he pleases.  4 Their idols are silver and gold, The work of human hands.  5 A mouth they have, but they cannot speak; Eyes, but they cannot see;  6 Ears they have, but they cannot hear; A nose, but they cannot smell;  7 Hands they have, but they cannot feel; Feet, but they cannot walk; They make no sound with their throat.  8 The people who make them will become just like them, As will all those who trust in them.  9 O Israel, trust in Jehovah —He is their help and their shield. 10 O house of Aaron, trust in Jehovah —He is their help and their shield. 11 You who fear Jehovah, trust in Jehovah —He is their help and their shield. 12 Jehovah remembers us and will bless; He will bless the house of Israel; He will bless the house of Aaron. 13 He will bless those who fear Jehovah, The small as well as the great. 14 Jehovah will give you an increase, To you and your children.* 15 May you be blessed by Jehovah, The Maker of heaven and earth. 16 As for the heavens, they belong to Jehovah, But the earth he has given to the sons of men. 17 The dead do not praise Jah; Nor do any who go down into the silence of death.* 18 But we will praise Jah From now on and forever. Praise Jah!*

116 I love Jehovah Because he hears* my voice, my pleas for help.  2 For he inclines his ear* to me, And I will call on him as long as I live.*  3 The ropes of death encircled me; The Grave had me in its grip.* I was overcome by distress and grief.  4 But I called on the name of Jehovah: “O Jehovah, rescue me!”*  5 Jehovah is compassionate* and righteous; Our God is merciful.  6 Jehovah is guarding the inexperienced. I was brought low, and he saved me.  7 Let my soul* rest once again, For Jehovah has dealt kindly with me.  8 You have rescued me* from death, My eye from tears, my foot from stumbling.  9 I will walk before Jehovah in the land of the living. 10 I had faith, for I spoke; I was greatly afflicted. 11 As for me, I panicked and said: “Every man is a liar.” 12 With what will I repay Jehovah For all the good he has done for me? 13 I will take up the cup of salvation,* And I will call on the name of Jehovah. 14 I will pay my vows to Jehovah In the presence of all his people. 15 Costly* in the eyes of Jehovah Is the death of his loyal ones. 16 I beg you, O Jehovah, For I am your servant. I am your servant, the son of your slave girl. You have freed me from my bonds. 17 I will offer to you the sacrifice of thanksgiving; I will call on the name of Jehovah. 18 I will pay my vows to Jehovah In the presence of all his people, 19 In the courtyards of the house of Jehovah, In your midst, O Jerusalem. Praise Jah!*

117 Praise Jehovah, all you nations; Glorify him, all you peoples.*  2 For his loyal love toward us is great; The faithfulness of Jehovah endures forever. Praise Jah!*

118 Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; His loyal love endures forever.  2 Let Israel now say: “His loyal love endures forever.”  3 Let those of the house of Aaron now say: “His loyal love endures forever.”  4 Let those fearing Jehovah now say: “His loyal love endures forever.”  5 I called on Jah* in my distress; Jah answered and brought me into a place of safety.*  6 Jehovah is on my side; I will not be afraid. What can man do to me?  7 Jehovah is on my side as my helper;* I will look in triumph on those who hate me.  8 It is better to take refuge in Jehovah Than to trust in humans.  9 It is better to take refuge in Jehovah Than to trust in princes. 10 All the nations surrounded me, But in the name of Jehovah, I warded them off. 11 They surrounded me, yes, I was completely surrounded, But in the name of Jehovah, I warded them off. 12 They surrounded me like bees, But they were extinguished as quickly as a fire among thorns. In the name of Jehovah, I warded them off. 13 I was pushed hard* to make me fall, But Jehovah helped me. 14 Jah is my shelter and my strength, And he has become my salvation. 15 The sound of rejoicing and salvation* Is in the tents of the righteous. The right hand of Jehovah is demonstrating its power. 16 The right hand of Jehovah is exalting itself; The right hand of Jehovah is demonstrating its power. 17 I will not die, no, I will live, In order to declare the works of Jah. 18 Jah disciplined me severely, But he did not hand me over to death. 19 Open to me the gates of righteousness; I will enter them and praise Jah. 20 This is the gate of Jehovah. The righteous will enter through it. 21 I will praise you, for you answered me And you became my salvation. 22 The stone that the builders rejected Has become the chief cornerstone.* 23 This has come from Jehovah; It is wonderful in our eyes. 24 This is the day that Jehovah has made; We will be joyful and rejoice in it. 25 Jehovah, save us, please, we beg! Jehovah, grant us victory, please! 26 Blessed is the one who comes in the name of Jehovah; We bless you from the house of Jehovah. 27 Jehovah is God; He gives us light. Join in the festival procession with branches in hand, Up to the horns of the altar. 28 You are my God, and I will praise you; My God, I will exalt you. 29 Give thanks to Jehovah, for he is good; His loyal love endures forever.

Or “on the day your army mobilizes.”

Or “he will feel no regret.”

Or “among.”

Lit., “head.”

Or “of the entire earth.”

Referring to “my Lord” in vs. 1.

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “gracious.”

Or “well-founded.”

Lit., “them.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “gracious.”

Or “graciously.”

Or “resolute; steady.”

Or “generously.”

Lit., “horn.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “sits enthroned.”

Or possibly, “garbage dump.”

Lit., “sons.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “holy place.”

Or “To us belongs nothing, O Jehovah, to us belongs nothing.”

Lit., “sons.”

Lit., “into silence.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or possibly, “I love because Jehovah hears.”

Or “bends down to listen.”

Lit., “in my days.”

Lit., “The distresses of Sheol found me.”

Or “my soul.”

Or “gracious.”

See Glossary.

Or “my soul.”

Or “grand salvation.”

Lit., “Precious.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “clans.”

Or “Hallelujah!” “Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

“Jah” is a shortened form of the name Jehovah.

Or “a roomy place.”

Or possibly, “along with those helping me.”

Or possibly, “You pushed me hard.”

Or “victory.”

Lit., “the head of the corner.”